<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts | Alberto Acerbi</title>
    <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://acerbialberto.com/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Posts</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://acerbialberto.com/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Posts</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>A few thoughts on cultural attraction</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2020_cultural_attraction/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2020_cultural_attraction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./featured.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I am finishing the work on the submission of a modelling paper about cultural attraction theory (the preprint, quite different from the current version, is &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/vjcq3/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), I thought I could go back after a while to a darling of this blog. Writing down these few musings is mostly useful for me, but perhaps they can be interesting for the people that already know the diatribe - the post is hardly a crowd-pleaser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, my general position is more or less stable on what I write five (!) years ago together with Alex Mesoudi (&lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10539-015-9490-2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, even if I have a different opinion on many specific points) and, more recently, in the first half of the &amp;ldquo;Transmitting and sharing&amp;rdquo; chapter of my &lt;a href=&#34;https://global.oup.com/academic/product/cultural-evolution-in-the-digital-age-9780198835943?cc=gb&amp;amp;lang=en&amp;amp;&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;book&lt;/a&gt;. The points carried forward by cultural attraction theory are valuable and overlooked in much cultural evolution research, so it is important to pay attention to them. Convergent transformation can, as much as faithful copying, bring about cultural stability. Explaining the diffusion of a trait with &lt;em&gt;culture&lt;/em&gt; - a tendency to copy others faithfully - is to assume what requires itself an explanation. We copy the majority, the successful, the elders: until we do not. Individual and social learning are not two different processes, and, yes, I now think that culture &amp;ldquo;is a property, not a thing&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other side, hi-fi copying is important in some domains, and there is a limit to what convergent transformations can achieve. Cultural transmission does allow for the diffusion of &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; information that can not be reconstructed. Cultural attraction people are correct, technically, when they say that high-fidelity transmission is a special case of attraction, with reconstruction equal to zero, or something analogous. However, I believe that the advantages linked to the generality of a theory depend on what we are trying to explain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My position is a bit annoying as I guess I end up to slightly irritating both camps, but, despite what you heard on Twitter, academics are a bunch of nice people, and I tend to be able to work with both the factions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, I became more and more convinced that the main reason for the disagreement resides in the fact that different people ask different &amp;ldquo;deep&amp;rdquo; questions about culture. Thom Scott-Phillips says something similar &lt;a href=&#34;https://thomscottphillips.files.wordpress.com/2016/05/scott-phillips-2016-review-of-lewens.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; (at the end of section 2). Many cultural evolutionists are interested to explain what is so special in humans, and the answer is, correctly: culture, as they define it. Many cultural attractionists (?), instead, are interested to explain why some cultural traits are succesfull, given the state of the world and of its inhabitants. Again, I tend to share the latter interest but, of course, both questions are legitimate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A similar way to put it is that many cultural attractionists are humanists (as in researchers working in the humanities) or social scientists that become frustrated with non-scientific explanations of culture, and pushed interdisciplinarity towards hard sciences. Many cultural evolutionists are instead natural scientists that &amp;ldquo;discovered&amp;rdquo; that culture is important to explain human and, up to a point, non-human behaviour, and pushed  interdisciplinarity the other way around. This does not need to be literally true - people actually following the exact career path - but it seems to me it catches an interesting difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, and perhaps most controversial, cultural attraction theory stresses (recently with more emphasis) that factors of attraction are multifaceted and, in particular, not only cognitive. Again, for the internal consistency of the theory, this is perfectly right. Personally, I met cultural attraction theory (which was called, at the time, &amp;ldquo;epidemiology of representations&amp;rdquo;) reading Dan Sperber&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Explaining-Culture-Naturalistic-Dan-Sperber/dp/0631200452&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Explaining Culture&lt;/a&gt;, and this changed my scientific life (and, as a consequence, if I look at it from today&amp;rsquo;s perspective, my life tout-court). While the book is the classic source for the &amp;ldquo;factors of attraction can be psychological and ecological&amp;rdquo; motto, it is also home of chapters on culture and mental (massive) modularity, anthropology and psychology, etc. For me, at least, there was a clear message that pan-human cognitive similarities constrain the forms that cultures can take, and contribute to explaining them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Independently on how these cognitive similarities are implemented and on how they arise, I still believe that cultural attraction theory is more &lt;em&gt;interesting&lt;/em&gt; if this message is true, and I would not shy away from that. For reconstruction and convergent transformation to provide satisfying explanations, they should be reconducted to something else, whatever this will be. Of course, the importance of these constraints is variable and domain-dependent, so that in some cases we should prefer reconstruction-based explanations, and in others preservative-transmission-based explanations, but that is, I believe, a stimulating empirical problem for cultural evolutionists.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sichuan food and the transience of traditions</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2019_sichuan/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2019_sichuan/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of my secret passion (or not-so-secret, if you know me a bit) is cooking. Last weekend was devoted to the new edition of Fuchsia Dunlop&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Food-Sichuan-Fuchsia-Dunlop/dp/1324004835&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;The Food of Sichuan&lt;/a&gt;, widely considered as one of the best western-accessible resource on the topic. If you want to know, I cooked &amp;lsquo;Strange Flavour&amp;rsquo; Bang Bang Chicken and Fish-Fragrant Aubergines. (Both will need much improvement&amp;mdash;for example I ended up burning the peanuts while deep-frying them&amp;hellip;&amp;mdash; so if I ever happen to offer to cook you Sichuan food, ask for my only piece of resistance so far, the classic Mapo Tofu.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book has a fairly good historical introduction, where a few things caught my eye. Sure, the cuisine of Sichuan is renowned for its variety, and for the ability to combine several ingredients to create distinctive flavour combinations, but at the end of the day many of us will appreciate it for the signature &amp;ldquo;hot-and-numbing&amp;rdquo; taste given by the combination of Sichuan pepper (in the picture below) and abundant serving of chillies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./featured.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, at odd with my intuitive idea of a millennia-old culinary tradition, chillies obviously &amp;ldquo;only reached China in the late sixteenth century [&amp;hellip;] probably brought to China by Portuguese traders&amp;rdquo;. The &lt;em&gt;barbarian peppers&lt;/em&gt; were considered an ornamental plant: &amp;ldquo;it would be at least another century before the use of chillies to flavour food was documented&amp;rdquo;. According to this account, &amp;ldquo;it wasn&amp;rsquo;t until the reign of the Jiaqing Emperor (1796-1820)&amp;rdquo; that the plant was established as a local crop in Sichuan, that is, two centuries ago. Deep-frying, which I associated intimately with Chinese cuisine, seems even more recent in Sichuan: &amp;ldquo;an interest in deep-frying [&amp;hellip;] is said to have come from Americans in 1930s Chongqing.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This reminded me of my previous research about Swedish food. (Yes, when living in Stockholm I had a blog about Swedish food, alas only in Italian, but you can have a look at some popular post, for example &lt;a href=&#34;https://cucinasvedeseperitaliani.wordpress.com/2010/09/08/surstromming/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://cucinasvedeseperitaliani.wordpress.com/2010/04/20/kottbullar/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.) Many classic recipes of the Swedish traditions were, in fact, the results of a few successful recipe books that appeared after the Second World War and canonised the &lt;em&gt;Husmanskost&lt;/em&gt;, i.e. the &amp;ldquo;traditional&amp;rdquo; home-cooked Swedish food. Traditional is in quotation marks not by chance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another example is an Italian classic: &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carbonara&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;pasta alla carbonara&lt;/a&gt;. Some even speculate that it was invented to please American soldiers during the liberation of Rome in 1944, by reminding them of their eggs and bacon breakfasts. Whatever this is true or not (it looks too good to be true though), the recipe is never mentioned before the Second World War, suggesting a recent origin. By the way: no onions and no cream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe many other examples can be found for &amp;ldquo;traditional&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;classic&amp;rdquo; dishes. This is of course nothing new. Another of my not-so-secrets is that I had a classic anthropological formation, and, in socio-cultural anthropology, the idea that traditions are often &lt;a href=&#34;https://books.google.co.uk/books/about/The_Invention_of_Tradition.html?id=sfvnNdVY3KIC&amp;amp;source=kp_book_description&amp;amp;redir_esc=y&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;invented&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://books.google.co.uk/books/about/Imagined_Communities.html?id=nQ9jXXJV-vgC&amp;amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;amp;source=kp_read_button&amp;amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;amp;q&amp;amp;f=false&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;imagined&lt;/a&gt; is common currency. In &lt;a href=&#34;https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=kSukCgAAQBAJ&amp;amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;amp;dq=how+traditions+live+and+day&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ved=0ahUKEwiRkqKZu9DlAhWtTxUIHY53AtkQ6AEIKTAA#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=how%20traditions%20live%20and%20day&amp;amp;f=false&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;How Traditions Live and Die&lt;/a&gt; Olivier Morin makes an analogous point using the example of Highland&amp;rsquo;s clans tartans, that were single-handedly created by a fabric producer in the 19th century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other traditions may be indeed millennia old. For example, Sara Graça da Silva and Jamie Tehrani used &lt;a href=&#34;https://royalsocietypublishing.org/doi/10.1098/rsos.150645&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;phylogenetic methods&lt;/a&gt; to analyse the relationships between folktales in Indo-European-speaking societies, and they claim to have found &amp;ldquo;evidence that one tale (‘The Smith and the Devil’) can be traced back to the Bronze Age&amp;rdquo;. The point is: we should be wary of considering traditions as, by-default, ancient and robust (perhaps because of an inborn tendency to copy others). Some may be, and others may be not. I wonder whether cultural evolutionists, beside Morin&amp;rsquo;s book and a less recent, and not very well-known I believe, book from Pascal Boyer (&lt;a href=&#34;https://books.google.co.uk/books/about/Tradition_as_Truth_and_Communication.html?id=Wuf2PXR1pBgC&amp;amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;amp;source=kp_read_button&amp;amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;amp;q&amp;amp;f=false&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Tradition as Truth and Communication&lt;/a&gt;), have explored in detail the topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A more general reflection: a backbone of cultural evolution is population thinking, which implies that culture is an emergent, population-level, product of individual interactions, and individual interactions are where the causal magic happens (at least, this is how I read it). From this perspective, it looks natural to think to cultural traditions in a non-essentialist way: they are just the temporary result of individual interactions, looked at on a certain zoom level. However, sometimes &amp;ldquo;culture&amp;rdquo; is essentialised and used itself as an explanation, as in &amp;ldquo;we do it &lt;em&gt;because of our culture&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;. These kinds of explanations are more and more present when reporting and justifying transcultural experiments (a good criticism of this notion of culture is in &lt;a href=&#34;https://brill.com/view/journals/jocc/18/3-4/article-p231_1.xml&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this paper&lt;/a&gt; from Lawrence Hirschfeld). Transcultural experiments are important and necessary, but we need to be cautious when we say that &amp;ldquo;eastern people&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;the Aka&amp;rdquo;, or any other experimental group, behave differently because of &amp;ldquo;culture&amp;rdquo;. It could be, but it could also be that many, interrelated, possibly short-lived, traditions create a specific situation, and it would be interesting to be able to disentangle these possibilities. Anthropologists (in anthropology the WEIRD problem is as a minumum a century-old one: a true tradition!) have recognised this problem, but the solutions proposed have not been, in my opinion, particularly successful, but this may be material for another post.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RStudio on Amazon Web Services</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2019_aws_rstudio/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2019_aws_rstudio/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Here a situation that may have occurred to some of you: your R script (a model analysing a big dataset, a simulation where you test many parameter combinations) needs hours to run. If you are lucky, you may have access to a cluster, or a remote computer, where you can run your script. All sorted. Sometimes - as it happens to me now, running &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/albertoacerbi/oranzees&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; individual-based model - you do not have this option. However, I just found out that launching your &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rstudio.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;RStudio&lt;/a&gt; script on Amazon Web Service (&lt;a href=&#34;https://aws.amazon.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;AWS&lt;/a&gt;) is quite easy (and it is free).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the information needed is scattered on the web, I put together a short tutorial. If you do not trust me, most material comes from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.louisaslett.com/RStudio_AMI/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, but it is not  explained step-by-step, some information are possibly not relevant for a non-expert (as myself) and, mostly, the AWS interface has been changed from when the page was written. So, follow this short instructions, and you can close your laptop and have your script running for you somewhere else!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-by-step-tutorial&#34;&gt;Step-by-step tutorial&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;1-create-an-aws-account&#34;&gt;(1) Create an AWS account&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, we need an AWS account. Amazon Web Service &amp;ldquo;provides on-demand cloud computing platforms to individuals, companies, and governments, on a metered pay-as-you-go basis&amp;rdquo;. However, some products - including the one we will use - are free. Let&amp;rsquo;s go to &lt;a href=&#34;https://aws.amazon.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;the AWS webpage&lt;/a&gt; and create the account. It asks us some personal data, including the address and, annoyingly, a credit card number, in case we use products that are not free, or exceed the usage limits. (In any case, Amazon probably already knows our credit card number.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;2-launch-the-ami&#34;&gt;(2) Launch the AMI&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we want to run our script in the Amazon cloud. Ideally, we would like to run it on a (virtual) computer with RStudio installed. Luckily, someone already did this. Go to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.louisaslett.com/RStudio_AMI/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; webpage and choose one of the &lt;em&gt;AMI&lt;/em&gt; on the right of the page, according to the geographic location (in my case: EU West, London).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amazon_Machine_Image&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; is the Wikipedia page about AMI (Amazon Machine Image) if you want to know more, but you do not need to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./01.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;3-choose-the-instance&#34;&gt;(3) Choose the instance&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we landed on the AWS page of the AMI we choose. The &amp;ldquo;Free Tier&amp;rdquo; instance is already selected, so we do not have to do anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./02.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;4-configure-the-security&#34;&gt;(4) Configure the security&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To access to Rstudio in the cloud with our browser we need to configure the security in the right way. Thus, before launching the instance, we need to go on the tab 6 (&amp;ldquo;Configure Security Group&amp;rdquo;), and select &amp;ldquo;HTTP&amp;rdquo; from the drop-down menu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./03.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;5-review-and-launch&#34;&gt;(5) Review and launch&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We click on &amp;ldquo;Review and Launch&amp;rdquo; and we land on this page. Check that the &amp;ldquo;AMI details&amp;rdquo; are correct and then click &amp;ldquo;Launch&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./04.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;6-select-the-key-pair&#34;&gt;(6) Select the key pair&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before launching the instance, we are asked to select a key pair. From the drop-down menu we choose &amp;ldquo;Proceed without a key pair&amp;rdquo;, and check the box below. Now we can click &amp;ldquo;Launch Instances&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./05.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;7-the-instance-is-launched&#34;&gt;(7) The instance is launched!&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All good. Click on the ID of the instance (it will be different from the one shown here), to access it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./06.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;8-connecting-to-rstudio&#34;&gt;(8) Connecting to RStudio&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the console of our instance. After some time, the &amp;ldquo;Instance State&amp;rdquo; will be on &amp;ldquo;running&amp;rdquo;. We need to copy the Public DNS, and paste it in the address bar of another page our browser to access our instance of RStudio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./07.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;9-starting-rstudio&#34;&gt;(9) Starting RStudio&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a while this page should appear (if not, we need to wait a bit an retry, it may need a few minutes). The username is &amp;ldquo;rstudio&amp;rdquo;, and the password is our &amp;ldquo;Instance ID&amp;rdquo; (see the previous screenshot, on the left side of the Public DNS).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./08.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;10-virtual-rstudio&#34;&gt;(10) Virtual RStudio&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If all went well, we should see the familiar screen below. There is a &lt;strong&gt;Welcome.R&lt;/strong&gt; script. There are two things we should do (which are well explained in the script). First, it is advisable to change our password, from the &amp;ldquo;Instance ID&amp;rdquo; to something else of our choice. To do this, we first load the package included (&lt;code&gt;library(&amp;quot;RStudioAMI&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;), and use the function &lt;code&gt;passwd()&lt;/code&gt;, which asks for old and new password. The second thing is that we can link our Dropbox so that we can load directly our script, using the function &lt;code&gt;linkDropbox()&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./09.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;11-authorising-dropbox&#34;&gt;(11) Authorising Dropbox&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After few seconds, a message on the RStudio console (&amp;ldquo;Please visit the following URL in your browser now to link the server to your Dropbox account:&amp;ldquo;) will prompt us to authorise the cloud computer to connect to our Dropbox, landing on this page. We need to click on &amp;ldquo;Connect&amp;rdquo;. (We will also receive a mail from Dropbox asking to confirm.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./10.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;12-excluding-folders-from-dropbox-sync&#34;&gt;(12) Excluding folders from Dropbox sync&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, a &amp;ldquo;Dropbox&amp;rdquo; folder appears in the &amp;ldquo;Files&amp;rdquo; tab of RStudio. We do not want to sync &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; our Dropbox folder in the cloud. When our Dropbox folders start to appear in RStudio, we can use the function &lt;code&gt;excludeSyncDropbox(&amp;quot;*&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt; to exclude all files to be synced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./11.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;13-syncing-what-we-need&#34;&gt;(13) Syncing what we need&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine the script we need to run is called &lt;strong&gt;scriptThatRunsForHours.R&lt;/strong&gt;. A good idea is to create a folder in our dropbox - let&amp;rsquo;s call it &amp;ldquo;AWS_RStudio&amp;rdquo; and put the script in that folder. Now we can ask to synchronise only this folder, using the function &lt;code&gt;includeSyncDropbox(&amp;quot;AWS_RStudio&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;. Now we can open our script as we would do in our local RStudio and do whatever we need to do with it, including running it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./12.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;14-going-back-the-script&#34;&gt;(14) Going back the script&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the script runs, we can close our browser, and just forget about it. To go back to our instance, we go again on the AWS webpage, we login to our account, and we click the EC2 service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./13.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should have one instance running. Clicking on it, we are back to the instance console (see point 8), from where, following again points 8 and 9, we go again on our virtual RStudio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./14.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;15-terminate-the-instance&#34;&gt;(15) Terminate the instance&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the script is finished, and if we do not have anything else to run, from the instance console we can &amp;ldquo;terminate&amp;rdquo; the instance, as shown below. All done!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./15.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;limitations&#34;&gt;Limitations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This quick tutorial is intended as a very basic shortcut to run RStudio on AWS. The pros are that it works, that it should have you run a R script in a handful of minutes and that it does not require any technical knowledge. On the other hand, there are some obvious limitations (all suggestions are more than welcome!):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have not been able to write output files on my local computer. While the modifications of the scripts I made in the instance are saved on my Dropbox, the output files, produced with &lt;code&gt;write_csv(&amp;quot;myLongScriptOutput.csv&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt; are not. They appear in the &amp;ldquo;Files&amp;rdquo; tab in the virtual RStudio and I manually export them from there to my computer (&amp;ldquo;More&amp;gt;Export&amp;rdquo;). This is not very elegant.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The virtual RStudio comes with some packages pre-installed. In particular, the &amp;ldquo;tidyverse&amp;rdquo; package, which is the only one I needed, is there. I did not try to install any other package, so I do not know whether this will work straightforwardly or not.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The most annoying aspect is that my script runs &lt;em&gt;slower&lt;/em&gt; in the cloud that on my laptop! (Around twice slower.) This is probably due to the fact that I am using a &amp;ldquo;Free Tier&amp;rdquo; instance, so I would need to pay for more computational power. So, this is a viable option if you are not exactly in a rush, unless someone finds a solution to this.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finally, I just scratched the surface of what one can do (again the goal was to provide a fast and easy solution). I do not have idea of how the majority of the options present in the instance console work, and I did not mention few for which I have some idea. (For example, how to monitor your script, or how to pair your instance with a ssh key so to access it directly from terminal, see point 6).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, comments and feedback welcome, and happy to know about better solutions!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vaccine hesitancy is not correlated with social media penetration at country-level in Europe</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2019_wellcome/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2019_wellcome/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Wellcome Trust has recently (yesterday) released the 2018 &lt;a href=&#34;https://wellcome.ac.uk/reports/wellcome-global-monitor/2018&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Global Monitor&lt;/a&gt;, a 140,000 people survey on how ‘people around the world think and feel about science and major health challenges’. Among the many interesting pieces of information, not surprisingly, attitudes towards vaccinations are starting to be widely discussed in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/society/2019/jun/19/survey-shows-crisis-of-confidence-in-vaccines-in-parts-of-europe&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;press&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first important thing to notice, as the Wellcome Trust correctly does, is that ‘worldwide, 79% of people agree that vaccines are safe and 84% agree that they are effective’ and ‘92% of parents worldwide said that their children have received a vaccine to prevent them from getting childhood diseases .’ Whatever we may think, the majority of people around the world rightly believe that vaccines are good. Of course, there is a minority of people, especially in western countries, that is less convinced of that. Citing again the Wellcome Trust, ‘In France, one in three people disagree that vaccines are safe, the highest percentage for any country worldwide’. The France figure is, however, one of few outliers, also for western countries, where the averages of people disagreeing that vaccines are safe are around 10%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, that one out of ten persons in western countries could think as such is worrying. Not surprisingly, social media has been identified as one of the culprits of this situation, and I bet that, following the Wellcome Trust survey, the trend will continue (I already found one article &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.independent.co.uk/news/health/anti-vaxx-vaccination-myth-poll-europe-pro-nature-birth-a8964441.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). Out of curiosity, I correlated the Wellcome trust data with recent data on social media penetration/usage in Europe, and they are not correlated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./social_media.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I was on it, I also correlated the data with the importance of religion..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./religion.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;the trust in science&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./science.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;and the GDP pro capita&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./gdp.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naturally, this is a very basic analysis. It could be for example that, within countries, people that are sceptical of vaccines use more social media than others. That anti-vaxx information spreads effectively in social media is not surprising. There are &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cell.com/trends/cognitive-sciences/fulltext/S1364-6613(15)00197-7?_returnURL=https%3A%2F%2Flinkinghub.elsevier.com%2Fretrieve%2Fpii%2FS1364661315001977%3Fshowall%3Dtrue&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;many reasons&lt;/a&gt; why anti-vaccination beliefs are easy to spread (and, conversely, it could be more difficult with pro-vaccination beliefs). Information around vaccines is psychologically attractive, involving potentially disgust and counterintuitive concepts that, coupled with a possible negative bias, make fearmongering on vaccines a good topic for &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41599-019-0224-y&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;online misinformation&lt;/a&gt;. All of this, however, is not a prerogative of digital social media (where correct, pro-vaccine, information &lt;a href=&#34;https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jama/fullarticle/2670250&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;also spreads effectively&lt;/a&gt;), and vaccine hesitancy is &lt;a href=&#34;http://sethmnookin.com/the-panic-virus/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;as old as vaccines themselves&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, each time you hear someone saying, or writing, that anti-vaccination beliefs are linked to social media you should be sceptical. At least: it is not obvious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are interested, all the technical stuff (data, R script, what I coded exactly as “vaccine hesitancy”, “social media penetration”, etc.) are in &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/albertoacerbi/vaccines-wellcome&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; GitHub repository.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The ordeal simulation hypothesis</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2019_ordeal_simulation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2019_ordeal_simulation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You have probably heard the adagio that “man bites dog”, and not “dog bites man”, makes for a good piece of news: unusual, exceptional, events are better stories than everyday occurrences. Hidden behind the surface, however, there is another message that seems so obvious we do not even think about it: both examples are negative events. “Dog wins the lottery” would probably be a good piece of news too, but it is not mentioned. That negative news – and possibly negative narratives in general – are more attractive than positive ones is a bit of a cliché, but it supported by much research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interesting case-study is false news. By definition, they do not need to describe real facts, so they can exploit our preferences in an almost unconstrained way. In a content analysis of a small sample of articles categorised as online misinformation, I found that &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41599-019-0224-y&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;negative articles where around five times more numerous than positive articles&lt;/a&gt;. It is not just about news. English-language fiction became consistently more negative &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/02699931.2016.1260528&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;in the last two centuries&lt;/a&gt;, and English-language song lyrics did the same &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/preprints/socarxiv/3j6wx/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;in the last fifty years&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And why, yet, this should be the case? There are many possible explanations: one is that the stories we tell each other are simulations. As much as pilots can exercise their flight skills in dangerous situations safe from risks in a simulator, the pleasure we experience when we enjoy narratives would be rooted in the possibility of exercise our skills in an analogous safe environment. The next time you are in the woods you should be suspicious of the wolf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From this perspective, it makes sense that negative events are predominant in stories: it is worst to arrive unprepared to a negative event than to a positive one. Some &lt;a href=&#34;https://global.oup.com/academic/product/9780190666514&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;research&lt;/a&gt; has explored the idea that, in fact, not generally negative events, but threats are what narratives are about. It does not matter &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1090513817301976&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;how realistic the threats are&lt;/a&gt;: you can enjoy watching &lt;em&gt;The Haunting of Hill House&lt;/em&gt; even if you do not think ghosts exist or sharing the dubious news about a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.snopes.com/fact-check/morgue-employee-cremated-nap/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;morgue employee cremated while taking a nap&lt;/a&gt; even if you do not usually hang out in morgues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a recently published &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41599-019-0267-0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt;, Olivier Morin, Oleg Sobchuk, and I, tried to explore further the threath simulation hypothesis. We found two problems with how the hypothesis is often presented. First, it leaves unspecified which kind of threats should be simulated in narratives. Second, and related, it is not clear whether it is a “theory of fictional content”, i.e. it applies specifically to fictional narratives, or to a more wide range of contents, since, as we saw before, also news tend to bend toward the negative (but also, for example, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11515147&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;dreams&lt;/a&gt; have been interpreted in the same way).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the paper, we explore a more exacting version of the hypothesis, that we called the Ordeals simulation hypothesis (mainly Olivier’s brainchild). The hypothesis specifies that neither negative events in general, nor threats in general, should be overrepresented in fiction, but ordeals. Ordeals – the meaning is different from the usage of the term in common language – are threats that are severe, rare, and reactable. ‘Reactable’ here means that we cannot prevent them (as we can do for, say, cardiovascular diseases or pathogen contamination), but they are also not completely out of our control (like being struck by lighting). Aggressions, violent social interactions and, most of all, homicides, are all examples of ordeals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./ordeal.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;jpeg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first question is then whether ordeals are overrepresented in fiction with respect to other threats, or, to take a clear case: why do people die in novels? The ordeal simulation hypothesis predicts that agentive or accidental deaths (such as homicides or calamities), but not natural deaths, should be overrepresented. (&lt;em&gt;Game of Thrones&lt;/em&gt; is too easy of an &lt;a href=&#34;https://deathtimeline.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;example&lt;/a&gt;, but I recently read that the currently much talked &lt;em&gt;Chernobyl&lt;/em&gt; series may have &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.forbes.com/sites/michaelshellenberger/2019/05/09/the-reason-they-fictionalize-nuclear-disasters-like-chernobyl-is-because-they-kill-so-few-people/#7e6edff641fc&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;exaggerated&lt;/a&gt; the number of deaths). We coded hundreds of summaries of novels in wikipedia: mortality rates of novels’ characters are disproportionally high, when compared to realistic estimates. For 100,000 adults in US, between 100 and 200 deaths are estimated every year. But, in novels, we calculated this figure as 19,000, that is, three orders of magnitude higher. The realistic rate for agentive death is only 31 over 100,000, but in novels is more than 13,000. Natural deaths are also overrepresented, but less so: in reality the rate is higher than agentive deaths (107 on 100,000), while in novels is only around 2,000. (Much more in the paper.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second question is whether the prominence of agentive deaths is a specific feature of fiction with respect to other kinds of content. To explore this, we used a different methodology: we performed a computer text analysis of two large, comparable, corpora, one of novels and one of private letters and diaries, to detect the frequencies of words related to death in general, and to agentive death (‘kill’, ‘murder’, ‘execution’, etc.) in particular. The ordeal simulation hypothesis would predict that the frequency of agentive death-related words would be higher in the novels than in the private documents, but no difference should be found for general death-related words. In this case, the prediction was not confirmed: mentions of death, both violent and non-violent, were about equally frequent in fictional and non-fictional material.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What can we conclude from all that? Agentive deaths are overrepresented in fiction, but they are also, so it seems, overrepresented in material written without the intention of being made public. Perhaps the ordeal simulation hypothesis is not on the right track. My opinion, however, is that the problem may lie in finding an explanation that works for, and only for, fictional material. From the psychological point of view, how different is to read a true story, a piece of news, or a novel? (agentive deaths sure are overrepresented in news, see the plot below – full study &lt;a href=&#34;https://ourworldindata.org/does-the-news-reflect-what-we-die-from&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./OUD.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How different is to write a novel, a diary entry, or a letter? Perhaps there is no specific feature that makes fictions different from other materials, besides, as suggested before when mentioning misinformation, bigger freedom of explore possible contents. Maybe developing a “theory of fiction” (that works only for fiction) is misguided. There are various elements that make narratives (fiction, diaries, news, but also scientific theories, political orientations, etc.) attractive, these elements are the legitimate objects of study, and we can apply them to various domains, fiction included.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41599-019-0267-0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt;, and if you are really interested, &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/fjkze/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;all&lt;/a&gt; the data and codes for the analysis. The paper was published in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/collections/feibciaebg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Cultural Evolution&lt;/a&gt; collection of Palgrave Communications, with many other contributions worth looking at.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is cultural evolution “neoliberal”?</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2019_neoliberal/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2019_neoliberal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have been involved, over the weekend, in a small twitter debate on the old question of whether anthropology should use qualitative or quantitative methodologies. The debate was not particularly interesting by itself (I had many, probably too many, similar conversations starting when I was an undergraduate student) and the readers of this blog know, or suspect, my position, so I am not dwelling on it. There is, however, a marginal aspect that made me think a bit: I have the feeling that, when it is all said and done, the negative attitudes toward quantifications are linked to the idea that quantifying human culture is politically “neoliberal”, if not altogether “right-wing”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am sure that no critic of quantification in anthropology will accept this as their own position and they will express more cogent (at least from their point of view) arguments. It does not matter: I am happy to explore a straw man here. (A tweet that was stating it explicitly appeared at some point over the weekend, and it was “liked” by one of the persons involved in the debate, but that is just a side-note, a “like” on Twitter does not need to mean anything.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whereas I can grasp why some evolutionary approaches can be considered as supporting neoliberal social policies – even though I think the question is more nuanced and complicated – how can quantification by itself be? Is studying &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.plosone.org/article/info%3Adoi%2F10.1371%2Fjournal.pone.0106565&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;how movies influence the popularity of dog breeds&lt;/a&gt; neoliberal? Is it &lt;em&gt;counting&lt;/em&gt; how many different &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ehbonline.org/article/S1090-5138(16)30274-4/fulltext&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;folktales&lt;/a&gt; there are in different populations? Is cultural evolution, intended as a general project of applying scientific and quantitative methods to the study of culture, neoliberal?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enough with rhetorical questions, but I would be interested if anybody knows any scholarly reference or developed argument that support this position (again, I know, it is a straw man). The only reason I can think of is that, in the last decades, researchers working on quantitative approaches to culture have been less active in political matters than researchers working on qualitative approaches, even though my impression is that the formers are politically leaning left as much as the rest of social scientists (at least the people that refer to the “cultural evolution” label).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am really not interested in starting a debate, but perhaps there are reasons for considering quantification as such, and I’d be happy to exploit collective intelligence to know more (as said, possibly in the form of scholarly publications, etc.). Ok, I am going back to my R codes now.
&lt;img src=&#34;./wall.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Morgue employee cremated by mistake while taking a nap</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2019_morgue/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2019_morgue/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Online misinformation, fake news, false news, hoaxes, you name it, has been blamed for almost everything bad happening in the last years, from the success of Trump to Brexit, from the election of Bolsonaro to the (relative) spread of the anti-vax movement. The scientific consensus on the prominence and on the effect of online misinformation, however, is, at best, mixed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some highly-publicised studies had supported the scaremongers showing, for example, that falsehood spread &lt;a href=&#34;http://science.sciencemag.org/content/359/6380/1146&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;farther, faster, deeper, and more broadly than the truth&lt;/a&gt; or that &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41562-017-0132&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;‘low-quality’ information is equally likely to go ‘viral’ than ‘hi-quality’ information because of our ‘limited attention’&lt;/a&gt; (notice however that the former study does not compare ‘falsehood’ with ‘truth’, but debunked rumours versus confirmed rumours, so that real news that nobody debunked, i.e. the majority of them, are not even considered, and the latter has been recently retracted).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many other works, however, had painted a more nuanced image, showing that the production and the consumption of misinformation is &lt;a href=&#34;http://science.sciencemag.org/content/363/6425/374?fbclid=IwAR0ThyrRJk7feelo0SdkBr6obs3NIwjJgZt_E4QCCHYkfAva7Eo8A5A4VlI&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;concentrated in a limited portion of social media users&lt;/a&gt;, that individuals that have already extreme political views &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dartmouth.edu/~nyhan/fake-news-2016.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;are more likely to be exposed to political misinformation&lt;/a&gt;, and that, in general, misinformation is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.31.2.211&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;unlikely to change people minds&lt;/a&gt;. And, simply, other studies have shown that the actual amount of online misinformation &lt;a href=&#34;http://advances.sciencemag.org/content/5/1/eaau4586&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;is not that big&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, the narrative supporting that online misinformation is dangerous is itself very persuasive. It is easier to think that the people that voted Trump (you can replace this with whatever you do not like) have been manipulated by evil figures, and if they would have access to the correct information they would have done the right thing. This narrative is also quite dangerous, I think, because creates an easy scapegoat (you can make up any newspaper article with this schema: “How [name of social media] helped [thing that you do not like]”) that often distract to more relevant social, economic, and cultural problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, this narrative does not fit particularly well with an evolutionary account of human behaviour. We are a species that heavily relies on communication, social interactions, and learning from others. While details widely vary, researchers studying cultural evolution and cognition agree that, for the characteristics allowing communication, social interactions, and learning from others to be evolved in the first place, we should not be too &lt;a href=&#34;https://psycnet.apa.org/record/2017-22175-001&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;gullible&lt;/a&gt;. Of course, the conditions could be so different now that we could be more easily tricked, but this is an open question, and, given a ‘presumption of good design’, we should be at least sceptical of answers that are too pessimistic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given this somewhat reassuring perspective, however, online misinformation does exist, and one can ask what the possible advantages of misinformation could be. In a recent &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41599-019-0224-y&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt;, I proposed that one of these could simply be that misinformation can be manufactured building on features that make it attractive in an almost unconstrained way, whereas ‘true’ news cannot, simply because they need to correspond to reality. Misinformation can be designed to spread more than real information does (whether this is a conscious process or not). Cognitive anthropologists have put forward features that make some content, everything else equal, more appealing, memorable, or attention-grabbing than other content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is an example: many misinformation articles (I examine a small sample of ‘fake news’ from 2017: all the material, including the links and the texts used, is &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/78vhn/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) contains threat-related information, even though threats &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1090513817301976&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;do not need to be relevant for us&lt;/a&gt; (as in the article that gives the title to this blog post: not many of us usually take naps in a morgue. Still, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://worldnewsdailyreport.com/morgue-employee-cremated-by-mistake-while-taking-a-nap/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;false news&lt;/a&gt; has been shared/liked/commented more than one million times on Facebook). Other features (negative content, disgust, etc.) and many more details are explained in the paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Misinformation is not low-quality information that succeeds in spreading because of the shortcomings of online communication. Quite the opposite, misinformation, or at least some of it, is high-quality information that spreads because online communication is efficient. The difference is that ‘quality’ is not about truthfulness, but about how it fits with our cognitive predispositions. Online “fake news”, is, from this perspective, not much of a political and propagandistic phenomenon, but is more similar to the diffusion of memes, urban legends, and the like (of course political misinformation exist, even though, interestingly, often takes advantage of similar cognitive preferences to spread, think about the notorious &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pizzagate_conspiracy_theory&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Pizzagate&lt;/a&gt;, with its mix of threat, sex, and disgust).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paper is part of a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/collections/feibciaebg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Cultural evolution&lt;/a&gt; collection, edited by Jamie Tehrani, and I invite you to have a look at the other articles too!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./cemetery.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
