<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>digital age | Alberto Acerbi</title>
    <link>https://acerbialberto.com/tags/digital-age/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://acerbialberto.com/tags/digital-age/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>digital age</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 07 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://acerbialberto.com/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>digital age</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/tags/digital-age/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is fighting fake news a red herring?</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2022_fake_news/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2022_fake_news/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./featured.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fake news spreading on social media is often considered the cause of all bad things happened in the last years. From &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.independent.co.uk/voices/michael-gove-boris-johnson-brexit-eurosceptic-press-theresa-may-a7533806.html&#34;&gt;Brexit&lt;/a&gt; to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/the-fix/wp/2018/04/03/a-new-study-suggests-fake-news-might-have-won-donald-trump-the-2016-election/&#34;&gt;election of Trump&lt;/a&gt;, and later to &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0247642&#34;&gt;covid anti-vaxx sentiments&lt;/a&gt;, examples are not lacking. Of course, &amp;ldquo;bad&amp;rdquo; depends on your point of view, but also vaccines and lockdown &lt;em&gt;support&lt;/em&gt; have been considered a product of &lt;a href=&#34;https://open.spotify.com/episode/3SCsueX2bZdbEzRtKOCEyT&#34;&gt;mass formation psychosis&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am &lt;a href=&#34;https://acerbialberto.wordpress.com/2016/08/16/did-technology-disrupt-the-truth-probably-not/&#34;&gt;long-time sceptical&lt;/a&gt; of this line of reasoning. From a &lt;a href=&#34;https://global.oup.com/academic/product/how-traditions-live-and-die-9780190210502?cc=gb&amp;amp;lang=en&amp;amp;&#34;&gt;cognitive&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://press.princeton.edu/books/hardcover/9780691178707/not-born-yesterday&#34;&gt;evolutionary&lt;/a&gt; perspective on &lt;a href=&#34;https://global.oup.com/academic/product/cultural-evolution-in-the-digital-age-9780198835943?cc=gb&amp;amp;lang=en&amp;amp;&#34;&gt;cultural transmission&lt;/a&gt;, it makes sense to think to humans not as overly gullible individuals, but as wary social learners, that use relatively sophisticated strategies to decide whether to accept social information or not. In fact, recent empirical studies &lt;a href=&#34;https://royalsocietypublishing.org/doi/10.1098/rstb.2020.0052&#34;&gt;show&lt;/a&gt; that apparently we do not use social information enough, even when it would be advantageous. You can replace to the stereotype of gullible individuals the one of stubborn agents: the problem seems to be not that we are too easy to influence, but that we do not change our mind when we should.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It could be, naturally, that the situation brought about with the diffusion of social media is so different from offline dynamics that we just cannot cope. This is a legitimate question. However, the broad picture painted by recent research seems to be consistent: fake news rarely changes our minds. We interact with online misinformation because &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41599-019-0224-y&#34;&gt;is fun or engrossing&lt;/a&gt;, to keep &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41599-020-0452-1&#34;&gt;in contact with others&lt;/a&gt;, to actually &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/21670811.2017.1360143&#34;&gt;debunk it&lt;/a&gt;, or because we are already on the same page, and we want to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/american-political-science-review/article/abs/partisan-polarization-is-the-primary-psychological-motivation-behind-political-fake-news-sharing-on-twitter/3F7D2098CD87AE5501F7AD4A7FA83602&#34;&gt;signal our political or group membership&lt;/a&gt;. But there is more: when considered together with all the information present on social media, the proportion of fake or deceptive news is often negligible. Depending on the criteria used, the proportion of unreliable news online is generally estimated in single digit percentages, with at worst being around 5% of the total proportion of information (see table 1 &lt;a href=&#34;https://misinforeview.hks.harvard.edu/article/research-note-fighting-misinformation-or-fighting-for-information/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for various estimates).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting from this finding, together with &lt;a href=&#34;https://reutersinstitute.politics.ox.ac.uk/people/sacha-altay&#34;&gt;Sacha Altay&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/site/hugomercier/&#34;&gt;Hugo Mercier&lt;/a&gt;, we recently published a &lt;a href=&#34;https://misinforeview.hks.harvard.edu/article/research-note-fighting-misinformation-or-fighting-for-information/&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; that considers how much effort is worth allocating to fight online misinformation. Assume that people believe only some of the reliable news they encounter and only some of the unreliable news. Given the relative paucity of online misinformation, efforts to increase belief in reliable information will have a bigger effect than contrary efforts to decrease belief in unreliable information. To test this intuition (Hugo&amp;rsquo;s intuition&amp;hellip;), we developed a simple model. The figure below illustrates the main result. We started by devising a measure of the total amount of &amp;ldquo;truth&amp;rdquo; in the system (&amp;ldquo;Global information score&amp;rdquo;, on the y-axis in the figure). Think about the &amp;ldquo;Global information score&amp;rdquo; as an index that is maximum (100) when all and only reliable information is trusted, and minimum when only and all unreliable information is (-100). Given a 5% of proportion of unreliable information, if we completely wipe out belief in unreliable information, the Global information score increases of one or two points (in the figure, the difference between the &amp;ldquo;Baseline&amp;rdquo; and the &amp;ldquo;Intervention on misinformation&amp;rdquo; line). If, instead, we leave the belief in misinformation as it is, and we increase of single percentage points the belief in reliable information, we have a bigger effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./figure_1.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This outcome is robust to various realistic estimates of the relative proportion of reliable/unreliable information, to various baseline tendencies to believe reliable/unreliable information, and, as we explore in the model, works when the exposure to news is unequally distributed as in reality (with very few people consuming a lot of pieces of news, and the majority a few), when acceptance of misinformation decreases trust in reliable information, and when acceptance of misinformation increases the supply of misinformation (see again the &lt;a href=&#34;https://misinforeview.hks.harvard.edu/article/research-note-fighting-misinformation-or-fighting-for-information/&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; for details). Of course, the model is bare-bones, but I hope it can be extended to include more realistic characteristics (for example, various typologies of news effects, going beyond reliable versus unreliable news) and to support real policy efforts - which is, well, why we made it in first place&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, yes, the title of this post is provocative, but it makes an important point. As we write in the paper, it is &lt;em&gt;possible&lt;/em&gt; that the relative low proportion of fake news that we observe is indeed due to the efforts that are made to control it. But I do think that the academic and societal attention to &amp;ldquo;fake news&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;infodemic&amp;rdquo;, and the like, is disproportionate. Focusing on reliable news on social media, on their engagement potential, on counteracting the decrease of trust in reliable sources, could be more important that fighting a dubious enemy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assuming that our opponents are motivated by false beliefs (of course, it is the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0747563217306726&#34;&gt;others&lt;/a&gt; that fall for fake news!), beside being probably wrong, is also a way to refuse to understand their motivations and, finally, to preclude confrontation. Maybe understanding their reasons could produce better outcomes. Second, fake news offers a convenient and easy-to-conceptualise explanation for problems that are, probably, complex and rooted in deep socio-economical causes. It looks quite comforting to think that, if we can control better Facebook or Twitter, people would start to think as we do, but if that is not the case, the problems may remain unsolved.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Won&#39;t somebody please think of the children!</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2021_facebook/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2021_facebook/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./featured.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With unsurprising regularity, new &amp;ldquo;scandals&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;shocking&amp;rdquo; information about social media appear in the press, and, of course, in social media themselves. Lately, Facebook seems to be the main target. (Incidentally, why Facebook? My hunch is that academics and journalists, which are the main producers and consumers of this information, tend to not be Facebook users, so it feels less dissonant to think it is the real baddy. If only &lt;em&gt;the others&lt;/em&gt; would understand it! &amp;hellip;Anyway, this is not very important for the rest of the post.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, around one month ago, the Washington Post &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/washingtonpost/status/1433749542474747910&#34;&gt;reported&lt;/a&gt; that &amp;ldquo;Misinformation on Facebook got six times more clicks than factual news during the 2020 election&amp;rdquo;. The news was, of course, a hit. However, the &amp;ldquo;six times&amp;rdquo; figure seems at odds with much recent literature that shows that, when considered together with the total information present, the amount of misinformation circulating in social media &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.science.org/doi/abs/10.1126/science.aau2706&#34;&gt;is&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/sciadv.aay3539&#34;&gt;actually&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/sciadv.aau4586&#34;&gt;modest&lt;/a&gt;, something like the 5% of the total information (often less). For this reason, it would have been interesting to know how the &amp;ldquo;clicks&amp;rdquo; were actually calculated or what was exactly considered as &amp;ldquo;misinformation&amp;rdquo;. Unfortunately the study to which the Washington Post referred to was not out at the moment, and it is still, after one month, not available (not even in form of preprint, which is now relatively standard practice).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later on &amp;mdash; mid September &amp;mdash; another scandal hit Facebook. This time, it was leaked documents to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wsj.com/articles/facebook-knows-instagram-is-toxic-for-teen-girls-company-documents-show-11631620739&#34;&gt;the Wall Street Journal&lt;/a&gt;, titled &amp;ldquo;Facebook Knows Instagram Is Toxic for Teen Girls, Company Documents Show&amp;rdquo;. You probably heard about it, and about the outraged editorials and comments all around social media: you have here a bad social media company (i) hiding information, and (ii) harming (iii) young girls. Hardly you can have something more attractive. However, it looks like the report was mostly based on a small survey on a few dozens of teenagers that were asked if they &lt;em&gt;thought&lt;/em&gt; Instagram was bad for them, and on &amp;ldquo;focus groups&amp;rdquo; with even less participants, where the reason why they thought it was bad were discussed in more details. Now, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cell.com/trends/cognitive-sciences/fulltext/S1364-6613(20)30251-5&#34;&gt;we&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pnas.org/content/116/21/10226.short&#34;&gt;are&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41562%20018%200506%201?mod=article_inline&#34;&gt;far&lt;/a&gt; to have an in-depth knowledge of the effects of Instagram and social media on well-being and mental health, but this survey does not add much to our previous knowledge, so it is difficult to justify the reactions. (A good analysis of the vicissitude can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://unherd.com/2021/09/facebooks-bad-science/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Move on to today, and we have the whistleblower Frances Haugen, ex Facebook employee, testifying in front of the US congress. Things get heated, outrage continues, with public personalities pushing on Twitter the sober hashtag &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/SachaBaronCohen/status/1445541488889241608&#34;&gt;#FacebookKills&lt;/a&gt;. I admit I did not read the full transcriptions (I am already using precious time by writing this blog post instead of working or, even better, having a walk, as Bristol is sunny in October!), and I am referring to reports from newspapers, in particular &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2021/oct/05/facebook-harms-children-damaging-democracy-claims-whistleblower&#34;&gt;the Guardian&lt;/a&gt;. From what I understand, there are not really big novelties in what the whistleblower reports. She is mostly repeating the accusations that Facebook knew about harming children and teenagers (but see the point above), adding various dubious twists. One is the analogy between social media usage and addiction (I cite: &amp;ldquo;It’s just like cigarettes&amp;hellip;teenagers don&amp;rsquo;t have good self-regulation.&amp;rdquo;), which is considered &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.oii.ox.ac.uk/blog/social-media-is-nothing-like-drugs-despite-all-the-horror-stories/&#34;&gt;flawed&lt;/a&gt; by practically all researchers in the field. Another is the idea, never &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pnas.org/content/118/32/e2101967118&#34;&gt;really&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11109-021-09734-6&#34;&gt;established&lt;/a&gt;, that the algorithm is pushing towards more extreme content (the algorithm &amp;ldquo;led children from very innocuous topics like healthy recipes&amp;hellip;all the way to anorexia-promoting content over a very short period of time&amp;rdquo;). We have gory details (&amp;ldquo;women would be walking around with brittle bones in 60 years’ time because of the anorexia-related content they found on Facebook platforms&amp;rdquo; in the words of the Guardian), and not very surprising considerations, such as that Facebook &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2021/oct/03/former-facebook-employee-frances-haugen-identifies-herself-as-whistleblower&#34;&gt;put profits before people&lt;/a&gt; (huge if true for a private company). In sum, nothing really new and, mostly, from what I get, nothing that can be actually used to understand better what is going on, a part the usual accusations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, I am not in the &amp;ldquo;everything is good as it is&amp;rdquo; team (I do not think anybody is), and there are several things that Facebook and other social media should do to makes things better. A short and idiosyncratic list could include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Making their data available and easy to access to researchers and to the general public. Twitter seems slightly better than Facebook about that. (Adding to what said above, Facebook got caught recently in other &amp;ldquo;scandals&amp;rdquo; about errors in sharing data and blocking access to scientists.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No social media, that I am aware, is open about the algorithm they use to present information to users. How our Facebook news feed is decided? What about Twitter? I find the lack of transparency particularly worrying, also because this information would finally allow to give better answers to central questions on the kind of information promoted by social media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Could we make social media better? We could and we certainly should experiment with alternatives. If it is true (see the point above) that, say, social media algorithms push contents that receive more interactions (I called it &lt;a href=&#34;https://global.oup.com/academic/product/cultural-evolution-in-the-digital-age-9780198835943?cc=gb&amp;amp;lang=en&amp;amp;&#34;&gt;optimisation for shallow engagement&lt;/a&gt;) and, say &lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007%2Fs42761-021-00046-w&#34;&gt;negative&lt;/a&gt; or strongly &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pnas.org/content/114/28/7313.long&#34;&gt;emotional&lt;/a&gt; content receive more interactions, this could created a vicious circle where negative (say) information receive more interactions &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; are proposed more, so end up to dominate social media content. But, of course, things are complicated. Many other factors could be relevant (again, we would need to know more about the algorithm!) and, importantly, preferences for negative (say) information could be linked to more general cognitive preferences and be &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/br56y/&#34;&gt;succesfull&lt;/a&gt; independently from social media, so that one would need to balance algorithmic and psychological forces. This is just an example, but many others could be discussed along similar lines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This goes clearly beyond my expertise, but putting Whatsapp, Instagram, Facebook (and what else?) in the same hands may not be a good idea. I leave this to people that know more, but it &lt;em&gt;feels&lt;/em&gt; that a decentralised system would work better for us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And on and on. All these are, I think, very reasonable criticisms to Facebook and other social media, and I&amp;rsquo;d be (and am) very supportive of calls to action in this direction. Now, it could be that the periodic outrages are useful, but, call me crazy, I am not sure about that. If one claims that #FacebookKills, it is very easy for Facebook to show that it does not and, well, they are right. The risk is that by muddling sensible requests with sensationalist claims, we are doing Facebook&amp;rsquo;s game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ps: I may be too old, so &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3jFqhjaGh30&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; the title reference.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Covid misinformation on mainstream Italian media</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2020_covid_misinfo/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2020_covid_misinfo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You may have heard the we live in a post-truth era, that we are facing an infodemic or, even, a &lt;a href=&#34;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/370/6523/1395&#34;&gt;syndemic&lt;/a&gt;, the combination of &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt; epidemics, meaning that covid &amp;ldquo;emerged in an information ecosystem that helps misinformation and lies spread faster than scientific evidence, weakening our ability to respond to new threats&amp;rdquo;. Not only this is not true but, I believe, is also a dangerous narrative that makes us focus on the wrong problems instead of the real ones. Anyway, this is not a topic I can elaborate on here (hey, I wrote a &lt;a href=&#34;https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2019_oup/&#34;&gt;book&lt;/a&gt; - partly - about that!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, of course, &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; misinformation does spread. Another aspect of these stale criticism is that, naturally, the culprit is social media. Luckily, many real experts of media have long recognised the contribution, or in fact the prominent role, that mainstream, traditional, media have in the current spread of misinformation. &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/rasmus_kleis&#34;&gt;Rasmus Kleis Nielsen&lt;/a&gt;, director of Reuters Institute at Oxford University, reports on Twitter several examples of mainstream media, or prominent political figures, spreading or originating false or misleading information: &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/search?q=Misinformation%20often%20comes%20from%20the%20top&amp;amp;src=typed_query&#34;&gt;Misinformation often comes from the top&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an Italian living in UK, with part of my family living in Italy, I have been irritated by how the major Italian newspaper (for number of readers), &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.repubblica.it&#34;&gt;La Repubblica&lt;/a&gt;, covered the last days of news from UK. But I noticed the disservice before, so hang with me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;maria.png&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 15th of November, La Repubblica - I repeat, the major Italian newspaper - covered the declarations of don Livio Fanzaga, the director of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Radio_Maria&#34;&gt;Radio Maria&lt;/a&gt;, a large Catholic radio, which, among others, claimed that &amp;ldquo;Coronavirus is a conspiracy under the impulse of Satan&amp;rdquo;, with the goal of &amp;ldquo;building a new world without God&amp;rdquo;. Now, why a major newspaper should report the delusional beliefs of a not very important figure? In addition, in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.repubblica.it/cronaca/2020/11/15/news/radio_maria_il_coronavirus_e_un_complotto_sotto_l_impulso_di_satana_-274486827/&#34;&gt;the whole article&lt;/a&gt; there is not a single comment from the journalist on the declarations. If I remember correctly, but I can not check now, the article was linked from the first page of the online version (why??) and the declarations were reported as &amp;ldquo;controversial&amp;rdquo;, which is, clearly, not the right word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./vaccine.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 9th of December, in the first days of the successful roll-out of the UK vaccine (our local medical practice texted us yesterday that the first 1,000 people have been vaccinated in our Bristol &lt;em&gt;neighbourhood&lt;/em&gt;), La Repubblica reported, as full-page headline of the online version, the news about the two allergic reactions among the early people vaccinated. Now, this is technically not false, but it is an expected consequence of &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; vaccines. It was quickly reported in other international newspapers (as it should be) and quickly forgotten (as it should be). Putting this news as full-page headline, when we should all strive to understand how to convince &amp;ldquo;hesitant&amp;rdquo; people and reassure everybody about the vaccine, is not only bad journalism, but it could have dangerous consequences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./UK1.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We arrive to Sunday, after the declaration of the stricter Christmas lockdown for some areas in UK, the new strain, and the stop of flights from UK to Italy. It is a worrying situation, so what does the major Italian newspaper do? Again, full-page headline. The summary contains an anonymous quote: &amp;ldquo;We run away. The situation in London is out of control&amp;rdquo;. While health secretary Matt Hancock did say that the new variant (not &amp;ldquo;the situation in London&amp;rdquo;) was &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.sky.com/story/covid-19-in-tier-4-everybody-needs-to-behave-as-if-they-already-have-coronavirus-matt-hancock-says-12168124&#34;&gt;out of control&lt;/a&gt;, he certainly did not say anything about running away from London, so it is not clear what the quote refers to. But, beside the details, it is clearly made up, explicitly or not, to scare readers (a strategy often used in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41599-019-0224-y&#34;&gt;misinformation&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./featured.png&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We arrived to the title that today made me writing this post instead of doing something more festive: &amp;ldquo;Chaos in UK, you even have to do the tests by yourself!&amp;rdquo;. Summary: &amp;ldquo;It is a jungle there, that&amp;rsquo;s why there has been an out-of-control diffusion&amp;rdquo;. The major italian newspaper. A (supposedly) serious, left-leaning, large circulation newspaper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not a supporter of the current UK government, and I have plenty of criticisms on their Covid management, but: you can &lt;em&gt;choose&lt;/em&gt; whether to do the swab yourself or with an assistant (parents always do it for children) and this is because people &lt;em&gt;prefer&lt;/em&gt; to do it by themselves instead of having someone else doing it to them. UK tested, from the beginning of October, between 300,000 and 400,000 people every day, which is double of triple of what Italy did. We had a test for our daughter (she had a fever for few days): we booked it online in the evening on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gov.uk/get-coronavirus-test&#34;&gt;nhs website&lt;/a&gt;, we got a slot for the next morning, we did it in 10 minutes and we had the result (negative!) the day after. Hardly chaos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is difficult to comment on the rest, that is, implying that the &amp;ldquo;out-of-control diffusion&amp;rdquo;, which I guess refers to the new strain, is due to the fact that here is a &amp;ldquo;jungle&amp;rdquo;. Not much to say: mutations can happen anywhere (as they did and do). Not to mentione that one of the reasons why the new mutation has been first found in UK is that UK does on average 56 genomic sequences for every 1,000 covid cases, against, for example, the 0.42 of Italy (data from &lt;a href=&#34;https://covidcg.org/?tab=global_sequencing&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;: in other words, if the new strain would have been equally present in Italy and UK, everything else being equal, UK would have around 130 times more likelihood to detect it).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To conclude this rant-ish and quickly written post. It is disheartening how this journalism seems to be acceptable. Beside the academic thoughts, it can have important (see the vaccine example above) and real (Hi mum, I am good!) consequences. The fact that it goes together with the &amp;ldquo;social media are the culprit&amp;rdquo; slogan just makes it more unnerving. Anyway: check your news sources, stay safe wherever you are, and enjoy the holidays if you can!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning from failures</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2020_jce/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2020_jce/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./featured.png&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the Second World War, aeroplanes coming back after battles showed a peculiar pattern of damage: they were mostly hit on the wings and on the centre of the fuselage (see the figure above, which is not a representation of any real data, but makes the point). Based on this, the military reckoned they needed to add additional protections on these parts. Statisticians suggested instead that protections were needed on the cockpit and on the back of the fuselage - the parts &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; hit. And they were right! The point is that those aeroplanes were the returning ones: aeroplanes presenting that pattern of damage were actually able to come back succesfully after battle. It was the aiprlanes hit in the other areas that were lost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether the story is true or not, it is a vivid representation of survivorship bias (as well as &lt;a href=&#34;https://xkcd.com/1827/&#34;&gt;this excellent xkcd&lt;/a&gt;). Each time someone is giving advice based on how they succeed, it is good to remember that one is generalising from a biased sample. In many fields, in addition, success is partly (or mostly, see again the xkcd comic), based on luck or on reasons that can be hardly linked to the success itself, which is a good moment to mention success in academia. The big professor that was interested in X from school? The brilliant researcher that takes a walk every morning? The 12-papers-a-year postdoc that meditate? The 10 rules for juggling academic job and family? (I swear I am not referring to any real example here. Really.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe we need to &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; consider advice from the unsuccessful cases. Thus, I will start the &lt;em&gt;succumbership bias&lt;/em&gt; series with my resignation from the role of coordinator of the Cultural Evolution Society publishing committee. The goal of the publishing committee was to start a society journal. After a couple of years, there has not been any progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A short summary: the 7th June 2013 (more than seven years ago), I wrote on my old blog the post &lt;a href=&#34;https://acerbialberto.wordpress.com/2013/06/07/journal-of-cultural-evolution-anyone/&#34;&gt;“Journal of Cultural Evolution”, anyone?&lt;/a&gt;. The post received a quite positive reaction, and various people thought it was a good idea. In 2014, at the EHBEA conference in Bristol, we had a first meeting to discuss the project, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://acerbialberto.wordpress.com/2014/03/21/journal-of-cultural-evolution-meeting-at-ehbea-2104/&#34;&gt;possibly to start to do something concrete in this direction&lt;/a&gt;. Nothing much happened, but in 2017, at the first conference of the Cultural Evolution Society in Jena, we had &lt;a href=&#34;https://acerbialberto.wordpress.com/2017/06/26/journal-of-cultural-evolution-again/&#34;&gt;another meeting&lt;/a&gt; about the possibility of the journal, and shortly after, the publishing committee started to ponder &lt;a href=&#34;https://acerbialberto.wordpress.com/2018/06/18/a-quick-update-on-the-journal-of-cultural-evolution/&#34;&gt;various options&lt;/a&gt;. Today, the Cultural Evolution Society is having a meeting in which I presented (indirectly) my resignation, and it should be discussed what will be done (if anything) with the journal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here a few thoughts, quite specifically linked to the journal topic, this time influenced by the succumbership bias!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You surely saw these quotes about &amp;ldquo;dreaming big&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;following your dreams&amp;rdquo;, and so on. But from the succumberhsip bias point of view, it may be better to have realistic goals, and not be too ambitious. We wanted an open access, self-published journal, we even discussed whether publishing directly the submissions and having online, voluntary, reviews. We did not want to restrict the scope of the journal to usual scientific articles, but having space for datasets, ethnography, commentaries. We wanted to &amp;ldquo;culturally evolve&amp;rdquo; the publishing system (a usual quote from CT). Perhaps we should have contacted Elsevier with &amp;ldquo;hey, do you want to publish the Journal of Cultural Evolution?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the members of the publishing committee - including yours truly - were working on this project in the spare time. Given the extent of the project I now think it would have been better to have a small group of people committed, and able to focus almost full time for a short period on it. This is not a criticism of our work (we did what we could!), but maybe something the Cultural Evolution Society can think about for the future?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then there are these quotes about many heads that are better than one, the plurality of opinions. Within the few heads of the publishing committee we had slightly different opinions about a wealth of topics (open science? Diversity and inclusivity? Independence? All of them? Can we? Shall we volunteer for this? No? But where do we find the money?). Not insurmountable, but maybe, just maybe, sometimes may be good to be all in agreement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This mostly relates to me. I am not exactly the best person concerning PR and networking, and I did not have strong links with the headquarters of the society. A better-connected person could have probably done a better job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You know that good things need time and it is important to be patient. If the project is good, one waits and, in the end, it will succeed. Or so says the survivor. Perhaps I should have suspected that, if the project was moving so slowly (remember the first idea was in 2013), something was not right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Related to the above, incentives change with time. In particular, one of the main reason to think about a journal for cultural evolution in 2013 was the absence of other, related, venues of publications. Today we have &lt;em&gt;Nature Human Behaviour&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Evolutionary Human Sciences&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Evolutionary Perspectives on Imaginative Culture&lt;/em&gt;, the &amp;ldquo;Cultural Evolution&amp;rdquo; collection in Palgrave&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Humanities and Social Sciences Communications&lt;/em&gt; and probably others that I am forgetting (excluding here journals that were already present in 2013 and publishing cultural evolution stuff, such as &lt;em&gt;Cliodynamics&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Evolution and Human Behavior&lt;/em&gt;, or the &lt;em&gt;Journal of Cognition and Culture&lt;/em&gt; among others).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, I still hope that a self-published, and possibly innovative, journal of the Cultural Evolution Society will appear (who knows, maybe on this moment the executive committee is turning down my resignation and allocating bazillion dollars for the project). Good luck to them/us and thank you to the people that tried with me to carry this forward!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ps: Of course, the succumbership bias is as bad as the survivorship bias.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;pps: Thank you to the people that shared kind words with me and, yes, it is not &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; bad, but honestly I did hope to be able to create this journal one day&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Twitter kick-starter</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2020_twitter/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2020_twitter/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./featured.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been told of NGOs job applications that require to include the candidate&amp;rsquo;s Twitter profile. Even when not that explicit, a curated Twitter account is increasingly important for the academic and academic-adjacent job market, if only for networking. As I am active on Twitter from October 2012, I had the occasion to give some advice on how to start on the social media (for example to my wife!). As it seems they worked, I have been suggested to put them in a blog post, so here it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, a few notes. This post is not about the technical basics (how to open an account, how to tweet, how to retweet, etc.), I consider you are good with those, or you can easily find this information somewhere else. Second, it is not about becoming a twitter star with thousands of followers, but about having a decent profile for your career development. The bits of advice are pretty general and they should work for an average user. Of course, there are plenty of exceptions and, to become a Twitter star, what counts is probably being &lt;em&gt;already&lt;/em&gt; a star, the actual content you share and, mostly, luck. But, again, this is not our goal. Finally, all this is focused on academic or closely linked profiles, that are the only ones for which I have a bit of experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time. It seems many people are worried that they do not have enough time to have a curated Twitter profile. While obviously Twitter is a rabbit hole where one can lose all the time in the world, this is not necessary. Nobody has to be completely updated on what the accounts they follow tweet: this is not only impossible but also useless. For the beginning, an hour a week it is more than sufficient to follow some people, read some tweets and post content. Two sessions of half an hour or less, for example, will be enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have a curated profile. Use a picture of yourself where you can be recognised. The short bio is important: avoid the witty sentence and put relevant information and links (if useful). Include a link to your website. Here, as an example, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/acerbialberto&#34;&gt;my profile&lt;/a&gt;. Again, there are many exceptions, but this works on average.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following and followers. Start by following a few hundred accounts, perhaps have a goal (&amp;ldquo;Following 200 accounts for the end of the month&amp;rdquo;). Follow accounts that are related to your field, big and small names, more than the people that you know. Twitter is not about keeping in contact, but about exchanging information. How can you find them? Search with keywords and follow the advice from Twitter. Here a useful shortcut: when you find a reliable profile in your field, that possibly does not follow too many accounts, go through their &amp;ldquo;following&amp;rdquo; and follow the ones that seem relevant. You also want to acquire followers. This mostly depends on the content that you share (see below), but ideally you want that a reasonable proportion of the account you follow will follow you back. Usually this happens, say around 50% at the beginning. When you will have more followers you will be more twitter-attractive, and the probability of begin followed back will grow. If you &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; are concerned about the number of followers, follow accounts that have more or less the same number of followers/following, as this probably means that they follow back whoever follows them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When to tweet. In general, the more you tweet, the better. However, time is not infinite, and there are many better things to do in life. Still, you should tweet original content (i.e. not a retweeet) &lt;em&gt;at least&lt;/em&gt; one or two times a week. This signals your account is active.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What to tweet. Things related to your professional topic. Do not tweet what you think about X - or do not do it often - probably not many care. Share information like links to papers, blogs, pieces of news, etc. and, in case, what you think about that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stick to one topic. The most important - I think - advice about content: be consistent. Do not tweet once about your scientific field, then about your cat, then about your favourite Sichuan dish, then the anti-Trump rant. People will follow and support you (with likes and retweets) if you provide a consistent and up-to-date information about one topic: &amp;ldquo;that&amp;rsquo;s one of the accounts to follow if you are interested in X&amp;rdquo; (where X is &amp;ldquo;anthropology&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;conservation&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;history of Middle East&amp;rdquo; or whatever). If I follow you because I am interested in conservation, I probably do not care about what you ate last night (there are other social media for this). One out-of-topic tweet from time to time is ok, but not too many. Of course you can have two related topics (say, ehm, &amp;ldquo;cultural evolution&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;digital media&amp;rdquo;) Two unrelated topics? Not sure. Each time I want to tweet something unrelated to my research, for example politics, I refrain, and I think it is good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How to find relevant content. This is the difficult part, here is what works for me. A good source of new scientific articles are Google Scholar alerts (of course you have a Google Scholar profile). They generally fit very well with your research, so you should be on the safe side. Another source is, of course, Twitter itself (for me it has replaced almost all the official journals&amp;rsquo; alerts): retweet relevant material from others (see also below for the &amp;ldquo;Retweet with comment&amp;rdquo;). A good way to provide new content even with retweets is to retweet material from more obscure accounts, or accounts unrelated to your field. Retweeting the last paper of the star researcher with 50,000 followers will not provide new content to your followers, but retweeting the interesting paper of a less known researcher, or showing how something in another field is related to yours will. News, conferences, open positions related to your field are also good content. At the end of the day, however, this will be about what you read and what you find interesting, so: be curious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check the content. Read before sharing is the basic advice. But, really, do it. You do not have to read a full scientific article before you tweet it, but you want to be sure that it is about what is supposed to be and that, for example, the link points to the correct place, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personalise the content. The other advantage of reading before sharing is that you can personalise the tweet, and this is added value. You can quickly say &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; the article, or the piece of news, is interesting or criticizable, this is better than just tweeting the title (but this is also ok). This is especially useful for reteweets: you can &amp;ldquo;Retweet with comment&amp;rdquo; so that, again, you add some personal information, but also, the tweet is associated in the timeline to your profile, so it is &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; tweet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Photos and videos. They do make tweets more attractive. If you tweet an article you may want to include one of the plots, or some related image. This is why I put in each blog post a picture, even if not very related (including this one): when sharing it on Twitter, the small picture appears together with the link.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hashtags. I do not use them, but it does seem they increase the number of likes and retweets (which in turn will ultimately increase the number of your followers) so I guess a moderate use (one, maximum two) in some of the tweets, when they are relevant, may be a good strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like. There are various reasons to like relevant tweets from other users. They will know about you, you can use them as bookmarks, and you possibly train the algorithm that select which tweets you will see more prominently. Also like all replies to your tweets, if they are not offensive, and if they are at least related, because why not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be nice. In eight years of Twitter, I believe I got involved in quarrels two or three times. Of course, I think it was not my fault, but that is too easy. In any case, there is nothing to gain. Twitter is not the place for long and nuanced discussions. This is fine, as long as one is aware of it. I found Twitter tremendously useful for sharing and discovering interesting stuff and for many good conversations and, so far, the balance useful/annoying has been largely positive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cultural evolution in the digital age book club</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2020_ceda_book_club/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2020_ceda_book_club/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./featured.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just a short post to advertise and bookmark the book club that &lt;a href=&#34;http://cognitionandculture.net&#34;&gt;cognitionandculture.net&lt;/a&gt; organised around &lt;em&gt;Cultural evolution in the digital age&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;http://cognitionandculture.net/webinars/cultural-evolution-in-the-digital-age/cultural-evolution-in-the-digital-age-book-club/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). Every now and then, the people at the International Cognition &amp;amp; Culture Institute (ICCI) choose a book of culture-and-cognition interest and invite the author to write a short précis and various experts on the topic to write commentaries (see some previous examples &lt;a href=&#34;http://cognitionandculture.net/ebooks&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).  All is followed by an open online discussion: for &lt;em&gt;Cultural evolution in the digital age&lt;/em&gt; it starts today and will last until the 12th of July.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The commentaries, by &lt;a href=&#34;http://cognitionandculture.net/webinars/cultural-evolution-in-the-digital-age/are-humans-wary-learners/&#34;&gt;Alex Mesoudi&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://cognitionandculture.net/webinars/cultural-evolution-in-the-digital-age/what-is-the-recipe/&#34;&gt;Sacha Altay&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://cognitionandculture.net/webinars/cultural-evolution-in-the-digital-age/cultural-transmission-reinvention-and-progress/&#34;&gt;Olivier Morin&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://cognitionandculture.net/webinars/cultural-evolution-in-the-digital-age/consuming-vs-sharing-information-online/&#34;&gt;Hugo Mercier&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://cognitionandculture.net/webinars/cultural-evolution-in-the-digital-age/the-participatory-age/&#34;&gt;Mathieu Charbonneau&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://cognitionandculture.net/webinars/cultural-evolution-in-the-digital-age/the-mystery-of-production/&#34;&gt;Pascal Boyer&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://cognitionandculture.net/webinars/cultural-evolution-in-the-digital-age/truth-is-not-always-the-point/&#34;&gt;Tiffany Morisseau&lt;/a&gt; are extremely insightful, and they should appeal to anybody interested in cultural evolution and especially in its application to contemporary online dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if it sounds like a cliché, I will not get tired to repeat how privileged I feel about having &lt;em&gt;Cultural evolution in the digital age&lt;/em&gt; at the centre of such a stimulating exchange. Everybody is very welcome to &lt;a href=&#34;http://cognitionandculture.net/webinars/cultural-evolution-in-the-digital-age/cultural-evolution-in-the-digital-age-book-club-general-discussion/&#34;&gt;join the discussion&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vaccine hesitancy is not correlated with social media penetration at country-level in Europe</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2019_wellcome/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2019_wellcome/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Wellcome Trust has recently (yesterday) released the 2018 &lt;a href=&#34;https://wellcome.ac.uk/reports/wellcome-global-monitor/2018&#34;&gt;Global Monitor&lt;/a&gt;, a 140,000 people survey on how ‘people around the world think and feel about science and major health challenges’. Among the many interesting pieces of information, not surprisingly, attitudes towards vaccinations are starting to be widely discussed in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/society/2019/jun/19/survey-shows-crisis-of-confidence-in-vaccines-in-parts-of-europe&#34;&gt;press&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first important thing to notice, as the Wellcome Trust correctly does, is that ‘worldwide, 79% of people agree that vaccines are safe and 84% agree that they are effective’ and ‘92% of parents worldwide said that their children have received a vaccine to prevent them from getting childhood diseases .’ Whatever we may think, the majority of people around the world rightly believe that vaccines are good. Of course, there is a minority of people, especially in western countries, that is less convinced of that. Citing again the Wellcome Trust, ‘In France, one in three people disagree that vaccines are safe, the highest percentage for any country worldwide’. The France figure is, however, one of few outliers, also for western countries, where the averages of people disagreeing that vaccines are safe are around 10%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, that one out of ten persons in western countries could think as such is worrying. Not surprisingly, social media has been identified as one of the culprits of this situation, and I bet that, following the Wellcome Trust survey, the trend will continue (I already found one article &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.independent.co.uk/news/health/anti-vaxx-vaccination-myth-poll-europe-pro-nature-birth-a8964441.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). Out of curiosity, I correlated the Wellcome trust data with recent data on social media penetration/usage in Europe, and they are not correlated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./social_media.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I was on it, I also correlated the data with the importance of religion..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./religion.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;the trust in science&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./science.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;and the GDP pro capita&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./gdp.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally, this is a very basic analysis. It could be for example that, within countries, people that are sceptical of vaccines use more social media than others. That anti-vaxx information spreads effectively in social media is not surprising. There are &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cell.com/trends/cognitive-sciences/fulltext/S1364-6613(15)00197-7?_returnURL=https%3A%2F%2Flinkinghub.elsevier.com%2Fretrieve%2Fpii%2FS1364661315001977%3Fshowall%3Dtrue&#34;&gt;many reasons&lt;/a&gt; why anti-vaccination beliefs are easy to spread (and, conversely, it could be more difficult with pro-vaccination beliefs). Information around vaccines is psychologically attractive, involving potentially disgust and counterintuitive concepts that, coupled with a possible negative bias, make fearmongering on vaccines a good topic for &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41599-019-0224-y&#34;&gt;online misinformation&lt;/a&gt;. All of this, however, is not a prerogative of digital social media (where correct, pro-vaccine, information &lt;a href=&#34;https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jama/fullarticle/2670250&#34;&gt;also spreads effectively&lt;/a&gt;), and vaccine hesitancy is &lt;a href=&#34;http://sethmnookin.com/the-panic-virus/&#34;&gt;as old as vaccines themselves&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, each time you hear someone saying, or writing, that anti-vaccination beliefs are linked to social media you should be sceptical. At least: it is not obvious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested, all the technical stuff (data, R script, what I coded exactly as “vaccine hesitancy”, “social media penetration”, etc.) are in &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/albertoacerbi/vaccines-wellcome&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; GitHub repository.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Morgue employee cremated by mistake while taking a nap</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2019_morgue/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2019_morgue/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Online misinformation, fake news, false news, hoaxes, you name it, has been blamed for almost everything bad happening in the last years, from the success of Trump to Brexit, from the election of Bolsonaro to the (relative) spread of the anti-vax movement. The scientific consensus on the prominence and on the effect of online misinformation, however, is, at best, mixed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some highly-publicised studies had supported the scaremongers showing, for example, that falsehood spread &lt;a href=&#34;http://science.sciencemag.org/content/359/6380/1146&#34;&gt;farther, faster, deeper, and more broadly than the truth&lt;/a&gt; or that &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41562-017-0132&#34;&gt;‘low-quality’ information is equally likely to go ‘viral’ than ‘hi-quality’ information because of our ‘limited attention’&lt;/a&gt; (notice however that the former study does not compare ‘falsehood’ with ‘truth’, but debunked rumours versus confirmed rumours, so that real news that nobody debunked, i.e. the majority of them, are not even considered, and the latter has been recently retracted).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many other works, however, had painted a more nuanced image, showing that the production and the consumption of misinformation is &lt;a href=&#34;http://science.sciencemag.org/content/363/6425/374?fbclid=IwAR0ThyrRJk7feelo0SdkBr6obs3NIwjJgZt_E4QCCHYkfAva7Eo8A5A4VlI&#34;&gt;concentrated in a limited portion of social media users&lt;/a&gt;, that individuals that have already extreme political views &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dartmouth.edu/~nyhan/fake-news-2016.pdf&#34;&gt;are more likely to be exposed to political misinformation&lt;/a&gt;, and that, in general, misinformation is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.31.2.211&#34;&gt;unlikely to change people minds&lt;/a&gt;. And, simply, other studies have shown that the actual amount of online misinformation &lt;a href=&#34;http://advances.sciencemag.org/content/5/1/eaau4586&#34;&gt;is not that big&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet, the narrative supporting that online misinformation is dangerous is itself very persuasive. It is easier to think that the people that voted Trump (you can replace this with whatever you do not like) have been manipulated by evil figures, and if they would have access to the correct information they would have done the right thing. This narrative is also quite dangerous, I think, because creates an easy scapegoat (you can make up any newspaper article with this schema: “How [name of social media] helped [thing that you do not like]”) that often distract to more relevant social, economic, and cultural problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, this narrative does not fit particularly well with an evolutionary account of human behaviour. We are a species that heavily relies on communication, social interactions, and learning from others. While details widely vary, researchers studying cultural evolution and cognition agree that, for the characteristics allowing communication, social interactions, and learning from others to be evolved in the first place, we should not be too &lt;a href=&#34;https://psycnet.apa.org/record/2017-22175-001&#34;&gt;gullible&lt;/a&gt;. Of course, the conditions could be so different now that we could be more easily tricked, but this is an open question, and, given a ‘presumption of good design’, we should be at least sceptical of answers that are too pessimistic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given this somewhat reassuring perspective, however, online misinformation does exist, and one can ask what the possible advantages of misinformation could be. In a recent &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41599-019-0224-y&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt;, I proposed that one of these could simply be that misinformation can be manufactured building on features that make it attractive in an almost unconstrained way, whereas ‘true’ news cannot, simply because they need to correspond to reality. Misinformation can be designed to spread more than real information does (whether this is a conscious process or not). Cognitive anthropologists have put forward features that make some content, everything else equal, more appealing, memorable, or attention-grabbing than other content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is an example: many misinformation articles (I examine a small sample of ‘fake news’ from 2017: all the material, including the links and the texts used, is &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/78vhn/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) contains threat-related information, even though threats &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1090513817301976&#34;&gt;do not need to be relevant for us&lt;/a&gt; (as in the article that gives the title to this blog post: not many of us usually take naps in a morgue. Still, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://worldnewsdailyreport.com/morgue-employee-cremated-by-mistake-while-taking-a-nap/&#34;&gt;false news&lt;/a&gt; has been shared/liked/commented more than one million times on Facebook). Other features (negative content, disgust, etc.) and many more details are explained in the paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Misinformation is not low-quality information that succeeds in spreading because of the shortcomings of online communication. Quite the opposite, misinformation, or at least some of it, is high-quality information that spreads because online communication is efficient. The difference is that ‘quality’ is not about truthfulness, but about how it fits with our cognitive predispositions. Online “fake news”, is, from this perspective, not much of a political and propagandistic phenomenon, but is more similar to the diffusion of memes, urban legends, and the like (of course political misinformation exist, even though, interestingly, often takes advantage of similar cognitive preferences to spread, think about the notorious &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pizzagate_conspiracy_theory&#34;&gt;Pizzagate&lt;/a&gt;, with its mix of threat, sex, and disgust).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paper is part of a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/collections/feibciaebg&#34;&gt;Cultural evolution&lt;/a&gt; collection, edited by Jamie Tehrani, and I invite you to have a look at the other articles too!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./cemetery.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
