<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>digital age | Alberto Acerbi</title>
    <link>http://acerbialberto.com/tags/digital-age/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://acerbialberto.com/tags/digital-age/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>digital age</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://acerbialberto.com/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>digital age</title>
      <link>http://acerbialberto.com/tags/digital-age/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vaccine hesitancy is not correlated with social media penetration at country-level in Europe</title>
      <link>http://acerbialberto.com/post/2019_wellcome/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://acerbialberto.com/post/2019_wellcome/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Wellcome Trust has recently (yesterday) released the 2018 &lt;a href=&#34;https://wellcome.ac.uk/reports/wellcome-global-monitor/2018&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Global Monitor&lt;/a&gt;, a 140,000 people survey on how ‘people around the world think and feel about science and major health challenges’. Among the many interesting pieces of information, not surprisingly, attitudes towards vaccinations are starting to be widely discussed in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/society/2019/jun/19/survey-shows-crisis-of-confidence-in-vaccines-in-parts-of-europe&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;press&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first important thing to notice, as the Wellcome Trust correctly does, is that ‘worldwide, 79% of people agree that vaccines are safe and 84% agree that they are effective’ and ‘92% of parents worldwide said that their children have received a vaccine to prevent them from getting childhood diseases .’ Whatever we may think, the majority of people around the world rightly believe that vaccines are good. Of course, there is a minority of people, especially in western countries, that is less convinced of that. Citing again the Wellcome Trust, ‘In France, one in three people disagree that vaccines are safe, the highest percentage for any country worldwide’. The France figure is, however, one of few outliers, also for western countries, where the averages of people disagreeing that vaccines are safe are around 10%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, that one out of ten persons in western countries could think as such is worrying. Not surprisingly, social media has been identified as one of the culprits of this situation, and I bet that, following the Wellcome Trust survey, the trend will continue (I already found one article &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.independent.co.uk/news/health/anti-vaxx-vaccination-myth-poll-europe-pro-nature-birth-a8964441.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). Out of curiosity, I correlated the Wellcome trust data with recent data on social media penetration/usage in Europe, and they are not correlated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./social_media.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I was on it, I also correlated the data with the importance of religion..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./religion.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;the trust in science&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./science.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;and the GDP pro capita&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./gdp.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naturally, this is a very basic analysis. It could be for example that, within countries, people that are sceptical of vaccines use more social media than others. That anti-vaxx information spreads effectively in social media is not surprising. There are &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cell.com/trends/cognitive-sciences/fulltext/S1364-6613(15)00197-7?_returnURL=https%3A%2F%2Flinkinghub.elsevier.com%2Fretrieve%2Fpii%2FS1364661315001977%3Fshowall%3Dtrue&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;many reasons&lt;/a&gt; why anti-vaccination beliefs are easy to spread (and, conversely, it could be more difficult with pro-vaccination beliefs). Information around vaccines is psychologically attractive, involving potentially disgust and counterintuitive concepts that, coupled with a possible negative bias, make fearmongering on vaccines a good topic for &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41599-019-0224-y&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;online misinformation&lt;/a&gt;. All of this, however, is not a prerogative of digital social media (where correct, pro-vaccine, information &lt;a href=&#34;https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jama/fullarticle/2670250&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;also spreads effectively&lt;/a&gt;), and vaccine hesitancy is &lt;a href=&#34;http://sethmnookin.com/the-panic-virus/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;as old as vaccines themselves&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, each time you hear someone saying, or writing, that anti-vaccination beliefs are linked to social media you should be sceptical. At least: it is not obvious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are interested, all the technical stuff (data, R script, what I coded exactly as “vaccine hesitancy”, “social media penetration”, etc.) are in &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/albertoacerbi/vaccines-wellcome&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; GitHub repository.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Morgue employee cremated by mistake while taking a nap</title>
      <link>http://acerbialberto.com/post/2019_morgue/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://acerbialberto.com/post/2019_morgue/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Online misinformation, fake news, false news, hoaxes, you name it, has been blamed for almost everything bad happening in the last years, from the success of Trump to Brexit, from the election of Bolsonaro to the (relative) spread of the anti-vax movement. The scientific consensus on the prominence and on the effect of online misinformation, however, is, at best, mixed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some highly-publicised studies had supported the scaremongers showing, for example, that falsehood spread &lt;a href=&#34;http://science.sciencemag.org/content/359/6380/1146&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;farther, faster, deeper, and more broadly than the truth&lt;/a&gt; or that &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41562-017-0132&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;‘low-quality’ information is equally likely to go ‘viral’ than ‘hi-quality’ information because of our ‘limited attention’&lt;/a&gt; (notice however that the former study does not compare ‘falsehood’ with ‘truth’, but debunked rumours versus confirmed rumours, so that real news that nobody debunked, i.e. the majority of them, are not even considered, and the latter has been recently retracted).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many other works, however, had painted a more nuanced image, showing that the production and the consumption of misinformation is &lt;a href=&#34;http://science.sciencemag.org/content/363/6425/374?fbclid=IwAR0ThyrRJk7feelo0SdkBr6obs3NIwjJgZt_E4QCCHYkfAva7Eo8A5A4VlI&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;concentrated in a limited portion of social media users&lt;/a&gt;, that individuals that have already extreme political views &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dartmouth.edu/~nyhan/fake-news-2016.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;are more likely to be exposed to political misinformation&lt;/a&gt;, and that, in general, misinformation is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.31.2.211&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;unlikely to change people minds&lt;/a&gt;. And, simply, other studies have shown that the actual amount of online misinformation &lt;a href=&#34;http://advances.sciencemag.org/content/5/1/eaau4586&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;is not that big&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, the narrative supporting that online misinformation is dangerous is itself very persuasive. It is easier to think that the people that voted Trump (you can replace this with whatever you do not like) have been manipulated by evil figures, and if they would have access to the correct information they would have done the right thing. This narrative is also quite dangerous, I think, because creates an easy scapegoat (you can make up any newspaper article with this schema: “How [name of social media] helped [thing that you do not like]”) that often distract to more relevant social, economic, and cultural problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, this narrative does not fit particularly well with an evolutionary account of human behaviour. We are a species that heavily relies on communication, social interactions, and learning from others. While details widely vary, researchers studying cultural evolution and cognition agree that, for the characteristics allowing communication, social interactions, and learning from others to be evolved in the first place, we should not be too &lt;a href=&#34;https://psycnet.apa.org/record/2017-22175-001&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;gullible&lt;/a&gt;. Of course, the conditions could be so different now that we could be more easily tricked, but this is an open question, and, given a ‘presumption of good design’, we should be at least sceptical of answers that are too pessimistic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given this somewhat reassuring perspective, however, online misinformation does exist, and one can ask what the possible advantages of misinformation could be. In a recent &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41599-019-0224-y&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt;, I proposed that one of these could simply be that misinformation can be manufactured building on features that make it attractive in an almost unconstrained way, whereas ‘true’ news cannot, simply because they need to correspond to reality. Misinformation can be designed to spread more than real information does (whether this is a conscious process or not). Cognitive anthropologists have put forward features that make some content, everything else equal, more appealing, memorable, or attention-grabbing than other content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is an example: many misinformation articles (I examine a small sample of ‘fake news’ from 2017: all the material, including the links and the texts used, is &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/78vhn/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) contains threat-related information, even though threats &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1090513817301976&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;do not need to be relevant for us&lt;/a&gt; (as in the article that gives the title to this blog post: not many of us usually take naps in a morgue. Still, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://worldnewsdailyreport.com/morgue-employee-cremated-by-mistake-while-taking-a-nap/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;false news&lt;/a&gt; has been shared/liked/commented more than one million times on Facebook). Other features (negative content, disgust, etc.) and many more details are explained in the paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Misinformation is not low-quality information that succeeds in spreading because of the shortcomings of online communication. Quite the opposite, misinformation, or at least some of it, is high-quality information that spreads because online communication is efficient. The difference is that ‘quality’ is not about truthfulness, but about how it fits with our cognitive predispositions. Online “fake news”, is, from this perspective, not much of a political and propagandistic phenomenon, but is more similar to the diffusion of memes, urban legends, and the like (of course political misinformation exist, even though, interestingly, often takes advantage of similar cognitive preferences to spread, think about the notorious &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pizzagate_conspiracy_theory&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Pizzagate&lt;/a&gt;, with its mix of threat, sex, and disgust).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paper is part of a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/collections/feibciaebg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Cultural evolution&lt;/a&gt; collection, edited by Jamie Tehrani, and I invite you to have a look at the other articles too!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./cemetery.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
