<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Alberto Acerbi</title>
    <link>https://acerbialberto.com/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://acerbialberto.com/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://acerbialberto.com/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Individual based models of cultural evolution</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/project/1_ibm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/project/1_ibm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I started my academic career as a modeller (in fact, as an artificial life/robotics researcher: &lt;a href=&#34;https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2006_jasss/&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; is my first publication ever), and I continue to believe that computational models are a fundamental tool to develop research in cultural evolution. On the one hand, models are excellent theory-generating machines: they allow you to formalise your thought experiments, and to explore their consequences, which is sometimes impossible by intuition alone. On the other, models make your theories explicit and directly testable by other researchers. Recent topics include whether &lt;a href=&#34;https://acerbialberto.com/publication/preprint_stability/&#34;&gt;cultural stability can be obtained without copying or selection&lt;/a&gt; (yes), whether &lt;a href=&#34;https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2016_sci_rep/&#34;&gt;conformity can be detected from population-level effects&lt;/a&gt;  (not always), or how &lt;a href=&#34;https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2016_jcp/&#34;&gt;redundancy can contribute to cultural stabilization&lt;/a&gt;. I am also particularly interested in the opportunities offered by tools like Git or R Markdown to document step-by-step the development of models, as I did for example &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/albertoacerbi/oranzees&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I have rencently published an open access manual on individual-based models in cultural evolution: &lt;a href=&#34;https://acerbialberto.com/IBM-cultevo/&#34;&gt;Individual-based models of cultural evolution. A step-by-step guide using R&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quantitative analysis of large-scale cultural data</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/project/2_culturomics/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/project/2_culturomics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am interested in the analysis of large, naturally occurring, datasets to investigate (especially modern) human cultural dynamics. For example, I used data on dog registrations to analyse &lt;a href=&#34;https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2013_plos_a/&#34;&gt;whether their popularity is due to individual considerations or to social influence&lt;/a&gt; (the latter, it seems), data from Google Books and the Gutenberg project to analyse &lt;a href=&#34;https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2017_cog_emo/&#34;&gt;the change in the expression of emotions&lt;/a&gt; through the last centuries, data on baby names and last.fm playlists to detect whether the &lt;a href=&#34;https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2014_ehb/&#34;&gt;turnover in popularity of cultural traits can give us some indication of the learning biases involved&lt;/a&gt;, or data on folktales, to check whether &lt;a href=&#34;https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2017_ehb/&#34;&gt;their complexity is correlated with the size of the population were they are diffused&lt;/a&gt;. I recently studied &lt;a href=&#34;https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2019_ehs/&#34;&gt;the cultural evolution of emotion words in a large (&amp;gt;150,000 songs) data set of English-language song lyrics&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cultural evolution in the digital age</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/project/3_ceda/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/project/3_ceda/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the last years, I became interested in how cultural evolution can contribute to the study of cultural dynamics in the digital age, and, at the same time, how new digital media impact on human cultural evolution. You can find in my blog a few posts on this. &lt;a href=&#34;https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2016_fhn/&#34;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; a paper where I present some possible areas of interest and &lt;a href=&#34;https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2019_pal_comm_a/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; one where I study online misinformation for a cognitive anthropology perspective. I am currently working on how digital media can enhance cumulative cultural evolution, using the case study of &lt;a href=&#34;https://acerbialberto.com/publication/cp_2020_chr/&#34;&gt;online fan fiction&lt;/a&gt;. I recently finished a book on the topic, &lt;a href=&#34;https://global.oup.com/academic/product/cultural-evolution-in-the-digital-age-9780198835943&#34;&gt;published by Oxford University Press&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cultural evolution and cultural attraction</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/project/4_attraction/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/project/4_attraction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am interested in the theoretical debate between cultural attraction theory and “standard” cultural evolution theory.  While I have &lt;a href=&#34;https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2015_phil_bio/&#34;&gt;argued&lt;/a&gt; that the two approaches are not necessarily in conflict, I believe that cultural attraction theory presents some important points that deserve further empirical investigation. Among them, one is the influence of general cognitive factors on culture, from &lt;a href=&#34;https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2017_ehb/&#34;&gt;folktales&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&#34;https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2019_pal_comm_a/&#34;&gt;online misinformation&lt;/a&gt;. Anoter is the fact that, in some domains, the actual &lt;a href=&#34;https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2018_jocc/&#34;&gt;content&lt;/a&gt; of cultural traits might be more important than contextual or “social” factors to determine their success. Much more on all that is explored in my &lt;a href=&#34;https://global.oup.com/academic/product/cultural-evolution-in-the-digital-age-9780198835943&#34;&gt;book&lt;/a&gt;. I recently worked on a series of &lt;a href=&#34;https://acerbialberto.com/publication/preprint_stability/&#34;&gt;simulation models&lt;/a&gt; that can be considered an attempt to formalise cultural attraction theory.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
