<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>pop culture | Alberto Acerbi</title>
    <link>https://acerbialberto.com/tags/pop-culture/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://acerbialberto.com/tags/pop-culture/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>pop culture</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 10 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://acerbialberto.com/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>pop culture</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/tags/pop-culture/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sentiment analysis of song lyrics by genre</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2020_mxm_genres/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2020_mxm_genres/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a recent &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/evolutionary-human-sciences/article/cultural-evolution-of-emotional-expression-in-50-years-of-song-lyrics/E6E64C02BDB0480DB13B8B6BB7DFF598/core-reader&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href=&#34;https://lottybrand.wordpress.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Lotty Brand&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://alexmesoudi.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Alex Mesoudi&lt;/a&gt;, we documented how the lyrics of popular songs have become sadder in the last few decades. The proportion of words with positive emotional content has decreased and, on the contrary, the proportion of words with negative emotional content has increased, on average, from the 1960s to now. (If you are a reader of this blog you probably already know about all that - if not, see &lt;a href=&#34;https://aeon.co/ideas/why-are-pop-songs-getting-sadder-than-they-used-to-be&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this aeon piece&lt;/a&gt; for more about the research).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several people have suggested that this could be mainly due to the fact that new - sadder or angrier - genres (for example &lt;a href=&#34;https://marginalrevolution.com/marginalrevolution/2020/02/pop-songs-are-getting-sadder-and-angrier.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;hip-hop&lt;/a&gt;) have replaced the genres dominant fifty years ago. This is a sensible hypothesis. In one of the two datasets we used for the main analysis (indicated in the paper as &amp;ldquo;mxm&amp;rdquo; dataset), derived from the lyrics in the website &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.musixmatch.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;musixmatch.com&lt;/a&gt;, songs are also tagged with their genre, so it was relatively straightforward to explore the contribution of each genre to the general trend. The R code and the outputs are available in a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/albertoacerbi/mxm_genres_analysis&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, here the general trends for the &amp;ldquo;mxm&amp;rdquo; dataset. (If you are interested, we explain in the aeon piece linked above what the facts that these numbers are small and that the proportion of negative emotion-words is anyway always lower than the proportion of positive emotion-words mean for the importance of the trends.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./mxm_all.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going to the genre analysis, there are 168 possible genre tags in the dataset, on a total of 159,015 songs, but the most common 20 genres account for 99% of all songs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./genres.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are clear difference in the emotional tone of lyrics in different genres, and they correspond to the general intuition: among the &lt;em&gt;sad&lt;/em&gt; genres there are indeed recently emerged ones, such as &amp;ldquo;Heavy Metal&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Punk&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Hip Hop/Rap&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Indie Rock&amp;rdquo;, or &amp;ldquo;Alternative&amp;rdquo;. (&amp;ldquo;Holiday&amp;rdquo;, the more positive and less negative genre, is basically the Spotify Christmas playlist of your dreams - or nightmares perhaps.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./overall_emo_genres.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can also look at the prevalence of genres through years. Genres like &amp;ldquo;Alternative&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Heavy Metal&amp;rdquo; did indeed grew in popularity, whereas they were completely absent in the 1960s. On the contrary, positively-connotated genres like &amp;ldquo;R&amp;amp;B/Soul&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Christian &amp;amp; Gospel&amp;rdquo; show a strong decrease. Notice &amp;ldquo;Hip Hop/Rap&amp;rdquo; does not appear as growing too much in this dataset, which implies that is not the cause of the increase of negative emotion in lyrics (&lt;em&gt;in this dataset&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./featured.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This suggests that there is some truth in the idea that the overall increase in sadness is due to the emergence of new, sadder, genres. Genres like &amp;ldquo;Alternative&amp;rdquo;, for example, did not show any trend, but their &amp;ldquo;baseline&amp;rdquo;, so to speak, corresponds well to the current levels of negative/positive emotions overall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./mxm_Alternative.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Heavy Metal&amp;rdquo;, consistently with the stereotype, is indeed, on average, a sad genre - as I said on Twitter, &amp;ldquo;unsurprising sentiment analysis results are good sentiment analysis results&amp;rdquo;. In fact, in 2010, the proportion of words expressing negative emotions was &lt;em&gt;higher&lt;/em&gt; than the proportion of words expressing positive emotions, going beyond the overall results (and showing that the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pnas.org/content/112/8/2389&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Polyanna principle&lt;/a&gt; does not hold everywhere&amp;hellip;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./mxm_Heavy_Metal.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, we can see that also &amp;ldquo;Rock&amp;rdquo; and Pop&amp;rdquo;, the two most popular genres in the 1960s and still accounting for more than 30% of the total number of songs in 2010, show clear trends going in the overall direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./mxm_Rock.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./mxm_Pop.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This suggests that the overall trend is not only imputable to the introduction of new genres, but that also &amp;ldquo;classic&amp;rdquo; genres have become sadder. In the same &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/albertoacerbi/mxm_genres_analysis&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;, you can find the correspondent plots for all the 20 genres analysed.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sentiment analysis of Child Ballads&#39; lyrics</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2020_child_ballads/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2020_child_ballads/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./featured.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have recently published, together with &lt;a href=&#34;https://lottybrand.wordpress.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Lotty Brand&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://alexmesoudi.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Alex Mesoudi&lt;/a&gt;, a paper studying the expression of emotions in the lyrics of the last 50 years of English-language pop songs - open access &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/evolutionary-human-sciences/article/cultural-evolution-of-emotional-expression-in-50-years-of-song-lyrics/E6E64C02BDB0480DB13B8B6BB7DFF598/core-reader&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. We try to explain two related empirical findings: the frequency of words with positive emotional content decreases and, on the contrary, the frequency of words with negative emotional content increases in song lyrics. (Both by roughly one third. If, for example, the average song in 1960s had 30 words associated with negative emotion, the average song in 2010s has 40, assuming that they have the same total number of words.) This is a specific aspect of a relatively well-known phenomenon, that has been measured in various ways: pop songs have become sadder in the last decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we added in the paper is an attempt of explaining why this happened. We looked for cultural influences, such as upcoming artists copying the emotional tone from successful, or prestigious, artists of the previous years, but we did not find they were able to explain the pattern. We found, instead, that a general preference for songs with more negative lyrics, coupled with &amp;ldquo;unbiased transmission&amp;rdquo;, i.e. upcoming artists copying at random from the artists of the previous years, could explain it. Of course, upcoming artists do not &amp;ldquo;copy at random&amp;rdquo;: unbiased transmission stands for many unknown processes that cumulatively appear similar to genetic drift, where songs tend to &amp;ldquo;inherit&amp;rdquo; from one year to the other some of their features. The effect of unbiased transmission is important in our statistical model, but unbiased transmission is non-directional, so that a preference for negative lyrics, even if weak, can drive the process. We also wrote a popular piece about it in &lt;a href=&#34;https://aeon.co/ideas/why-are-pop-songs-getting-sadder-than-they-used-to-be&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;aeon&lt;/a&gt;, where we explain more in detail all that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interesting question for me is then why, if there is a general preference for negative lyrics, we observe a &lt;em&gt;trend&lt;/em&gt; toward sadder songs or, in other words, why songs in the 1960s, at the beginning of our datasets, were happier? There are many possible answers here: one, that I thought possible, was that in the middle of last century songs were artificially, so to say, happier, possibly because of more control from centralised broadcasting networks, producers, and similar. It could have been possible that, if few people in the key positions wanted to push happier songs, they could succeed. Or at least, their work would have been easier than now, when we have access to more options, from private radio to recorded tape cassettes to, obviously, Spotify and co. In sum, access to more options allows people to listen to the music they &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; want to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to test this idea? An immediate prediction is that older songs should be sadder than middle-of-last-century songs. After some searches, and a chat with &lt;a href=&#34;https://patrickesavage.wordpress.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Pat Savage&lt;/a&gt;, I found the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Child_Ballads&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Child Ballads&lt;/a&gt;, a collection of 305 traditional ballads, put together in the 19th century. The datation of the ballads is problematic (even though most of them are probably from the 19th century), but the collection fits well in a not-very rigorous, but useful, category of &amp;ldquo;older&amp;rdquo; songs. I extracted the texts from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sacred-texts.com/neu/eng/child/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and performed the same sentiment analysis I have made for the recent pop songs. An obvious problem is that the sentiment analysis (&lt;a href=&#34;http://liwc.wpengine.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;LIWC&lt;/a&gt;, dictionary-based) uses a contemporary lexicon, which may not be suitable for the analysis of old lyrics. A shortcut I used for this (very) exploratory analysis is to also check how many of the words in each songs were recognised by a &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/hunspell/vignettes/intro.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;contemporary English dictionary&lt;/a&gt; and to use this figure to calculate the proportion of positive- and negative-emotion words. All the code is available in a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/albertoacerbi/child_ballads_emo&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
It looks my hypothesis was wrong. The proportion of words associated to emotions, both positive and negative, is more similar to the 1960s figure than to the contemporary one. In sum, old ballads are happier than contemporary pop songs, and in line with pop songs of fifty years ago. (In the plot below, &amp;ldquo;Billboard&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;mxm&amp;rdquo; are the two datasets we used to assess the sentiment of the last fifty years songs. More information in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/evolutionary-human-sciences/article/cultural-evolution-of-emotional-expression-in-50-years-of-song-lyrics/E6E64C02BDB0480DB13B8B6BB7DFF598/core-reader&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; or in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://aeon.co/ideas/why-are-pop-songs-getting-sadder-than-they-used-to-be&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;aeon piece&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./positive.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./negative.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, this is a very basic, and hardly rigorous, analysis. In my intuition old ballads are not exactly cheerful and breezy. Still, apparently, they are, at least when compared to contemporary pop lyrics. What to do with these results, I do not know. Are there more rigorous assessments of sentiment for old song lyrics around? Are Child ballads representative? Other ideas that can explain the contemporary trends? Feedback and advice are welcome as usual!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
