<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>misinformation | Alberto Acerbi</title>
<<<<<<< HEAD
    <link>https://acerbialberto.com/tags/misinformation/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://acerbialberto.com/tags/misinformation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>misinformation</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 09 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://acerbialberto.com/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>misinformation</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/tags/misinformation/</link>
=======
    <link>/tags/misinformation/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tags/misinformation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>misinformation</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 09 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>misinformation</title>
      <link>/tags/misinformation/</link>
>>>>>>> 13c6f5d2904fb25956bb85b4643c352e64cf9372
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Misinformation Is a Threat Because (Other) People are Gullible</title>
<<<<<<< HEAD
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/preprint_misinfo_third_person/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/preprint_misinfo_third_person/</guid>
=======
      <link>/publication/preprint_misinfo_third_person/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/preprint_misinfo_third_person/</guid>
>>>>>>> 13c6f5d2904fb25956bb85b4643c352e64cf9372
      <description>

&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.31234/osf.io/n4qrj&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is fighting fake news a red herring?</title>
<<<<<<< HEAD
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2022_fake_news/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2022_fake_news/</guid>
=======
      <link>/post/2022_fake_news/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2022_fake_news/</guid>
>>>>>>> 13c6f5d2904fb25956bb85b4643c352e64cf9372
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./featured.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fake news spreading on social media is often considered the cause of all bad things happened in the last years. From &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.independent.co.uk/voices/michael-gove-boris-johnson-brexit-eurosceptic-press-theresa-may-a7533806.html&#34;&gt;Brexit&lt;/a&gt; to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/the-fix/wp/2018/04/03/a-new-study-suggests-fake-news-might-have-won-donald-trump-the-2016-election/&#34;&gt;election of Trump&lt;/a&gt;, and later to &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0247642&#34;&gt;covid anti-vaxx sentiments&lt;/a&gt;, examples are not lacking. Of course, &amp;ldquo;bad&amp;rdquo; depends on your point of view, but also vaccines and lockdown &lt;em&gt;support&lt;/em&gt; have been considered a product of &lt;a href=&#34;https://open.spotify.com/episode/3SCsueX2bZdbEzRtKOCEyT&#34;&gt;mass formation psychosis&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am &lt;a href=&#34;https://acerbialberto.wordpress.com/2016/08/16/did-technology-disrupt-the-truth-probably-not/&#34;&gt;long-time sceptical&lt;/a&gt; of this line of reasoning. From a &lt;a href=&#34;https://global.oup.com/academic/product/how-traditions-live-and-die-9780190210502?cc=gb&amp;amp;lang=en&amp;amp;&#34;&gt;cognitive&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://press.princeton.edu/books/hardcover/9780691178707/not-born-yesterday&#34;&gt;evolutionary&lt;/a&gt; perspective on &lt;a href=&#34;https://global.oup.com/academic/product/cultural-evolution-in-the-digital-age-9780198835943?cc=gb&amp;amp;lang=en&amp;amp;&#34;&gt;cultural transmission&lt;/a&gt;, it makes sense to think to humans not as overly gullible individuals, but as wary social learners, that use relatively sophisticated strategies to decide whether to accept social information or not. In fact, recent empirical studies &lt;a href=&#34;https://royalsocietypublishing.org/doi/10.1098/rstb.2020.0052&#34;&gt;show&lt;/a&gt; that apparently we do not use social information enough, even when it would be advantageous. You can replace to the stereotype of gullible individuals the one of stubborn agents: the problem seems to be not that we are too easy to influence, but that we do not change our mind when we should.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It could be, naturally, that the situation brought about with the diffusion of social media is so different from offline dynamics that we just cannot cope. This is a legitimate question. However, the broad picture painted by recent research seems to be consistent: fake news rarely changes our minds. We interact with online misinformation because &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41599-019-0224-y&#34;&gt;is fun or engrossing&lt;/a&gt;, to keep &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41599-020-0452-1&#34;&gt;in contact with others&lt;/a&gt;, to actually &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/21670811.2017.1360143&#34;&gt;debunk it&lt;/a&gt;, or because we are already on the same page, and we want to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/american-political-science-review/article/abs/partisan-polarization-is-the-primary-psychological-motivation-behind-political-fake-news-sharing-on-twitter/3F7D2098CD87AE5501F7AD4A7FA83602&#34;&gt;signal our political or group membership&lt;/a&gt;. But there is more: when considered together with all the information present on social media, the proportion of fake or deceptive news is often negligible. Depending on the criteria used, the proportion of unreliable news online is generally estimated in single digit percentages, with at worst being around 5% of the total proportion of information (see table 1 &lt;a href=&#34;https://misinforeview.hks.harvard.edu/article/research-note-fighting-misinformation-or-fighting-for-information/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for various estimates).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting from this finding, together with &lt;a href=&#34;https://reutersinstitute.politics.ox.ac.uk/people/sacha-altay&#34;&gt;Sacha Altay&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/site/hugomercier/&#34;&gt;Hugo Mercier&lt;/a&gt;, we recently published a &lt;a href=&#34;https://misinforeview.hks.harvard.edu/article/research-note-fighting-misinformation-or-fighting-for-information/&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; that considers how much effort is worth allocating to fight online misinformation. Assume that people believe only some of the reliable news they encounter and only some of the unreliable news. Given the relative paucity of online misinformation, efforts to increase belief in reliable information will have a bigger effect than contrary efforts to decrease belief in unreliable information. To test this intuition (Hugo&amp;rsquo;s intuition&amp;hellip;), we developed a simple model. The figure below illustrates the main result. We started by devising a measure of the total amount of &amp;ldquo;truth&amp;rdquo; in the system (&amp;ldquo;Global information score&amp;rdquo;, on the y-axis in the figure). Think about the &amp;ldquo;Global information score&amp;rdquo; as an index that is maximum (100) when all and only reliable information is trusted, and minimum when only and all unreliable information is (-100). Given a 5% of proportion of unreliable information, if we completely wipe out belief in unreliable information, the Global information score increases of one or two points (in the figure, the difference between the &amp;ldquo;Baseline&amp;rdquo; and the &amp;ldquo;Intervention on misinformation&amp;rdquo; line). If, instead, we leave the belief in misinformation as it is, and we increase of single percentage points the belief in reliable information, we have a bigger effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./figure_1.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This outcome is robust to various realistic estimates of the relative proportion of reliable/unreliable information, to various baseline tendencies to believe reliable/unreliable information, and, as we explore in the model, works when the exposure to news is unequally distributed as in reality (with very few people consuming a lot of pieces of news, and the majority a few), when acceptance of misinformation decreases trust in reliable information, and when acceptance of misinformation increases the supply of misinformation (see again the &lt;a href=&#34;https://misinforeview.hks.harvard.edu/article/research-note-fighting-misinformation-or-fighting-for-information/&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; for details). Of course, the model is bare-bones, but I hope it can be extended to include more realistic characteristics (for example, various typologies of news effects, going beyond reliable versus unreliable news) and to support real policy efforts - which is, well, why we made it in first place&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, yes, the title of this post is provocative, but it makes an important point. As we write in the paper, it is &lt;em&gt;possible&lt;/em&gt; that the relative low proportion of fake news that we observe is indeed due to the efforts that are made to control it. But I do think that the academic and societal attention to &amp;ldquo;fake news&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;infodemic&amp;rdquo;, and the like, is disproportionate. Focusing on reliable news on social media, on their engagement potential, on counteracting the decrease of trust in reliable sources, could be more important that fighting a dubious enemy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assuming that our opponents are motivated by false beliefs (of course, it is the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0747563217306726&#34;&gt;others&lt;/a&gt; that fall for fake news!), beside being probably wrong, is also a way to refuse to understand their motivations and, finally, to preclude confrontation. Maybe understanding their reasons could produce better outcomes. Second, fake news offers a convenient and easy-to-conceptualise explanation for problems that are, probably, complex and rooted in deep socio-economical causes. It looks quite comforting to think that, if we can control better Facebook or Twitter, people would start to think as we do, but if that is not the case, the problems may remain unsolved.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research note: Fighting misinformation or fighting for information?</title>
<<<<<<< HEAD
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2022_hks_misinfo/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2022_hks_misinfo/</guid>
=======
      <link>/publication/2022_hks_misinfo/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/2022_hks_misinfo/</guid>
>>>>>>> 13c6f5d2904fb25956bb85b4643c352e64cf9372
      <description>

&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.37016/mr-2020-87&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Misinformation on Misinformation: Conceptual and Methodological Challenges</title>
<<<<<<< HEAD
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/preprint_misinfo_on_misinfo/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/preprint_misinfo_on_misinfo/</guid>
=======
      <link>/publication/preprint_misinfo_on_misinfo/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/preprint_misinfo_on_misinfo/</guid>
>>>>>>> 13c6f5d2904fb25956bb85b4643c352e64cf9372
      <description>

&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.31234/osf.io/edqc8&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cultural transmission bias in the spread of voter fraud conspiracy theories on Twitter during the 2020 US election</title>
<<<<<<< HEAD
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/preprint_voter_fraud/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/preprint_voter_fraud/</guid>
=======
      <link>/publication/preprint_voter_fraud/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/preprint_voter_fraud/</guid>
>>>>>>> 13c6f5d2904fb25956bb85b4643c352e64cf9372
      <description>

&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.31234/osf.io/2jksg&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cultural evolution in the digital age</title>
<<<<<<< HEAD
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2019_oup/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2019_oup/</guid>
=======
      <link>/publication/2019_oup/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/2019_oup/</guid>
>>>>>>> 13c6f5d2904fb25956bb85b4643c352e64cf9372
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Book Club at &lt;a href=&#34;http://cognitionandculture.net/webinars/cultural-evolution-in-the-digital-age/&#34;&gt;cognitionandculture.net&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;International Cognition and Culture Institute&lt;/em&gt; has organised a book club around Cultural Evolution in the Digital Age running in June and July 2020. The book club includes my precis, commentaries by Alex Mesoudi, Hugo Mercier, Mathieu Charbonneau, Olivier Morin, Pascal Boyer, Sacha Altay, and Tiffany Morisseau, plus my reply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Academic reviews:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Joshua Conrad Jackson, &lt;a href=&#34;https://escholarship.org/uc/item/8hg2441f&#34;&gt;New Technology, Same Culture&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Cliodynamics: The Journal of Quantitative History and Cultural Evolution&lt;/em&gt;, 2020&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With &lt;em&gt;Cultural Evolution in the Digital Age&lt;/em&gt;, Acerbi joins the likes of Peter Turchin, David Sloan Wilson, and Joseph Henrich in offering an engaging and accessible application of cultural evolutionary models, which will almost certainly attract new scholars to the field. Never did I expect to read about Grumpy Cat and the social brain hypothesis in the same book, but the result was genuinely satisfying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stefan Velesky, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jstor.org/stable/10.26613/esic.4.2.195&#34;&gt;Review of Cultural Evolution in the Digital Age&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Evolutionary Studies in Imaginative Culture&lt;/em&gt;, 2020&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Cultural Evolution in the Digital Age,&lt;/em&gt; Acerbi combines cultural evolution with cognitive anthropology and media studies to provide one of the most solid science-based takes on the impact of digital media on human behavior to date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Andrew Buskell, &lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10441-020-09384-x&#34;&gt;Evolution, Cultural Evolution, and Epistemic Optimism&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Acta Biotheoretica&lt;/em&gt;, 2020&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&amp;hellip;] enjoyable, story-driven journey. [&amp;hellip;] guide the reader through large and expanding literatures in an entertaining and illuminating way. [&amp;hellip;] upbeat about human capabilities and provide a useful optimistic counterpoint to the recent spate of epistemological doomsayers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oleg Sobchuk, &lt;a href=&#34;https://academic.oup.com/joc/advance-article-abstract/doi/10.1093/joc/jqaa038/6124730&#34;&gt;Cultural Evolution in the Digital Age&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Journal of Communication&lt;/em&gt;, 2021&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book by the anthropologist Alberto Acerbi builds a bridge between the field of media and communication studies and a rather new approach to studying culture: cultural evolution. Can this bridge be a firm structure? And do media studies and cultural evolution even need each other? Acerbi makes a persuasive case for the usefulness and importance of this connection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Simone Marsi, &lt;a href=&#34;https://ojs.unica.it/index.php/between/article/view/5245&#34;&gt;Cultural Evolution in the Digital Age&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Between&lt;/em&gt;, 2022 (Italian)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Con rigore scientifico, poggiando i piedi su esperimenti di antropologia e riflessioni scientifiche sull’evoluzionismo, Acerbi ci conduce in un inedito viaggio nella nostra quotidianità, disvelando pregiudizi e falsi miti sul mondo digitale, che sottratto al dibattito tra apocalittici della società reale e guru integrati nel mondo dei social, ci viene riproposto come un luogo in cui l’uomo mette in scena sé stesso, con i suoi difetti più torbidi e la sua più alta aspirazione alla conoscenza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;General reviews:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Acerbi advocates for a moderate approach to understanding the impact of digital media. Taking the &amp;ldquo;long view&amp;rdquo; provides a more accurate assessment than alarmist reactions. [&amp;hellip;] Acerbi&amp;rsquo;s book is filled with hope; it is not a Pollyanna assessment of the digital world but a balanced view.&amp;rdquo; - &lt;em&gt;Choice&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Media coverage:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/AX0Jy0__DbE&#34;&gt;Interview for the podcast &amp;lsquo;The Dissenter&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cs.eslrsociety.org/2020/07/15/cultural-evolution-in-the-digital-age/&#34;&gt;Interview for Cultured Scene, the Early Career Social Learning Researcher&amp;rsquo;s Society magazine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.trouw.nl/wetenschap/sturen-algoritmen-ons-gedrag-dat-valt-best-mee~ba0035f5/&#34;&gt;Sturen algoritmen ons gedrag? Dat valt best mee&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Trouw&lt;/em&gt; (The Netherlands)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lepoint.fr/phebe/phebe-tout-ce-que-vous-pensiez-savoir-d-internet-est-sans-doute-faux-07-02-2020-2361661_3590.php#&#34;&gt;Tout ce que vous pensiez savoir d&amp;rsquo;Internet est (sans doute) faux&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Le Point&lt;/em&gt; (France)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-isbn=&#34;9780198835943&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cognitive attraction and online misinformation</title>
<<<<<<< HEAD
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2019_pal_comm_a/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2019_pal_comm_a/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote a presentation of the research behind the paper in &lt;a href=&#34;https://acerbialberto.com/post/2019_morgue/&#34;&gt;this blog post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
=======
      <link>/publication/2019_pal_comm_a/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/2019_pal_comm_a/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote a presentation of the research behind the paper in &lt;a href=&#34;/post/2019_morgue/&#34;&gt;this blog post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
>>>>>>> 13c6f5d2904fb25956bb85b4643c352e64cf9372
&lt;p&gt;An &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cicap.org/n/articolo.php?id=278920&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; (in Italian) summarising the paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another popular &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lepoint.fr/phebe/phebe-les-vraies-raisons-du-succes-des-infox-09-09-2019-2334367_3590.php&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; (in French).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1057/s41599-019-0224-y&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A cultural evolution approach to digital media</title>
<<<<<<< HEAD
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2016_fhn/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2016_fhn/</guid>
=======
      <link>/publication/2016_fhn/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/2016_fhn/</guid>
>>>>>>> 13c6f5d2904fb25956bb85b4643c352e64cf9372
      <description>

&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.3389/fnhum.2016.00636&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
