<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>digital media | Alberto Acerbi</title>
    <link>https://acerbialberto.com/tags/digital-media/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://acerbialberto.com/tags/digital-media/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>digital media</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://acerbialberto.com/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>digital media</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/tags/digital-media/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Self-Interest, prosociality, and the moral cognition of markets: A comparative analysis of the Theory of Moral Sentiments and the Wealth of Nations</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2023_adam_smith/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2023_adam_smith/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1177/10434631231170460&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sentiment analysis of the Twitter response to Netflix&#39;s Our Planet documentary</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2023_our_planet/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2023_our_planet/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1111/cobi.14060&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Digital Culture</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/cp_2023_oxford_handbook/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/cp_2023_oxford_handbook/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>People believe misinformation is a threat because they assume others are gullible</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2023_misinfo_third_person/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2023_misinfo_third_person/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1177/14614448231153379&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Misinformation on Misinformation: Conceptual and Methodological Challenges</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2023_misinfo_on_misinfo/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2023_misinfo_on_misinfo/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;110.1177/20563051221150412&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why too much focus on online misinformation is a problem</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2023_focus_misinfo/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2023_focus_misinfo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./featured.gif&#34; alt=&#34;gif&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Together with &lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/view/sacha-altay/home&#34;&gt;Sacha Altay&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://manonberriche.github.io&#34;&gt;Manon Berriche&lt;/a&gt;, we just published a new article in &lt;em&gt;Social Media + Society&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/20563051221150412&#34;&gt;Misinformation on Misinformation: Conceptual and Methodological Challenges&lt;/a&gt;. The article puts together, in an hopefully coherent framework, a number of criticisms to current research on online misinformation that we discussed and developed in a more informal way in the past (several) years. If you know our research, it may not come as a surprise that we tend to be wary of a scaremongering approach to online misinformation, proposing instead that there may be nothing particularly surprising in the (limited) current spread of misinformation and that, if anything, misinformation is not much of a problem by itself, but a symptom of more deep, and important, societal problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, these ideas are quite controversial today, but this is not what I want to explore in this short post: you can read the article, which is exactly about that and it is written for a - relatively - large audience. I want to focus on another aspect. I had the impression that, for some people at least, by minimising the danger of misinformation, we are siding with the &amp;ldquo;bad guys&amp;rdquo;. These bad guys being either big social media companies or vaguely right-wingish figures, which claim that the fight against misinformation is the way the &amp;ldquo;establishment&amp;rdquo; suppresses dissenting voices (&lt;a href=&#34;https://goofynomics.blogspot.com/2023/02/disinformare-sulla-disinformazione.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; an Italian example of this).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am unsuccessful enough as a public persona to not be too worried about being associated to the bad guys, but I think it is quite misguided. First, downplaying the importance of online misinformation is hardly playing into big social media companies&amp;rsquo; hands. On the contrary, the continuous attention to online misinformation provides both an analogous continuous attention to the activity of social media companies and support to the (I think wrong) idea that what happens on social media has a determinant influence on seemingly any event. If you are Elon Musk, you would certainly prefer people thinking that Twitter can change election results or even the course of a pandemic, than thinking that it does not matter that much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my all-time favourite here is an Economist&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.economist.com/prospero/2019/07/24/the-great-hack-is-a-misinformed-documentary-about-misinformation&#34;&gt;review&lt;/a&gt; of &amp;ldquo;The Great Hack&amp;rdquo;, a documentary about Cambridge Analytica: &amp;ldquo;So credulous is “The Great Hack” that if Cambridge Analytica had not shut down, its bosses would be using the movie as a testimonial&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or, let me quote from &lt;a href=&#34;https://harpers.org/archive/2021/09/bad-news-selling-the-story-of-disinformation/&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; excellent article:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ironically, to the extent that this work creates undue alarm about disinformation, it supports Facebook’s sales pitch. What could be more appealing to an advertiser, after all, than a machine that can persuade anyone of anything? This understanding benefits Facebook, which spreads more bad information, which creates more alarm. Legacy outlets with usefully prestigious brands are taken on board as trusted partners, to determine when the levels of contamination in the information ecosystem (from which they have magically detached themselves) get too high. For the old media institutions, it’s a bid for relevance, a form of self-preservation. For the tech platforms, it’s a superficial strategy to avoid deeper questions. A trusted disinformation field is, in this sense, a very useful thing for Mark Zuckerberg.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This quote also hints to another important point: how the focus on misinformation may be a &amp;ldquo;superficial strategy to avoid deeper questions&amp;rdquo;. We do not have good support for the idea that misinformation &lt;em&gt;causes&lt;/em&gt; bad outcomes outside of social media. Really, we do not (you can read much more about this in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/20563051221150412&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt;). &lt;em&gt;Assuming&lt;/em&gt; that it does, when what we want to assess are exactly the effects of misinformation, is putting the cart before the horse. In a world with unlimited resources this could not be a problem. Maybe (maybe) zero misinformation is better than some misinformation. However, we do not live a world with unlimited resources. When people claim that, say, to increase vaccinations we need to fight misinformation, they are using time - and, mostly, a lot of resources - assuming that misinformation causes people not vaccinating themselves. But if that is not the case, we are wasting time, and a lot of resources. More, we are not considering the importance of deeper issues, focusing our efforts on dubious technological fixes. Perhaps, in the case of vaccination, we should work on the reasons behind the luck of trust in science, institutions, reliable news sources, and so on. And, unfortunately, these reasons may have even deeper social, economical, and cultural causes, but, hey, &amp;ldquo;fake news&amp;rdquo;!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From storytelling to Facebook</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2022_from_storytelling/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2022_from_storytelling/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./featured.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are starting to have some suggestion about what kind of content is advantaged on social media, all other things being equal. Good candidates are &lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s42761-021-00057-7&#34;&gt;negative&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s42761-021-00046-w&#34;&gt;content&lt;/a&gt;, generally &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pnas.org/doi/10.1073/pnas.1618923114?url_ver=Z39.88-2003&amp;amp;rfr_id=ori:rid:crossref.org&amp;amp;rfr_dat=cr_pub%20%200pubmed&#34;&gt;emotional&lt;/a&gt; content, or &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pnas.org/doi/full/10.1073/pnas.2024292118&#34;&gt;out-group&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/american-political-science-review/article/abs/partisan-polarization-is-the-primary-psychological-motivation-behind-political-fake-news-sharing-on-twitter/3F7D2098CD87AE5501F7AD4A7FA83602&#34;&gt;detraction&lt;/a&gt; (link to some papers if you click on the contents).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These effects, albeit generally quite small, are interesting, and they are consistent with the broadly accepted narrative that social media have a detrimental influence on human communication and social interactions. This may definitely be true, but what I believe is an important missing piece is a contrast with other forms of communication and social interactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, how do we know that it is &lt;em&gt;because of social media&lt;/em&gt; that negative content - or emotional, or partisan, etc. - is favoured? To answer this question, we would need to isolate the features of social media we suppose are behind the effect, and compare situations in which these features are present and not, and we should be able to show that, say, negative content is favoured when the features are present, and not when they are not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can consider other forms of communication, and see what are the features that differ with respect to social media-mediated communication. An obvious starting point is oral, face-to-face, communication, a form of social interaction that has been dominant for the majority of human history (and partly still is). There are various studies in cultural evolution, for example, that show how &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1163%2F15685373-12342189&#34;&gt;emotional&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1090513816301660&#34;&gt;negative&lt;/a&gt; content is favoured also in experiments that reproduce situations similar to oral transmission. How does oral communication differ from social media-mediated communication? First, anonymity is, though not impossible, difficult to implement in oral communication, while it is easier to implement in social media. Second, oral communication generally takes place in small group, where people often know each other. Third, the oral back-and-forth requires understanding, memorisation, and (re)production, while in social media one just need to decide what to share (understanding itself is not required if memorisation and reproduction are not needed).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, there could be other interesting differences (suggestions welcome!), but let&amp;rsquo;s stop here. I recently published a &lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s12110-022-09423-1&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; where I tried to do something similar, focusing on the last difference. I used &amp;ldquo;attractive&amp;rdquo; content that was found to be advantaged in recall and transmission in cultural evolution experiments - negative, eliciting disgust, and threat-related - and I compared it to a &amp;ldquo;neutral&amp;rdquo; version of the same content, i.e. without the elements making it negative, etc. The first, experiment, let&amp;rsquo;s call it &amp;ldquo;storytelling&amp;rdquo; scenario, was a situation resembling oral transmission (participants had to listen - actually read on a computer screen - a story and then retell - write - it to another participant, and so on) and the second one, &amp;ldquo;social media&amp;rdquo; scenario, was resembling online sharing (participants had to read a story and decide whether they would share it or not).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Long story short, the results presented a mixed picture (experiments and analyses were fully &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/wf7pd&#34;&gt;preregistered&lt;/a&gt;, maybe there is a connection here?!), but two suggestions can be summarised here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Negative content was the only content that was both better recalled and transmitted in the &amp;ldquo;storytelling&amp;rdquo; experiment and shared in the &amp;ldquo;social media&amp;rdquo; experiment with respect to its neutral counterpart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, attractive contents seem to be more advantaged in the &amp;ldquo;storytelling&amp;rdquo; than in the &amp;ldquo;social media&amp;rdquo; scenario. On one side, this seem reasonable, if we think that this content is attractive because of its properties, and its properties impact on understanding, memorisation, etc. On the other side, is feels surprising as we tend to believe that social media communication is &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; biased than oral one. (While I like this result, it needs to be said that the kind of content was chosen because advantaged in experiments resembling oral transmission.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All data and code to reproduce the analysis are available &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/5yh4u/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To conclude: as usual, things are complicated, but I do think that comparing social media communication with other forms of communication is the only way to understand the possible causal effect of social media. In addition, if we could isolate the undesirable features (if any), we could design specific, targeted, interventions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research note: Fighting misinformation or fighting for information?</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2022_hks_misinfo/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2022_hks_misinfo/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.37016/mr-2020-87&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cultural transmission bias in the spread of voter fraud conspiracy theories on Twitter during the 2020 US election</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/preprint_voter_fraud/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/preprint_voter_fraud/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.31234/osf.io/2jksg&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cultural Accumulation and Improvement in Online Fan Fiction</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/cp_2020_chr/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/cp_2020_chr/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The impact of the “World’s 25 Most Endangered Primates” list on scientific publications and media</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2020_jnc/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2020_jnc/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1016/j.jnc.2020.125794&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cultural evolution in the digital age</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2019_oup/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2019_oup/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Book Club at &lt;a href=&#34;http://cognitionandculture.net/webinars/cultural-evolution-in-the-digital-age/&#34;&gt;cognitionandculture.net&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;International Cognition and Culture Institute&lt;/em&gt; has organised a book club around Cultural Evolution in the Digital Age running in June and July 2020. The book club includes my precis, commentaries by Alex Mesoudi, Hugo Mercier, Mathieu Charbonneau, Olivier Morin, Pascal Boyer, Sacha Altay, and Tiffany Morisseau, plus my reply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Academic reviews:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Joshua Conrad Jackson, &lt;a href=&#34;https://escholarship.org/uc/item/8hg2441f&#34;&gt;New Technology, Same Culture&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Cliodynamics: The Journal of Quantitative History and Cultural Evolution&lt;/em&gt;, 2020&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With &lt;em&gt;Cultural Evolution in the Digital Age&lt;/em&gt;, Acerbi joins the likes of Peter Turchin, David Sloan Wilson, and Joseph Henrich in offering an engaging and accessible application of cultural evolutionary models, which will almost certainly attract new scholars to the field. Never did I expect to read about Grumpy Cat and the social brain hypothesis in the same book, but the result was genuinely satisfying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stefan Velesky, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jstor.org/stable/10.26613/esic.4.2.195&#34;&gt;Review of Cultural Evolution in the Digital Age&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Evolutionary Studies in Imaginative Culture&lt;/em&gt;, 2020&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Cultural Evolution in the Digital Age,&lt;/em&gt; Acerbi combines cultural evolution with cognitive anthropology and media studies to provide one of the most solid science-based takes on the impact of digital media on human behavior to date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Andrew Buskell, &lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10441-020-09384-x&#34;&gt;Evolution, Cultural Evolution, and Epistemic Optimism&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Acta Biotheoretica&lt;/em&gt;, 2020&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&amp;hellip;] enjoyable, story-driven journey. [&amp;hellip;] guide the reader through large and expanding literatures in an entertaining and illuminating way. [&amp;hellip;] upbeat about human capabilities and provide a useful optimistic counterpoint to the recent spate of epistemological doomsayers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oleg Sobchuk, &lt;a href=&#34;https://academic.oup.com/joc/advance-article-abstract/doi/10.1093/joc/jqaa038/6124730&#34;&gt;Cultural Evolution in the Digital Age&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Journal of Communication&lt;/em&gt;, 2021&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book by the anthropologist Alberto Acerbi builds a bridge between the field of media and communication studies and a rather new approach to studying culture: cultural evolution. Can this bridge be a firm structure? And do media studies and cultural evolution even need each other? Acerbi makes a persuasive case for the usefulness and importance of this connection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Simone Marsi, &lt;a href=&#34;https://ojs.unica.it/index.php/between/article/view/5245&#34;&gt;Cultural Evolution in the Digital Age&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Between&lt;/em&gt;, 2022 (Italian)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Con rigore scientifico, poggiando i piedi su esperimenti di antropologia e riflessioni scientifiche sull’evoluzionismo, Acerbi ci conduce in un inedito viaggio nella nostra quotidianità, disvelando pregiudizi e falsi miti sul mondo digitale, che sottratto al dibattito tra apocalittici della società reale e guru integrati nel mondo dei social, ci viene riproposto come un luogo in cui l’uomo mette in scena sé stesso, con i suoi difetti più torbidi e la sua più alta aspirazione alla conoscenza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;General reviews:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Acerbi advocates for a moderate approach to understanding the impact of digital media. Taking the &amp;ldquo;long view&amp;rdquo; provides a more accurate assessment than alarmist reactions. [&amp;hellip;] Acerbi&amp;rsquo;s book is filled with hope; it is not a Pollyanna assessment of the digital world but a balanced view.&amp;quot; - &lt;em&gt;Choice&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Media coverage:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/AX0Jy0__DbE&#34;&gt;Interview for the podcast &amp;lsquo;The Dissenter&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cs.eslrsociety.org/2020/07/15/cultural-evolution-in-the-digital-age/&#34;&gt;Interview for Cultured Scene, the Early Career Social Learning Researcher&amp;rsquo;s Society magazine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.trouw.nl/wetenschap/sturen-algoritmen-ons-gedrag-dat-valt-best-mee~ba0035f5/&#34;&gt;Sturen algoritmen ons gedrag? Dat valt best mee&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Trouw&lt;/em&gt; (The Netherlands)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lepoint.fr/phebe/phebe-tout-ce-que-vous-pensiez-savoir-d-internet-est-sans-doute-faux-07-02-2020-2361661_3590.php#&#34;&gt;Tout ce que vous pensiez savoir d&amp;rsquo;Internet est (sans doute) faux&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Le Point&lt;/em&gt; (France)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-isbn=&#34;9780198835943&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cognitive attraction and online misinformation</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2019_pal_comm_a/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2019_pal_comm_a/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote a presentation of the research behind the paper in &lt;a href=&#34;https://acerbialberto.com/post/2019_morgue/&#34;&gt;this blog post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cicap.org/n/articolo.php?id=278920&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; (in Italian) summarising the paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another popular &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lepoint.fr/phebe/phebe-les-vraies-raisons-du-succes-des-infox-09-09-2019-2334367_3590.php&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; (in French).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1057/s41599-019-0224-y&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A cultural evolution approach to digital media</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2016_fhn/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2016_fhn/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.3389/fnhum.2016.00636&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
