<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Alberto Acerbi</title>
    <link>https://acerbialberto.com/authors/admin/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://acerbialberto.com/authors/admin/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Alberto Acerbi</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 21 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://acerbialberto.com/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Alberto Acerbi</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/authors/admin/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Machine Culture</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2023_nhb/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2023_nhb/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1038/s41562-023-01742-2&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Large language models show human-like content biases in transmission chain experiment</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2023_pnas/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2023_pnas/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1073/pnas.2313790120&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Postdoc position</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2023_postdoc/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2023_postdoc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./featured.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am advertising a two-year postdoc position in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sociologia.unitn.it/en&#34;&gt;Department of Sociology and Social Research&lt;/a&gt;  in Trento, possibly starting from December 2023, broadly on analysis of social media data from a cultural evolution perspective. The application deadline is the 15th of November (12am Italian time); candidates can apply &lt;a href=&#34;https://lavoraconnoi.unitn.it/assegni-di-ricerca/dipartimento-di-sociologia-e-ricerca-sociale-avviso-di-selezione-il-conferimento-di-n-1-assegno-34&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I tried to put together a &amp;ldquo;light&amp;rdquo; application: beside the mandatory CV and list of publication, the candidates need to submit only a page where they explain if and how they meet the desirable qualifications (see below). All the detailed information are at the link above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The postdoc will work in a project funded by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.templeton.org&#34;&gt;John Templeton Foundation&lt;/a&gt; on &amp;ldquo;Changing the perspective on social media interventions: improving engagement with true news&amp;rdquo;. The basic idea, explored at length in &lt;a href=&#34;https://misinforeview.hks.harvard.edu/article/research-note-fighting-misinformation-or-fighting-for-information/&#34;&gt;this paper&lt;/a&gt; with Sacha Altay and Hugo Mercier, is that, to improve the social media informational ecosystem, we should focus on increasing the engagement with true news, rather than fighting the diffusion of misinformation. More in details, the project identified four features of content that increase engagement with information: negative content, emotional content in general, threat-related information, and out-group detraction. We will collect a large dataset of social media messages related to news from outlets of different political orientations and examine if these features of content will predict engagement with true/reliable news, and what kind of engagement, by including in the analysis also reactions and comments. Given the recent mess with social media (thank you Elon), we will be relatively free about which data exactly to collect, and possibly to modify various aspects of the research questions, as long as they fit with the basic idea. (Optimistically, it could be an interesting time to analyse the consequences of the changing social media informational landscape.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The essential requisites are a PhD in any related discipline (social and psychological sciences, data/computer sciences, etc.) and good programming experience with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.r-project.org&#34;&gt;R language&lt;/a&gt;. Experience with collection and analysis of data from social media, NLP (text mining, sentiment analysis, etc.), open science (e.g. preregistration, managing open data repositories), collaborative programming tools (e.g. GitHub), and statistical modelling are desirable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am completely open to remote work - as I did myself several postdocs, I know it can be annoying to relocate for a non-permanent contract and I have/had myself several long-distance collaborations - but, if one has the possibility, living in Trento could be a plus. Trento is a beautiful town in the Dolomites and it is consistently at the top ranks for quality of life in Italy (as I now live here, I can confirm). The Department of Sociology and Social Research is very research-active, and the postdoc will participate in the activities of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://c2s2.unitn.it&#34;&gt;C2S2 - Centre for Computational Social Science and Human Dynamics&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The salary is in the top tier of Italian postdoc (gross 38,900 Euros/year) and the grant include research and travel money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lavoraconnoi.unitn.it/assegni-di-ricerca/dipartimento-di-sociologia-e-ricerca-sociale-avviso-di-selezione-il-conferimento-di-n-1-assegno-34&#34;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; again the link to apply, and if you are interested or have any question feel free to get in contact with me!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Two thoughts on Manovich&#39;s &#34;Cultural Analytics&#34;</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2023_manovich/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2023_manovich/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./featured.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year I had the occasion to teach my first - and probably one of the first, if not &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; first, in Italy - course of Cultural Analytics (kudos to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sociologia.unitn.it/en&#34;&gt;Department of Sociology and Social Research&lt;/a&gt; of Trento for the boldness). Among many other things, it gave me the occasion to decide how much using of the &amp;ldquo;foundational&amp;rdquo; Lev Manovich text in the program. &lt;em&gt;Cultural Analytics&lt;/em&gt; has also been &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.raffaellocortina.it/scheda-libro/lev-manovich/cultural-analytics-9788832854978-3891.html&#34;&gt;recently translated in Italian&lt;/a&gt; (while we&amp;rsquo;re at it: kudos also to Raffaello Cortina Editore) generating some attention, at least in a small niche of Italian researchers interested in the topic. Therefore, I am taking some time to share a couple of thoughts about it - maybe one day I should write a proper review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, how much did I use of it? Well, not much, a part from various mentions in the introductory lecture, when trying to define what cultural analytics was for me, and how in fact it was different from what sketched in the book. My first concern is indeed about the actual scope of cultural analytics. According to Manovich, cultural analytics is &amp;ldquo;the analysis of &lt;strong&gt;massive&lt;/strong&gt; cultural datasets and flows using computational and visualization techniques.” (bold added, this is not from the book, but from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://culturalanalytics.org/article/11060-the-science-of-culture-social-computing-digital-humanities-and-cultural-analytics&#34;&gt;introductory article&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;em&gt;Journal of Cultural Analytics&lt;/em&gt;) and &amp;ldquo;The scale of culture in the twenty-first century makes it impossible to see it with existing methods […] cultural analytics refers to […] exploration and analysis of &lt;strong&gt;contemporary&lt;/strong&gt; culture at scale&amp;rdquo; (bold mine again, this is from the book.) Does cultural analytics need to concern only massive and contemporary datasets? Big data are undoubtedly important for cultural analytics research. The exponential growth in the number and size of freely available data sets - both “traditional” data that are digitised (books, paintings, news corpora, etc.) thus easy to process, and “new” data (social media, online reviews, web searches, etc.) clearly made possible the (relative) explosion of computational studies of culture, but are there reasons to exclude the rest? Analysis of small and old datasets are common in digital humanities - say Franco Moretti&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://oldemc.english.ucsb.edu/emc-courses/Novel-Mediation-S2011/novel-mediation/Articles/Moretti.style.pdf&#34;&gt;Style, Inc. Reflections on Seven Thousand Titles (British Novels, 1740–1850)&lt;/a&gt;, the title says it all - and are there reasons why this is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; cultural analytics? I do not see any.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, and more importantly, my impression is that the book is pervaded by the idea that with good visualizations, good analyses, and big &lt;em&gt;enough&lt;/em&gt; data, the explanatory power will come by itself. In one of the opening examples of the book (full article &lt;a href=&#34;http://manovich.net/content/04-projects/071-how-to-compare/68_article_2011_sm.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), Manovich describes a visualization of more than a million of manga covers, oriented on the axis by standard deviation of pixels’ grayscale values in a page (from least to highest contrast) and by entropy measured over all pixels’ grayscale values in a page (from least details to a lot of details). The visualization is fascinating, and the conclusion is that there are not clear divisions among areas of the figure, making concepts like discrete &amp;ldquo;styles&amp;rdquo; not very meaningful. This is quite interesting, but what is the hypothesis tested? How does this fit in a broader, more satisfying (at least for me), theory of culture? As mentioned, these do not seem, according to Manovich, important goals for cultural analytics, that gets defined by its quite specific subject, &amp;ldquo;analysis of all kinds of media&amp;rdquo; in &amp;ldquo;contemporary digital culture&amp;rdquo;. I spent years, with many others, to sell the idea that &amp;ldquo;big data needs big theory&amp;rdquo;, and I am pretty sure you suspect the theory (or the set of ideas) I have in mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps I am not doing cultural analytics, and I should use another name? Computational analysis of culture? Even &amp;ldquo;Computational evolutionary analysis of culture&amp;rdquo;? Is this important?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, of course, there are many other points on which I wholeheartedly agree with the book (just to mention one, the importance of the analyses of visual aspects of culture that, for practical reasons, are often overlooked in computational studies of culture) and I guess that, among other social scientists, we would probably look like doing exactly the same thing, but maybe there are other ten or fifteen persons that could be interested about that!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Negativity bias in the spread of voter fraud conspiracy theory tweets during the 2020 US election</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2023_voter_fraud/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2023_voter_fraud/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1057/s41599-023-02106-x&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Self-Interest, prosociality, and the moral cognition of markets: A comparative analysis of the Theory of Moral Sentiments and the Wealth of Nations</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2023_adam_smith/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2023_adam_smith/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1177/10434631231170460&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sentiment analysis of the Twitter response to Netflix&#39;s Our Planet documentary</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2023_our_planet/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2023_our_planet/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1111/cobi.14060&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Digital Culture</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/cp_2023_oxford_handbook/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/cp_2023_oxford_handbook/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1093/oxfordhb/9780198869252.013.41
&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>People believe misinformation is a threat because they assume others are gullible</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2023_misinfo_third_person/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2023_misinfo_third_person/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1177/14614448231153379&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Misinformation on Misinformation: Conceptual and Methodological Challenges</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2023_misinfo_on_misinfo/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2023_misinfo_on_misinfo/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;110.1177/20563051221150412&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why too much focus on online misinformation is a problem</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2023_focus_misinfo/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2023_focus_misinfo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./featured.gif&#34; alt=&#34;gif&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Together with &lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/view/sacha-altay/home&#34;&gt;Sacha Altay&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://manonberriche.github.io&#34;&gt;Manon Berriche&lt;/a&gt;, we just published a new article in &lt;em&gt;Social Media + Society&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/20563051221150412&#34;&gt;Misinformation on Misinformation: Conceptual and Methodological Challenges&lt;/a&gt;. The article puts together, in an hopefully coherent framework, a number of criticisms to current research on online misinformation that we discussed and developed in a more informal way in the past (several) years. If you know our research, it may not come as a surprise that we tend to be wary of a scaremongering approach to online misinformation, proposing instead that there may be nothing particularly surprising in the (limited) current spread of misinformation and that, if anything, misinformation is not much of a problem by itself, but a symptom of more deep, and important, societal problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, these ideas are quite controversial today, but this is not what I want to explore in this short post: you can read the article, which is exactly about that and it is written for a - relatively - large audience. I want to focus on another aspect. I had the impression that, for some people at least, by minimising the danger of misinformation, we are siding with the &amp;ldquo;bad guys&amp;rdquo;. These bad guys being either big social media companies or vaguely right-wingish figures, which claim that the fight against misinformation is the way the &amp;ldquo;establishment&amp;rdquo; suppresses dissenting voices (&lt;a href=&#34;https://goofynomics.blogspot.com/2023/02/disinformare-sulla-disinformazione.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; an Italian example of this).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am unsuccessful enough as a public persona to not be too worried about being associated to the bad guys, but I think it is quite misguided. First, downplaying the importance of online misinformation is hardly playing into big social media companies&amp;rsquo; hands. On the contrary, the continuous attention to online misinformation provides both an analogous continuous attention to the activity of social media companies and support to the (I think wrong) idea that what happens on social media has a determinant influence on seemingly any event. If you are Elon Musk, you would certainly prefer people thinking that Twitter can change election results or even the course of a pandemic, than thinking that it does not matter that much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my all-time favourite here is an Economist&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.economist.com/prospero/2019/07/24/the-great-hack-is-a-misinformed-documentary-about-misinformation&#34;&gt;review&lt;/a&gt; of &amp;ldquo;The Great Hack&amp;rdquo;, a documentary about Cambridge Analytica: &amp;ldquo;So credulous is “The Great Hack” that if Cambridge Analytica had not shut down, its bosses would be using the movie as a testimonial&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or, let me quote from &lt;a href=&#34;https://harpers.org/archive/2021/09/bad-news-selling-the-story-of-disinformation/&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; excellent article:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ironically, to the extent that this work creates undue alarm about disinformation, it supports Facebook’s sales pitch. What could be more appealing to an advertiser, after all, than a machine that can persuade anyone of anything? This understanding benefits Facebook, which spreads more bad information, which creates more alarm. Legacy outlets with usefully prestigious brands are taken on board as trusted partners, to determine when the levels of contamination in the information ecosystem (from which they have magically detached themselves) get too high. For the old media institutions, it’s a bid for relevance, a form of self-preservation. For the tech platforms, it’s a superficial strategy to avoid deeper questions. A trusted disinformation field is, in this sense, a very useful thing for Mark Zuckerberg.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This quote also hints to another important point: how the focus on misinformation may be a &amp;ldquo;superficial strategy to avoid deeper questions&amp;rdquo;. We do not have good support for the idea that misinformation &lt;em&gt;causes&lt;/em&gt; bad outcomes outside of social media. Really, we do not (you can read much more about this in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/20563051221150412&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt;). &lt;em&gt;Assuming&lt;/em&gt; that it does, when what we want to assess are exactly the effects of misinformation, is putting the cart before the horse. In a world with unlimited resources this could not be a problem. Maybe (maybe) zero misinformation is better than some misinformation. However, we do not live a world with unlimited resources. When people claim that, say, to increase vaccinations we need to fight misinformation, they are using time - and, mostly, a lot of resources - assuming that misinformation causes people not vaccinating themselves. But if that is not the case, we are wasting time, and a lot of resources. More, we are not considering the importance of deeper issues, focusing our efforts on dubious technological fixes. Perhaps, in the case of vaccination, we should work on the reasons behind the luck of trust in science, institutions, reliable news sources, and so on. And, unfortunately, these reasons may have even deeper social, economical, and cultural causes, but, hey, &amp;ldquo;fake news&amp;rdquo;!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unxeroxing culture</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2023_unxeroxing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2023_unxeroxing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./featured.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Believe it or not, this post is more than three years in the making (I can prove it with a talk in Stockholm, &lt;a href=&#34;https://acerbialberto.com/talk/2019_stockholm/&#34;&gt;dated december 2019&lt;/a&gt;, where I was starting to put together the argument), but, as academic publishing goes, the three papers that were supposed to be part of it are only out now, so here it is. The topic is hardly new, in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dan.sperber.fr/wp-content/uploads/1991_atran_learning-without-teaching-its-place-in-culture.pdf&#34;&gt;general&lt;/a&gt; and for me, and it is a classic in the so-called Paris school of cultural evolution - in fact, I may have stolen the xerox analogy from Olivier Morin&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://global.oup.com/academic/product/how-traditions-live-and-die-9780190210502?cc=gb&amp;amp;lang=en&amp;amp;&#34;&gt;book&lt;/a&gt; - but here is my version. (Maybe the last one?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is an apparent paradox: on one side, humans are clearly cultural animals. Everything we see, do, use, results from accumulated knowledge that we could not re-invent by ourselves. Vaccines and electric cars, sure, but also kinship systems and lasagne. Nothing controversial here. On the other side, however (here the controversial part), humans do not seem to copy others that much. We rarely blindly copy others&amp;rsquo; actions and beliefs in the details: in general, we reconstruct them accordingly to our previous beliefs and interests. Rich domain-specific shared knowledge influences what and how we learn from others. Finally, experiments show that, even when we should - and could easily - copy from others, we do it less than what would be optimal (more on this below). How can we reconcile these two observations? In general, cultural evolutionists tend to minimise the importance of the second observation: we copy &lt;em&gt;enough&lt;/em&gt; to keep the machinery on, and that is the important part. Or, according to some readings, evolutionary psychologists tend to to minimise the first bit: many - or more that one would think - &amp;ldquo;cultural&amp;rdquo; items and behaviours are ultimately product of evolutionary hard-coded knowledge that interacts with variable environmental inputs. Another option to solve the paradox, that I, among many others, favour, is that interactions other than copying are crucial to produce and stabilise culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, quickly, the three papers, and then why I think this is important. When reviewing the literature on conformity- and prestige-based copying for my &lt;a href=&#34;https://global.oup.com/academic/product/cultural-evolution-in-the-digital-age-9780198835943?cc=gb&amp;amp;lang=en&amp;amp;&#34;&gt;book&lt;/a&gt;, I was surprised to find out not only that the usage of conformity and prestige cues was seldom the main determinant of decisions to copy, which I more or less expected, but that participants were often not copying others at all, even when this was useful and for free. (Interestingly, given the possibility of publication bias, this was coming from experiments in which the researchers were &lt;em&gt;expecting&lt;/em&gt; participants to copy and studying something else.) &lt;a href=&#34;https://royalsocietypublishing.org/doi/abs/10.1098/rstb.2020.0052&#34;&gt;In the first paper&lt;/a&gt; of this mighty trilogy, we reviewed various experiments where was possible to estimate if social learning was underused, correctly used, or overused, by participants, and we found that the under-usage was very robust, around ten times more common than correct or over-usage. While there may be many reasons, also specific to the experimental set-ups, for why this is the case, a safe take-home message is that it is difficult, looking at these results, to claim that we are by default avid copiers. &lt;a href=&#34;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/35511533/&#34;&gt;Various&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://psyarxiv.com/uctxa/&#34;&gt;later&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://psyarxiv.com/3xv8s&#34;&gt;experiments&lt;/a&gt; seem to confirm the outcome of our review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two other papers are modelling works, and they both explore how mechanisms different from copying can produce culture. I already talked about the first one &lt;a href=&#34;https://acerbialberto.com/post/2022_continuum/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, while &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-022-25646-9&#34;&gt;the second one&lt;/a&gt; has only been published recently, after a fairly troubled existence as a preprint. The model here focuses on claims about culture in non-human primates, but the argument is more general. We show that population-level patterns that we would consider &amp;ldquo;cultural&amp;rdquo;, such as certain distributions of behaviours in different populations, can in fact be produced by non-copying mechanisms, especially the &amp;ldquo;triggering&amp;rdquo; of behaviours already-present in the individual repertoire, following the observations of that behaviour in conspecifics. Nothing controversial, really: I suspect the difficulties in publishing this model were mainly due to two factors, one possibly interesting and the other less. The possibly interesting one is that the &amp;ldquo;triggering&amp;rdquo; mechanism in the model was considered by some reviewers and readers as indistinguishable from copying. Our agents had a set of latent behaviours, and they were (roughly) expressing them with a probability equal to their frequency in the population. But, that this &lt;em&gt;seems&lt;/em&gt; like copying was exactly our point: without &amp;ldquo;opening the box&amp;rdquo;, we can not infer from population patterns the individual mechanisms. The second, less interesting, is that we entered in a big primatology feud (on which, luckily, I do not have anything to do), and we tried to build a detailed model to interest primatologists (while an abstract model would have been cleaner in my opinion).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, why do I think all this is important? From the cultural evolution perspective, I believe there is much to gain by considering other mechanisms beside copying. Do not get me wrong, I do think copying is important, very convenient to model, and useful in many domains or as an approximation, but maybe expanding the tool kit could be an important avenue for cultural evolution research, and help to make better sense of what we observe. Also, it may be, you know, &lt;em&gt;correct&lt;/em&gt;. Second, related to my other research interest, i.e., the spread of information of in digital and online media, this view seem to me an antidote to the often-assumed idea that we are often victims of propaganda, fake news, and so on. Given how much time (and money) is spent to &lt;em&gt;fight&lt;/em&gt; fake news, this may be a quite important issue, as the &lt;a href=&#34;https://aeon.co/ideas/the-smart-move-we-learn-more-by-trusting-than-by-not-trusting&#34;&gt;problem&lt;/a&gt; seems often to be not that we are too gullible, but that we are too stubborn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, happy 2023 everyone!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The method of exclusion (still) cannot identify specific mechanisms of cultural inheritance</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2022_oranzees/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2022_oranzees/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1038/s41598-022-25646-9&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The self-control vs. self-indulgence dilemma. A culturomic analysis of 20th century trends</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2022_jbee/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2022_jbee/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1016/j.socec.2022.101946&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Individual-based models of cultural evolution. A step-by-step guide using R</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2022_ibmcultevo/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2022_ibmcultevo/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-isbn=&#34;9781032252063&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From storytelling to Facebook</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2022_from_storytelling/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2022_from_storytelling/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./featured.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are starting to have some suggestion about what kind of content is advantaged on social media, all other things being equal. Good candidates are &lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s42761-021-00057-7&#34;&gt;negative&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s42761-021-00046-w&#34;&gt;content&lt;/a&gt;, generally &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pnas.org/doi/10.1073/pnas.1618923114?url_ver=Z39.88-2003&amp;amp;rfr_id=ori:rid:crossref.org&amp;amp;rfr_dat=cr_pub%20%200pubmed&#34;&gt;emotional&lt;/a&gt; content, or &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pnas.org/doi/full/10.1073/pnas.2024292118&#34;&gt;out-group&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/american-political-science-review/article/abs/partisan-polarization-is-the-primary-psychological-motivation-behind-political-fake-news-sharing-on-twitter/3F7D2098CD87AE5501F7AD4A7FA83602&#34;&gt;detraction&lt;/a&gt; (link to some papers if you click on the contents).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These effects, albeit generally quite small, are interesting, and they are consistent with the broadly accepted narrative that social media have a detrimental influence on human communication and social interactions. This may definitely be true, but what I believe is an important missing piece is a contrast with other forms of communication and social interactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, how do we know that it is &lt;em&gt;because of social media&lt;/em&gt; that negative content - or emotional, or partisan, etc. - is favoured? To answer this question, we would need to isolate the features of social media we suppose are behind the effect, and compare situations in which these features are present and not, and we should be able to show that, say, negative content is favoured when the features are present, and not when they are not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can consider other forms of communication, and see what are the features that differ with respect to social media-mediated communication. An obvious starting point is oral, face-to-face, communication, a form of social interaction that has been dominant for the majority of human history (and partly still is). There are various studies in cultural evolution, for example, that show how &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1163%2F15685373-12342189&#34;&gt;emotional&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1090513816301660&#34;&gt;negative&lt;/a&gt; content is favoured also in experiments that reproduce situations similar to oral transmission. How does oral communication differ from social media-mediated communication? First, anonymity is, though not impossible, difficult to implement in oral communication, while it is easier to implement in social media. Second, oral communication generally takes place in small group, where people often know each other. Third, the oral back-and-forth requires understanding, memorisation, and (re)production, while in social media one just need to decide what to share (understanding itself is not required if memorisation and reproduction are not needed).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, there could be other interesting differences (suggestions welcome!), but let&amp;rsquo;s stop here. I recently published a &lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s12110-022-09423-1&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; where I tried to do something similar, focusing on the last difference. I used &amp;ldquo;attractive&amp;rdquo; content that was found to be advantaged in recall and transmission in cultural evolution experiments - negative, eliciting disgust, and threat-related - and I compared it to a &amp;ldquo;neutral&amp;rdquo; version of the same content, i.e. without the elements making it negative, etc. The first, experiment, let&amp;rsquo;s call it &amp;ldquo;storytelling&amp;rdquo; scenario, was a situation resembling oral transmission (participants had to listen - actually read on a computer screen - a story and then retell - write - it to another participant, and so on) and the second one, &amp;ldquo;social media&amp;rdquo; scenario, was resembling online sharing (participants had to read a story and decide whether they would share it or not).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Long story short, the results presented a mixed picture (experiments and analyses were fully &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/wf7pd&#34;&gt;preregistered&lt;/a&gt;, maybe there is a connection here?!), but two suggestions can be summarised here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Negative content was the only content that was both better recalled and transmitted in the &amp;ldquo;storytelling&amp;rdquo; experiment and shared in the &amp;ldquo;social media&amp;rdquo; experiment with respect to its neutral counterpart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, attractive contents seem to be more advantaged in the &amp;ldquo;storytelling&amp;rdquo; than in the &amp;ldquo;social media&amp;rdquo; scenario. On one side, this seem reasonable, if we think that this content is attractive because of its properties, and its properties impact on understanding, memorisation, etc. On the other side, is feels surprising as we tend to believe that social media communication is &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; biased than oral one. (While I like this result, it needs to be said that the kind of content was chosen because advantaged in experiments resembling oral transmission.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All data and code to reproduce the analysis are available &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/5yh4u/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To conclude: as usual, things are complicated, but I do think that comparing social media communication with other forms of communication is the only way to understand the possible causal effect of social media. In addition, if we could isolate the undesirable features (if any), we could design specific, targeted, interventions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From storytelling to Facebook. Content biases when retelling or sharing a story</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2022_hn_chains/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2022_hn_chains/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1007/s12110-022-09423-1&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A continuum of fidelity and selection</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2022_continuum/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2022_continuum/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./featured.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is a carbonara? A recent YouGov &lt;a href=&#34;https://yougov.co.uk/topics/international/articles-reports/2022/02/03/italian-food-crimes?utm_source=twitter&amp;amp;utm_medium=website_article&amp;amp;utm_campaign=italian_food_crimes&#34;&gt;survey&lt;/a&gt; suggests that the majority of Italians find unacceptable to include cream in a carbonara sauce. But what about meat? Does it have to be guanciale or smoked pancetta is alright? And the cheese? I often use parmigiano instead of pecorino, and I do not feel much anxious about this modification. The cultural trait &amp;ldquo;carbonara&amp;rdquo; has fuzzy bundaries, still some similarity between various instantiations needs to exist to refer to them as &amp;ldquo;carbonara&amp;rdquo;. (We prepare, at home, a pasta with pancetta, cream, and onion soffritto: it is delicious, but we call it &amp;ldquo;french carbonara&amp;rdquo;, i.e., it is another, different, cultural trait.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This property is fundamental for studying culture. A prerequisite for culture to exist is that there is a sufficient number of instantiations that are similar enough to justify the existence of &amp;ldquo;cultural traits&amp;rdquo; (another one is that there is some role of social transmission of information in how these instantiations are brough about). How does this (relative) similarity is maintained? In cultural evolution, the usual answer is: faithful copying and selection. According to this view, we have particular abilities that make us able to copy with precision from others, and we use a suite of heuristics (often referred to as &lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.3758/BF03196002&#34;&gt;social learning strategies&lt;/a&gt;) that make us choose preferentially some individuals to copy from, or some traits. This view has been very influential and productive, and for good reasons! Humans &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; able to copy others faithfully and humans do use heuristics that select preferentially some traits to copy with respect to others. In addition, this description has the great appeal of making the processes of cultural transmission and evolution broadly similar to the processes of genetic transmission and evolution, with all the interesting advantages coming from here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other researchers think that similarity among different instantiations of the same cultural traits is due also to other reasons, and that these reasons are also important. We do not need to bring up faithful copying to explain why percussive tools have similar features, masks are used in rituals, or there is a division of labor between sexes. (Anthropologists love to show how in the society &lt;em&gt;X&lt;/em&gt; there are not masks, which is sometimes interesting but does not change the general principle.) Even without faithful copying, starting from some degree of social information,  cultural traits can be reconstructed similarly, in a process sometimes dubbed &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S1090513817301344?via%3Dihub&#34;&gt;convergent transformation&lt;/a&gt;. If faces are remarkable, attention-grabbing, and memorable visual stimuli, masks will come to exist with high likelihood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, this is old story, and everybody agree - I think - that different mechanisms can bring about similarity among cultural traits (and thus: &lt;em&gt;culture&lt;/em&gt;), and that there is not a real contrast between explanations that emphasise copying or explanations that emphasise convergent transformation (I wrote about this &lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10539-015-9490-2&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://oxford.universitypressscholarship.com/view/10.1093/oso/9780198835943.001.0001/oso-9780198835943-chapter-7&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). What I would like to ask is: and so? Is there any interesting direction that we can go from here? In a recent &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/evolutionary-human-sciences/article/culture-without-copying-or-selection/4A0AD3781ED1616BD9D9424BD02FDCB4&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href=&#34;https://mcharbonneau.com&#34;&gt;Mathieu Charbonneau&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.santafe.edu/people/profile/helena-miton&#34;&gt;Helena Miton&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://thomscottphillips.com&#34;&gt;Thom Scott-Phillips&lt;/a&gt;, we tried to model both processes: a process of faithful copying and selection and one of convergent transformation without selection. The model first shows, probably not surprisingly, that both processes can bring about similarity - or stability (I tend to think to similarity as a relationship among traits, and stability as a population-level property, but the latter is consequence of the former).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two others uses of the model, possibly with more consequences. The first is about what happens when convergent transformation and faithful copying act together. If selection is at work, and goes in a different direction with respect to convergent transformation (think a ban against masks) &lt;a href=&#34;https://brill.com/view/journals/jocc/7/1-2/article-p89_4.xml&#34;&gt;the final outcomes depends&lt;/a&gt; on the relative strength of selection and convergent transformation. But: what does it happen if selection is not at work, and copying is faithful but random? One could suppose that random copying would &amp;ldquo;lock&amp;rdquo; cultural traits in a different configuration with respect to the one of convergent transformation, but this is not the case. As convergent transformation is the only directional process at work, even if there is a strong unbalance of forces (copying is &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; faithful and convergent transformation is weak), cultural stability is reached where convergent transformation alone would push. This suggests to me - but we did not model it - that if various processes of cultural selections (think the social learning strategies mentioned above), strong but with variable directions, act together with convergent transformation, we should still be able to observe the effect of the latter, no matter how weak it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, a process based on faithful copying plus selection and a process based on convergent transformation produce the same final state: a stable culture. Are there ways to distinguish the two? Our model suggests two ways: in a process based on faithful copying plus selection, the distance between the copied trait and the reproduced trait (how different are they?) is constant, as it is independent from the actual features of the trait. In a process based on convergent transformation, we should instead expect that this distance is larger for traits that are far from the convergence point, and smaller for traits that are close to it. For an observer, it looks like we are in some circumstances very good at copying, but in fact it just happens we are closer to the convergence point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second way to distinguish the two processes concerns the effect of population size. The relationship between demography and cultural evolution is a huge topic and I do not want to say much about it here, but only that there are some reasons why cultural processes based o convergent transformation could be less sensitive to demographic effects. You can read more in our paper, or in &lt;a href=&#34;https://royalsocietypublishing.org/doi/10.1098/rstb.2020.0053&#34;&gt;this modelling paper&lt;/a&gt; that reached compatible conclusions. Some &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S1090513816302744?via%3Dihub&#34;&gt;empirical&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://psyarxiv.com/2he8k/&#34;&gt;results&lt;/a&gt; seem also to suggest a weaker influence of population size on cultural evolution in cultural domain in which convergent transformation may be important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To conclude, I believe it is possible, speculatively, to go further. One can map various cultural domains in a bi-dimensional continuum of fidelity and selection (see the figure below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./figure_1.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the &amp;ldquo;final products&amp;rdquo; look like (more or less) stable cultures, but they are reached in different ways, and they may have different features. The top-right corner (high fidelity and selection) concerns cultural domains usually studied in cultural evolution, where the analogy with biological evolution is robust. On the opposite, the bottom-left corner is about cultural domains where convergent reconstruction is more important, that we explored in our model, and that are often the focus of Cultural Attraction Theory (CAT) inspired research. The bottom-right corner (high fidelity, but no, or low selection) is in fact what studies on &lt;a href=&#34;https://royalsocietypublishing.org/doi/10.1098/rspb.2004.2746&#34;&gt;random copying&lt;/a&gt; in cultural evolution have scrutinized. Finally, I was uncertain about the top-left corner (selection but low fidelity): some suggestions concerned &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/dansperber/status/1460219599044190214&#34;&gt;technical skills or scientific theories that are very hard to acquire&lt;/a&gt; or, more generally, processes with &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/AndrewBuskell/status/1460179218935996419&#34;&gt;high task-difficulty&lt;/a&gt;, with &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/mr_shaman_phd/status/1460183798012952581&#34;&gt;teaching from experts to novices&lt;/a&gt; involved. While this is just a sketch, I wonder whether could be used to explain some differences among cultural domains (demographic effects, like in the case above, but also others, for example opportunities for cumulative cultural evolution?) or to make sense of cultural changes (is the diffusion of digital media moving some cultural domains from the left to the right of the space?). As they say, more research is needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P.s.: I am not sure why I started this post with a carbonara. But carbonara is good. And you should not put cream, but patiently learn how to do a &amp;ldquo;saucy&amp;rdquo; sauce with eggs: lot of convergent transformation involved.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is fighting fake news a red herring?</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2022_fake_news/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2022_fake_news/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./featured.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fake news spreading on social media is often considered the cause of all bad things happened in the last years. From &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.independent.co.uk/voices/michael-gove-boris-johnson-brexit-eurosceptic-press-theresa-may-a7533806.html&#34;&gt;Brexit&lt;/a&gt; to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/the-fix/wp/2018/04/03/a-new-study-suggests-fake-news-might-have-won-donald-trump-the-2016-election/&#34;&gt;election of Trump&lt;/a&gt;, and later to &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0247642&#34;&gt;covid anti-vaxx sentiments&lt;/a&gt;, examples are not lacking. Of course, &amp;ldquo;bad&amp;rdquo; depends on your point of view, but also vaccines and lockdown &lt;em&gt;support&lt;/em&gt; have been considered a product of &lt;a href=&#34;https://open.spotify.com/episode/3SCsueX2bZdbEzRtKOCEyT&#34;&gt;mass formation psychosis&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am &lt;a href=&#34;https://acerbialberto.wordpress.com/2016/08/16/did-technology-disrupt-the-truth-probably-not/&#34;&gt;long-time sceptical&lt;/a&gt; of this line of reasoning. From a &lt;a href=&#34;https://global.oup.com/academic/product/how-traditions-live-and-die-9780190210502?cc=gb&amp;amp;lang=en&amp;amp;&#34;&gt;cognitive&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://press.princeton.edu/books/hardcover/9780691178707/not-born-yesterday&#34;&gt;evolutionary&lt;/a&gt; perspective on &lt;a href=&#34;https://global.oup.com/academic/product/cultural-evolution-in-the-digital-age-9780198835943?cc=gb&amp;amp;lang=en&amp;amp;&#34;&gt;cultural transmission&lt;/a&gt;, it makes sense to think to humans not as overly gullible individuals, but as wary social learners, that use relatively sophisticated strategies to decide whether to accept social information or not. In fact, recent empirical studies &lt;a href=&#34;https://royalsocietypublishing.org/doi/10.1098/rstb.2020.0052&#34;&gt;show&lt;/a&gt; that apparently we do not use social information enough, even when it would be advantageous. You can replace to the stereotype of gullible individuals the one of stubborn agents: the problem seems to be not that we are too easy to influence, but that we do not change our mind when we should.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It could be, naturally, that the situation brought about with the diffusion of social media is so different from offline dynamics that we just cannot cope. This is a legitimate question. However, the broad picture painted by recent research seems to be consistent: fake news rarely changes our minds. We interact with online misinformation because &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41599-019-0224-y&#34;&gt;is fun or engrossing&lt;/a&gt;, to keep &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41599-020-0452-1&#34;&gt;in contact with others&lt;/a&gt;, to actually &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/21670811.2017.1360143&#34;&gt;debunk it&lt;/a&gt;, or because we are already on the same page, and we want to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/american-political-science-review/article/abs/partisan-polarization-is-the-primary-psychological-motivation-behind-political-fake-news-sharing-on-twitter/3F7D2098CD87AE5501F7AD4A7FA83602&#34;&gt;signal our political or group membership&lt;/a&gt;. But there is more: when considered together with all the information present on social media, the proportion of fake or deceptive news is often negligible. Depending on the criteria used, the proportion of unreliable news online is generally estimated in single digit percentages, with at worst being around 5% of the total proportion of information (see table 1 &lt;a href=&#34;https://misinforeview.hks.harvard.edu/article/research-note-fighting-misinformation-or-fighting-for-information/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for various estimates).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting from this finding, together with &lt;a href=&#34;https://reutersinstitute.politics.ox.ac.uk/people/sacha-altay&#34;&gt;Sacha Altay&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/site/hugomercier/&#34;&gt;Hugo Mercier&lt;/a&gt;, we recently published a &lt;a href=&#34;https://misinforeview.hks.harvard.edu/article/research-note-fighting-misinformation-or-fighting-for-information/&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; that considers how much effort is worth allocating to fight online misinformation. Assume that people believe only some of the reliable news they encounter and only some of the unreliable news. Given the relative paucity of online misinformation, efforts to increase belief in reliable information will have a bigger effect than contrary efforts to decrease belief in unreliable information. To test this intuition (Hugo&amp;rsquo;s intuition&amp;hellip;), we developed a simple model. The figure below illustrates the main result. We started by devising a measure of the total amount of &amp;ldquo;truth&amp;rdquo; in the system (&amp;ldquo;Global information score&amp;rdquo;, on the y-axis in the figure). Think about the &amp;ldquo;Global information score&amp;rdquo; as an index that is maximum (100) when all and only reliable information is trusted, and minimum when only and all unreliable information is (-100). Given a 5% of proportion of unreliable information, if we completely wipe out belief in unreliable information, the Global information score increases of one or two points (in the figure, the difference between the &amp;ldquo;Baseline&amp;rdquo; and the &amp;ldquo;Intervention on misinformation&amp;rdquo; line). If, instead, we leave the belief in misinformation as it is, and we increase of single percentage points the belief in reliable information, we have a bigger effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./figure_1.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This outcome is robust to various realistic estimates of the relative proportion of reliable/unreliable information, to various baseline tendencies to believe reliable/unreliable information, and, as we explore in the model, works when the exposure to news is unequally distributed as in reality (with very few people consuming a lot of pieces of news, and the majority a few), when acceptance of misinformation decreases trust in reliable information, and when acceptance of misinformation increases the supply of misinformation (see again the &lt;a href=&#34;https://misinforeview.hks.harvard.edu/article/research-note-fighting-misinformation-or-fighting-for-information/&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; for details). Of course, the model is bare-bones, but I hope it can be extended to include more realistic characteristics (for example, various typologies of news effects, going beyond reliable versus unreliable news) and to support real policy efforts - which is, well, why we made it in first place&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, yes, the title of this post is provocative, but it makes an important point. As we write in the paper, it is &lt;em&gt;possible&lt;/em&gt; that the relative low proportion of fake news that we observe is indeed due to the efforts that are made to control it. But I do think that the academic and societal attention to &amp;ldquo;fake news&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;infodemic&amp;rdquo;, and the like, is disproportionate. Focusing on reliable news on social media, on their engagement potential, on counteracting the decrease of trust in reliable sources, could be more important that fighting a dubious enemy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assuming that our opponents are motivated by false beliefs (of course, it is the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0747563217306726&#34;&gt;others&lt;/a&gt; that fall for fake news!), beside being probably wrong, is also a way to refuse to understand their motivations and, finally, to preclude confrontation. Maybe understanding their reasons could produce better outcomes. Second, fake news offers a convenient and easy-to-conceptualise explanation for problems that are, probably, complex and rooted in deep socio-economical causes. It looks quite comforting to think that, if we can control better Facebook or Twitter, people would start to think as we do, but if that is not the case, the problems may remain unsolved.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research note: Fighting misinformation or fighting for information?</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2022_hks_misinfo/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2022_hks_misinfo/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.37016/mr-2020-87&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Culture without copying or selection</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2021_ehs/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2021_ehs/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1017/ehs.2021.47&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Won&#39;t somebody please think of the children!</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2021_facebook/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2021_facebook/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./featured.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With unsurprising regularity, new &amp;ldquo;scandals&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;shocking&amp;rdquo; information about social media appear in the press, and, of course, in social media themselves. Lately, Facebook seems to be the main target. (Incidentally, why Facebook? My hunch is that academics and journalists, which are the main producers and consumers of this information, tend to not be Facebook users, so it feels less dissonant to think it is the real baddy. If only &lt;em&gt;the others&lt;/em&gt; would understand it! &amp;hellip;Anyway, this is not very important for the rest of the post.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, around one month ago, the Washington Post &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/washingtonpost/status/1433749542474747910&#34;&gt;reported&lt;/a&gt; that &amp;ldquo;Misinformation on Facebook got six times more clicks than factual news during the 2020 election&amp;rdquo;. The news was, of course, a hit. However, the &amp;ldquo;six times&amp;rdquo; figure seems at odds with much recent literature that shows that, when considered together with the total information present, the amount of misinformation circulating in social media &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.science.org/doi/abs/10.1126/science.aau2706&#34;&gt;is&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/sciadv.aay3539&#34;&gt;actually&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/sciadv.aau4586&#34;&gt;modest&lt;/a&gt;, something like the 5% of the total information (often less). For this reason, it would have been interesting to know how the &amp;ldquo;clicks&amp;rdquo; were actually calculated or what was exactly considered as &amp;ldquo;misinformation&amp;rdquo;. Unfortunately the study to which the Washington Post referred to was not out at the moment, and it is still, after one month, not available (not even in form of preprint, which is now relatively standard practice).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later on &amp;mdash; mid September &amp;mdash; another scandal hit Facebook. This time, it was leaked documents to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wsj.com/articles/facebook-knows-instagram-is-toxic-for-teen-girls-company-documents-show-11631620739&#34;&gt;the Wall Street Journal&lt;/a&gt;, titled &amp;ldquo;Facebook Knows Instagram Is Toxic for Teen Girls, Company Documents Show&amp;rdquo;. You probably heard about it, and about the outraged editorials and comments all around social media: you have here a bad social media company (i) hiding information, and (ii) harming (iii) young girls. Hardly you can have something more attractive. However, it looks like the report was mostly based on a small survey on a few dozens of teenagers that were asked if they &lt;em&gt;thought&lt;/em&gt; Instagram was bad for them, and on &amp;ldquo;focus groups&amp;rdquo; with even less participants, where the reason why they thought it was bad were discussed in more details. Now, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cell.com/trends/cognitive-sciences/fulltext/S1364-6613(20)30251-5&#34;&gt;we&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pnas.org/content/116/21/10226.short&#34;&gt;are&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41562%20018%200506%201?mod=article_inline&#34;&gt;far&lt;/a&gt; to have an in-depth knowledge of the effects of Instagram and social media on well-being and mental health, but this survey does not add much to our previous knowledge, so it is difficult to justify the reactions. (A good analysis of the vicissitude can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://unherd.com/2021/09/facebooks-bad-science/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Move on to today, and we have the whistleblower Frances Haugen, ex Facebook employee, testifying in front of the US congress. Things get heated, outrage continues, with public personalities pushing on Twitter the sober hashtag &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/SachaBaronCohen/status/1445541488889241608&#34;&gt;#FacebookKills&lt;/a&gt;. I admit I did not read the full transcriptions (I am already using precious time by writing this blog post instead of working or, even better, having a walk, as Bristol is sunny in October!), and I am referring to reports from newspapers, in particular &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2021/oct/05/facebook-harms-children-damaging-democracy-claims-whistleblower&#34;&gt;the Guardian&lt;/a&gt;. From what I understand, there are not really big novelties in what the whistleblower reports. She is mostly repeating the accusations that Facebook knew about harming children and teenagers (but see the point above), adding various dubious twists. One is the analogy between social media usage and addiction (I cite: &amp;ldquo;It’s just like cigarettes&amp;hellip;teenagers don&amp;rsquo;t have good self-regulation.&amp;rdquo;), which is considered &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.oii.ox.ac.uk/blog/social-media-is-nothing-like-drugs-despite-all-the-horror-stories/&#34;&gt;flawed&lt;/a&gt; by practically all researchers in the field. Another is the idea, never &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pnas.org/content/118/32/e2101967118&#34;&gt;really&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11109-021-09734-6&#34;&gt;established&lt;/a&gt;, that the algorithm is pushing towards more extreme content (the algorithm &amp;ldquo;led children from very innocuous topics like healthy recipes&amp;hellip;all the way to anorexia-promoting content over a very short period of time&amp;rdquo;). We have gory details (&amp;ldquo;women would be walking around with brittle bones in 60 years’ time because of the anorexia-related content they found on Facebook platforms&amp;rdquo; in the words of the Guardian), and not very surprising considerations, such as that Facebook &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2021/oct/03/former-facebook-employee-frances-haugen-identifies-herself-as-whistleblower&#34;&gt;put profits before people&lt;/a&gt; (huge if true for a private company). In sum, nothing really new and, mostly, from what I get, nothing that can be actually used to understand better what is going on, a part the usual accusations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, I am not in the &amp;ldquo;everything is good as it is&amp;rdquo; team (I do not think anybody is), and there are several things that Facebook and other social media should do to makes things better. A short and idiosyncratic list could include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Making their data available and easy to access to researchers and to the general public. Twitter seems slightly better than Facebook about that. (Adding to what said above, Facebook got caught recently in other &amp;ldquo;scandals&amp;rdquo; about errors in sharing data and blocking access to scientists.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No social media, that I am aware, is open about the algorithm they use to present information to users. How our Facebook news feed is decided? What about Twitter? I find the lack of transparency particularly worrying, also because this information would finally allow to give better answers to central questions on the kind of information promoted by social media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Could we make social media better? We could and we certainly should experiment with alternatives. If it is true (see the point above) that, say, social media algorithms push contents that receive more interactions (I called it &lt;a href=&#34;https://global.oup.com/academic/product/cultural-evolution-in-the-digital-age-9780198835943?cc=gb&amp;amp;lang=en&amp;amp;&#34;&gt;optimisation for shallow engagement&lt;/a&gt;) and, say &lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007%2Fs42761-021-00046-w&#34;&gt;negative&lt;/a&gt; or strongly &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pnas.org/content/114/28/7313.long&#34;&gt;emotional&lt;/a&gt; content receive more interactions, this could created a vicious circle where negative (say) information receive more interactions &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; are proposed more, so end up to dominate social media content. But, of course, things are complicated. Many other factors could be relevant (again, we would need to know more about the algorithm!) and, importantly, preferences for negative (say) information could be linked to more general cognitive preferences and be &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/br56y/&#34;&gt;succesfull&lt;/a&gt; independently from social media, so that one would need to balance algorithmic and psychological forces. This is just an example, but many others could be discussed along similar lines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This goes clearly beyond my expertise, but putting Whatsapp, Instagram, Facebook (and what else?) in the same hands may not be a good idea. I leave this to people that know more, but it &lt;em&gt;feels&lt;/em&gt; that a decentralised system would work better for us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And on and on. All these are, I think, very reasonable criticisms to Facebook and other social media, and I&amp;rsquo;d be (and am) very supportive of calls to action in this direction. Now, it could be that the periodic outrages are useful, but, call me crazy, I am not sure about that. If one claims that #FacebookKills, it is very easy for Facebook to show that it does not and, well, they are right. The risk is that by muddling sensible requests with sensationalist claims, we are doing Facebook&amp;rsquo;s game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ps: I may be too old, so &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3jFqhjaGh30&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; the title reference.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Review of Joseph Henrich, The Weirdest People in the World</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2021_henrich/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2021_henrich/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.26613/esic.5.1.217&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beyond social learning</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2021_ptrsb_beyond/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2021_ptrsb_beyond/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1098/rstb.2020.0050&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modelling cultural systems and selective filters</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2021_ptrsb_systems/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2021_ptrsb_systems/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1098/rstb.2020.0045&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Social information use and social information waste</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2021_ptrsb_antisocial/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2021_ptrsb_antisocial/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1098/rstb.2020.0052&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Individual-based models of cultural evolution. A step-by-step guide using R</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2020_ibm_cultevo/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2020_ibm_cultevo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./featured.png&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the past, I have been asked by a few people where they could start if they wanted to learn how to do individual-based models (IBMs) of cultural evolution. I never had a good answer, so, together with &lt;a href=&#34;https://marcosmolla.com&#34;&gt;Marco Smolla&lt;/a&gt;, we discussed it would have been interesting to develop some material, in a form of a long tutorial, or a book (at that time, conferences were still in person&amp;hellip;). While doing some research, I quickly found that &lt;a href=&#34;https://marcosmolla.com&#34;&gt;Alex Mesoudi&lt;/a&gt; had already put together some basic R Markdown IBMs with the same goal, so we happily joined forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result is &lt;a href=&#34;https://acerbialberto.com/IBM-cultevo/&#34;&gt;Individual-based model of cultural evolution. A step-by-step guide using R&lt;/a&gt;. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://acerbialberto.com/IBM-cultevo/introduction.html&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt; quickly explains the whys, whats, and hows of the book, and I would suggest to start from there if you are intersted. Some main points here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book is intended for people with a basic R knowledge that want to learn cultural evolution IBMs &lt;em&gt;by doing&lt;/em&gt;. We cut most of the theoretical complexities of modelling (some references can be found in the Introduction) and focused on reproducing existent models, explaining the code almost line-by-line. In sum, this is not a book you want to read on the couch in front of the fire, but on your desk in front of an RStudio window.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We choose to use R (and, with some licence, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tidyverse.org&#34;&gt;tidyverse&lt;/a&gt;) not because is the best programming language for IBMs, but because is probably the most diffuse at the moment among researchers in cultural evolution. The idea is that, if one already knows R, the additional cost of learning IBMs is relatively limited, as opposed to starting from scratch with a new programming language. (And, anyway, I am too old to learn Julia.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book builds in complexity, both from the programming and the conceptual point of view. We start with IBMs versions of the &amp;ldquo;classic&amp;rdquo; cultural evolution analytical models, assuming that most of the readers will be at least familiar with their verbal descriptions, and we then move to more recent, or less standard, topics. They include Roger&amp;rsquo;s paradox and its solutions, how to model the effects of demography and migrations, social networks, the importance of convergent transformations, etc. A full table of content is &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/albertoacerbi/IBM-cultevo/blob/main/README.md&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We tried to be generally consistent with programming style, conventions, etc. (see again the Introduction), but we also use, especially in the later chapters, different programming techniques so that readers can see how things can be done differently. This should expand the programming knowledge - or simply be confusing. Feedback is welcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the code-heavy nature of the book, the best way to use it is from the Bookdown-generated html version, available &lt;a href=&#34;https://acerbialberto.com/IBM-cultevo/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, where the code can be easily copied-and-pasted. The R Markdown files that build the book can be find &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/albertoacerbi/IBM-cultevo&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, if you prefer to work directly on those. There is also a pdf version &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/32v6a/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; but, as said above, the html version is advised. Also, some of the code did not render well in the pdf, so you may need both in any case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the html version of the book is, and will always be, open access. We have a doi that can be used to cite it, and we are discussing some options to also have a &amp;ldquo;proper&amp;rdquo; publisher for a physical, paper-based, version, but nothing has been planned yet. In fact, if someone has any advice, they are welcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So: happy modelling, and remember the book is a first complete draft, but still a draft, so we expect to change and improve bits and pieces in a collaborative effort!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Covid misinformation on mainstream Italian media</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2020_covid_misinfo/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2020_covid_misinfo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You may have heard the we live in a post-truth era, that we are facing an infodemic or, even, a &lt;a href=&#34;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/370/6523/1395&#34;&gt;syndemic&lt;/a&gt;, the combination of &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt; epidemics, meaning that covid &amp;ldquo;emerged in an information ecosystem that helps misinformation and lies spread faster than scientific evidence, weakening our ability to respond to new threats&amp;rdquo;. Not only this is not true but, I believe, is also a dangerous narrative that makes us focus on the wrong problems instead of the real ones. Anyway, this is not a topic I can elaborate on here (hey, I wrote a &lt;a href=&#34;https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2019_oup/&#34;&gt;book&lt;/a&gt; - partly - about that!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, of course, &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; misinformation does spread. Another aspect of these stale criticism is that, naturally, the culprit is social media. Luckily, many real experts of media have long recognised the contribution, or in fact the prominent role, that mainstream, traditional, media have in the current spread of misinformation. &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/rasmus_kleis&#34;&gt;Rasmus Kleis Nielsen&lt;/a&gt;, director of Reuters Institute at Oxford University, reports on Twitter several examples of mainstream media, or prominent political figures, spreading or originating false or misleading information: &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/search?q=Misinformation%20often%20comes%20from%20the%20top&amp;amp;src=typed_query&#34;&gt;Misinformation often comes from the top&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an Italian living in UK, with part of my family living in Italy, I have been irritated by how the major Italian newspaper (for number of readers), &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.repubblica.it&#34;&gt;La Repubblica&lt;/a&gt;, covered the last days of news from UK. But I noticed the disservice before, so hang with me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;maria.png&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 15th of November, La Repubblica - I repeat, the major Italian newspaper - covered the declarations of don Livio Fanzaga, the director of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Radio_Maria&#34;&gt;Radio Maria&lt;/a&gt;, a large Catholic radio, which, among others, claimed that &amp;ldquo;Coronavirus is a conspiracy under the impulse of Satan&amp;rdquo;, with the goal of &amp;ldquo;building a new world without God&amp;rdquo;. Now, why a major newspaper should report the delusional beliefs of a not very important figure? In addition, in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.repubblica.it/cronaca/2020/11/15/news/radio_maria_il_coronavirus_e_un_complotto_sotto_l_impulso_di_satana_-274486827/&#34;&gt;the whole article&lt;/a&gt; there is not a single comment from the journalist on the declarations. If I remember correctly, but I can not check now, the article was linked from the first page of the online version (why??) and the declarations were reported as &amp;ldquo;controversial&amp;rdquo;, which is, clearly, not the right word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./vaccine.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 9th of December, in the first days of the successful roll-out of the UK vaccine (our local medical practice texted us yesterday that the first 1,000 people have been vaccinated in our Bristol &lt;em&gt;neighbourhood&lt;/em&gt;), La Repubblica reported, as full-page headline of the online version, the news about the two allergic reactions among the early people vaccinated. Now, this is technically not false, but it is an expected consequence of &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; vaccines. It was quickly reported in other international newspapers (as it should be) and quickly forgotten (as it should be). Putting this news as full-page headline, when we should all strive to understand how to convince &amp;ldquo;hesitant&amp;rdquo; people and reassure everybody about the vaccine, is not only bad journalism, but it could have dangerous consequences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./UK1.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We arrive to Sunday, after the declaration of the stricter Christmas lockdown for some areas in UK, the new strain, and the stop of flights from UK to Italy. It is a worrying situation, so what does the major Italian newspaper do? Again, full-page headline. The summary contains an anonymous quote: &amp;ldquo;We run away. The situation in London is out of control&amp;rdquo;. While health secretary Matt Hancock did say that the new variant (not &amp;ldquo;the situation in London&amp;rdquo;) was &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.sky.com/story/covid-19-in-tier-4-everybody-needs-to-behave-as-if-they-already-have-coronavirus-matt-hancock-says-12168124&#34;&gt;out of control&lt;/a&gt;, he certainly did not say anything about running away from London, so it is not clear what the quote refers to. But, beside the details, it is clearly made up, explicitly or not, to scare readers (a strategy often used in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41599-019-0224-y&#34;&gt;misinformation&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./featured.png&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We arrived to the title that today made me writing this post instead of doing something more festive: &amp;ldquo;Chaos in UK, you even have to do the tests by yourself!&amp;rdquo;. Summary: &amp;ldquo;It is a jungle there, that&amp;rsquo;s why there has been an out-of-control diffusion&amp;rdquo;. The major italian newspaper. A (supposedly) serious, left-leaning, large circulation newspaper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not a supporter of the current UK government, and I have plenty of criticisms on their Covid management, but: you can &lt;em&gt;choose&lt;/em&gt; whether to do the swab yourself or with an assistant (parents always do it for children) and this is because people &lt;em&gt;prefer&lt;/em&gt; to do it by themselves instead of having someone else doing it to them. UK tested, from the beginning of October, between 300,000 and 400,000 people every day, which is double of triple of what Italy did. We had a test for our daughter (she had a fever for few days): we booked it online in the evening on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gov.uk/get-coronavirus-test&#34;&gt;nhs website&lt;/a&gt;, we got a slot for the next morning, we did it in 10 minutes and we had the result (negative!) the day after. Hardly chaos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is difficult to comment on the rest, that is, implying that the &amp;ldquo;out-of-control diffusion&amp;rdquo;, which I guess refers to the new strain, is due to the fact that here is a &amp;ldquo;jungle&amp;rdquo;. Not much to say: mutations can happen anywhere (as they did and do). Not to mentione that one of the reasons why the new mutation has been first found in UK is that UK does on average 56 genomic sequences for every 1,000 covid cases, against, for example, the 0.42 of Italy (data from &lt;a href=&#34;https://covidcg.org/?tab=global_sequencing&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;: in other words, if the new strain would have been equally present in Italy and UK, everything else being equal, UK would have around 130 times more likelihood to detect it).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To conclude this rant-ish and quickly written post. It is disheartening how this journalism seems to be acceptable. Beside the academic thoughts, it can have important (see the vaccine example above) and real (Hi mum, I am good!) consequences. The fact that it goes together with the &amp;ldquo;social media are the culprit&amp;rdquo; slogan just makes it more unnerving. Anyway: check your news sources, stay safe wherever you are, and enjoy the holidays if you can!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cultural Accumulation and Improvement in Online Fan Fiction</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/cp_2020_chr/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/cp_2020_chr/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning from failures</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2020_jce/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2020_jce/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./featured.png&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the Second World War, aeroplanes coming back after battles showed a peculiar pattern of damage: they were mostly hit on the wings and on the centre of the fuselage (see the figure above, which is not a representation of any real data, but makes the point). Based on this, the military reckoned they needed to add additional protections on these parts. Statisticians suggested instead that protections were needed on the cockpit and on the back of the fuselage - the parts &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; hit. And they were right! The point is that those aeroplanes were the returning ones: aeroplanes presenting that pattern of damage were actually able to come back succesfully after battle. It was the aiprlanes hit in the other areas that were lost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether the story is true or not, it is a vivid representation of survivorship bias (as well as &lt;a href=&#34;https://xkcd.com/1827/&#34;&gt;this excellent xkcd&lt;/a&gt;). Each time someone is giving advice based on how they succeed, it is good to remember that one is generalising from a biased sample. In many fields, in addition, success is partly (or mostly, see again the xkcd comic), based on luck or on reasons that can be hardly linked to the success itself, which is a good moment to mention success in academia. The big professor that was interested in X from school? The brilliant researcher that takes a walk every morning? The 12-papers-a-year postdoc that meditate? The 10 rules for juggling academic job and family? (I swear I am not referring to any real example here. Really.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe we need to &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; consider advice from the unsuccessful cases. Thus, I will start the &lt;em&gt;succumbership bias&lt;/em&gt; series with my resignation from the role of coordinator of the Cultural Evolution Society publishing committee. The goal of the publishing committee was to start a society journal. After a couple of years, there has not been any progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A short summary: the 7th June 2013 (more than seven years ago), I wrote on my old blog the post &lt;a href=&#34;https://acerbialberto.wordpress.com/2013/06/07/journal-of-cultural-evolution-anyone/&#34;&gt;“Journal of Cultural Evolution”, anyone?&lt;/a&gt;. The post received a quite positive reaction, and various people thought it was a good idea. In 2014, at the EHBEA conference in Bristol, we had a first meeting to discuss the project, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://acerbialberto.wordpress.com/2014/03/21/journal-of-cultural-evolution-meeting-at-ehbea-2104/&#34;&gt;possibly to start to do something concrete in this direction&lt;/a&gt;. Nothing much happened, but in 2017, at the first conference of the Cultural Evolution Society in Jena, we had &lt;a href=&#34;https://acerbialberto.wordpress.com/2017/06/26/journal-of-cultural-evolution-again/&#34;&gt;another meeting&lt;/a&gt; about the possibility of the journal, and shortly after, the publishing committee started to ponder &lt;a href=&#34;https://acerbialberto.wordpress.com/2018/06/18/a-quick-update-on-the-journal-of-cultural-evolution/&#34;&gt;various options&lt;/a&gt;. Today, the Cultural Evolution Society is having a meeting in which I presented (indirectly) my resignation, and it should be discussed what will be done (if anything) with the journal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here a few thoughts, quite specifically linked to the journal topic, this time influenced by the succumbership bias!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You surely saw these quotes about &amp;ldquo;dreaming big&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;following your dreams&amp;rdquo;, and so on. But from the succumberhsip bias point of view, it may be better to have realistic goals, and not be too ambitious. We wanted an open access, self-published journal, we even discussed whether publishing directly the submissions and having online, voluntary, reviews. We did not want to restrict the scope of the journal to usual scientific articles, but having space for datasets, ethnography, commentaries. We wanted to &amp;ldquo;culturally evolve&amp;rdquo; the publishing system (a usual quote from CT). Perhaps we should have contacted Elsevier with &amp;ldquo;hey, do you want to publish the Journal of Cultural Evolution?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the members of the publishing committee - including yours truly - were working on this project in the spare time. Given the extent of the project I now think it would have been better to have a small group of people committed, and able to focus almost full time for a short period on it. This is not a criticism of our work (we did what we could!), but maybe something the Cultural Evolution Society can think about for the future?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then there are these quotes about many heads that are better than one, the plurality of opinions. Within the few heads of the publishing committee we had slightly different opinions about a wealth of topics (open science? Diversity and inclusivity? Independence? All of them? Can we? Shall we volunteer for this? No? But where do we find the money?). Not insurmountable, but maybe, just maybe, sometimes may be good to be all in agreement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This mostly relates to me. I am not exactly the best person concerning PR and networking, and I did not have strong links with the headquarters of the society. A better-connected person could have probably done a better job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You know that good things need time and it is important to be patient. If the project is good, one waits and, in the end, it will succeed. Or so says the survivor. Perhaps I should have suspected that, if the project was moving so slowly (remember the first idea was in 2013), something was not right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Related to the above, incentives change with time. In particular, one of the main reason to think about a journal for cultural evolution in 2013 was the absence of other, related, venues of publications. Today we have &lt;em&gt;Nature Human Behaviour&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Evolutionary Human Sciences&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Evolutionary Perspectives on Imaginative Culture&lt;/em&gt;, the &amp;ldquo;Cultural Evolution&amp;rdquo; collection in Palgrave&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Humanities and Social Sciences Communications&lt;/em&gt; and probably others that I am forgetting (excluding here journals that were already present in 2013 and publishing cultural evolution stuff, such as &lt;em&gt;Cliodynamics&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Evolution and Human Behavior&lt;/em&gt;, or the &lt;em&gt;Journal of Cognition and Culture&lt;/em&gt; among others).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, I still hope that a self-published, and possibly innovative, journal of the Cultural Evolution Society will appear (who knows, maybe on this moment the executive committee is turning down my resignation and allocating bazillion dollars for the project). Good luck to them/us and thank you to the people that tried with me to carry this forward!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ps: Of course, the succumbership bias is as bad as the survivorship bias.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;pps: Thank you to the people that shared kind words with me and, yes, it is not &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; bad, but honestly I did hope to be able to create this journal one day&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome to B-data</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2020_bdata/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2020_bdata/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./featured.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A short blog post to present a little project I am working on within the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.brunel.ac.uk/psychology&#34;&gt;Psychology Division&lt;/a&gt; at Brunel University. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.brunel.ac.uk/psychology/research-and-phd-programmes/Collection-of-resources&#34;&gt;B-data&lt;/a&gt; is a collection of resources for finding and processing online behavioural data (that is the &lt;em&gt;B&lt;/em&gt; in the name&amp;hellip;), which may be interesting for people working in psychology and cultural evolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As explained in the page:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;B-data is a curated collection of resources for working with online behavioural data. In recent years, there has been an enormous growth of freely available datasets. In parallel, computational resources and tools to process and analyse them have become more broadly accessible. Lastly, working on pre-existent data can be an important resource in situations where collecting new data may be problematic, for example, due to contemporary COVID 19-related restrictions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The collection aims to provide not only links to datasets of psychological interest, but a more comprehensive perspective on working with online data, including software, examples of previous researches, or pointers to tools for extracting your data from webpages and social media. It will be hopefully useful for research, student projects, and teaching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the number of possible datasets and software out there is enormous. The collection tries to strike a balance between the standard choices and resources linked to more specific topics, and cannot be in any way exhaustive. If you have a niche interest you would probably not find here a datasets, but it should be, at least, a good place to start exploring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am still working on it, but there should be enough material to be hopefully useful for other people. And, of course, feedback and suggestions are more than welcome!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Twitter kick-starter</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2020_twitter/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2020_twitter/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./featured.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been told of NGOs job applications that require to include the candidate&amp;rsquo;s Twitter profile. Even when not that explicit, a curated Twitter account is increasingly important for the academic and academic-adjacent job market, if only for networking. As I am active on Twitter from October 2012, I had the occasion to give some advice on how to start on the social media (for example to my wife!). As it seems they worked, I have been suggested to put them in a blog post, so here it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, a few notes. This post is not about the technical basics (how to open an account, how to tweet, how to retweet, etc.), I consider you are good with those, or you can easily find this information somewhere else. Second, it is not about becoming a twitter star with thousands of followers, but about having a decent profile for your career development. The bits of advice are pretty general and they should work for an average user. Of course, there are plenty of exceptions and, to become a Twitter star, what counts is probably being &lt;em&gt;already&lt;/em&gt; a star, the actual content you share and, mostly, luck. But, again, this is not our goal. Finally, all this is focused on academic or closely linked profiles, that are the only ones for which I have a bit of experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time. It seems many people are worried that they do not have enough time to have a curated Twitter profile. While obviously Twitter is a rabbit hole where one can lose all the time in the world, this is not necessary. Nobody has to be completely updated on what the accounts they follow tweet: this is not only impossible but also useless. For the beginning, an hour a week it is more than sufficient to follow some people, read some tweets and post content. Two sessions of half an hour or less, for example, will be enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have a curated profile. Use a picture of yourself where you can be recognised. The short bio is important: avoid the witty sentence and put relevant information and links (if useful). Include a link to your website. Here, as an example, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/acerbialberto&#34;&gt;my profile&lt;/a&gt;. Again, there are many exceptions, but this works on average.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following and followers. Start by following a few hundred accounts, perhaps have a goal (&amp;ldquo;Following 200 accounts for the end of the month&amp;rdquo;). Follow accounts that are related to your field, big and small names, more than the people that you know. Twitter is not about keeping in contact, but about exchanging information. How can you find them? Search with keywords and follow the advice from Twitter. Here a useful shortcut: when you find a reliable profile in your field, that possibly does not follow too many accounts, go through their &amp;ldquo;following&amp;rdquo; and follow the ones that seem relevant. You also want to acquire followers. This mostly depends on the content that you share (see below), but ideally you want that a reasonable proportion of the account you follow will follow you back. Usually this happens, say around 50% at the beginning. When you will have more followers you will be more twitter-attractive, and the probability of begin followed back will grow. If you &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; are concerned about the number of followers, follow accounts that have more or less the same number of followers/following, as this probably means that they follow back whoever follows them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When to tweet. In general, the more you tweet, the better. However, time is not infinite, and there are many better things to do in life. Still, you should tweet original content (i.e. not a retweeet) &lt;em&gt;at least&lt;/em&gt; one or two times a week. This signals your account is active.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What to tweet. Things related to your professional topic. Do not tweet what you think about X - or do not do it often - probably not many care. Share information like links to papers, blogs, pieces of news, etc. and, in case, what you think about that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stick to one topic. The most important - I think - advice about content: be consistent. Do not tweet once about your scientific field, then about your cat, then about your favourite Sichuan dish, then the anti-Trump rant. People will follow and support you (with likes and retweets) if you provide a consistent and up-to-date information about one topic: &amp;ldquo;that&amp;rsquo;s one of the accounts to follow if you are interested in X&amp;rdquo; (where X is &amp;ldquo;anthropology&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;conservation&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;history of Middle East&amp;rdquo; or whatever). If I follow you because I am interested in conservation, I probably do not care about what you ate last night (there are other social media for this). One out-of-topic tweet from time to time is ok, but not too many. Of course you can have two related topics (say, ehm, &amp;ldquo;cultural evolution&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;digital media&amp;rdquo;) Two unrelated topics? Not sure. Each time I want to tweet something unrelated to my research, for example politics, I refrain, and I think it is good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How to find relevant content. This is the difficult part, here is what works for me. A good source of new scientific articles are Google Scholar alerts (of course you have a Google Scholar profile). They generally fit very well with your research, so you should be on the safe side. Another source is, of course, Twitter itself (for me it has replaced almost all the official journals&amp;rsquo; alerts): retweet relevant material from others (see also below for the &amp;ldquo;Retweet with comment&amp;rdquo;). A good way to provide new content even with retweets is to retweet material from more obscure accounts, or accounts unrelated to your field. Retweeting the last paper of the star researcher with 50,000 followers will not provide new content to your followers, but retweeting the interesting paper of a less known researcher, or showing how something in another field is related to yours will. News, conferences, open positions related to your field are also good content. At the end of the day, however, this will be about what you read and what you find interesting, so: be curious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check the content. Read before sharing is the basic advice. But, really, do it. You do not have to read a full scientific article before you tweet it, but you want to be sure that it is about what is supposed to be and that, for example, the link points to the correct place, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personalise the content. The other advantage of reading before sharing is that you can personalise the tweet, and this is added value. You can quickly say &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; the article, or the piece of news, is interesting or criticizable, this is better than just tweeting the title (but this is also ok). This is especially useful for reteweets: you can &amp;ldquo;Retweet with comment&amp;rdquo; so that, again, you add some personal information, but also, the tweet is associated in the timeline to your profile, so it is &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; tweet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Photos and videos. They do make tweets more attractive. If you tweet an article you may want to include one of the plots, or some related image. This is why I put in each blog post a picture, even if not very related (including this one): when sharing it on Twitter, the small picture appears together with the link.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hashtags. I do not use them, but it does seem they increase the number of likes and retweets (which in turn will ultimately increase the number of your followers) so I guess a moderate use (one, maximum two) in some of the tweets, when they are relevant, may be a good strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like. There are various reasons to like relevant tweets from other users. They will know about you, you can use them as bookmarks, and you possibly train the algorithm that select which tweets you will see more prominently. Also like all replies to your tweets, if they are not offensive, and if they are at least related, because why not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be nice. In eight years of Twitter, I believe I got involved in quarrels two or three times. Of course, I think it was not my fault, but that is too easy. In any case, there is nothing to gain. Twitter is not the place for long and nuanced discussions. This is fine, as long as one is aware of it. I found Twitter tremendously useful for sharing and discovering interesting stuff and for many good conversations and, so far, the balance useful/annoying has been largely positive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cultural evolution in the digital age book club</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2020_ceda_book_club/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2020_ceda_book_club/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./featured.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just a short post to advertise and bookmark the book club that &lt;a href=&#34;http://cognitionandculture.net&#34;&gt;cognitionandculture.net&lt;/a&gt; organised around &lt;em&gt;Cultural evolution in the digital age&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;http://cognitionandculture.net/webinars/cultural-evolution-in-the-digital-age/cultural-evolution-in-the-digital-age-book-club/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). Every now and then, the people at the International Cognition &amp;amp; Culture Institute (ICCI) choose a book of culture-and-cognition interest and invite the author to write a short précis and various experts on the topic to write commentaries (see some previous examples &lt;a href=&#34;http://cognitionandculture.net/ebooks&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).  All is followed by an open online discussion: for &lt;em&gt;Cultural evolution in the digital age&lt;/em&gt; it starts today and will last until the 12th of July.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The commentaries, by &lt;a href=&#34;http://cognitionandculture.net/webinars/cultural-evolution-in-the-digital-age/are-humans-wary-learners/&#34;&gt;Alex Mesoudi&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://cognitionandculture.net/webinars/cultural-evolution-in-the-digital-age/what-is-the-recipe/&#34;&gt;Sacha Altay&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://cognitionandculture.net/webinars/cultural-evolution-in-the-digital-age/cultural-transmission-reinvention-and-progress/&#34;&gt;Olivier Morin&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://cognitionandculture.net/webinars/cultural-evolution-in-the-digital-age/consuming-vs-sharing-information-online/&#34;&gt;Hugo Mercier&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://cognitionandculture.net/webinars/cultural-evolution-in-the-digital-age/the-participatory-age/&#34;&gt;Mathieu Charbonneau&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://cognitionandculture.net/webinars/cultural-evolution-in-the-digital-age/the-mystery-of-production/&#34;&gt;Pascal Boyer&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://cognitionandculture.net/webinars/cultural-evolution-in-the-digital-age/truth-is-not-always-the-point/&#34;&gt;Tiffany Morisseau&lt;/a&gt; are extremely insightful, and they should appeal to anybody interested in cultural evolution and especially in its application to contemporary online dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if it sounds like a cliché, I will not get tired to repeat how privileged I feel about having &lt;em&gt;Cultural evolution in the digital age&lt;/em&gt; at the centre of such a stimulating exchange. Everybody is very welcome to &lt;a href=&#34;http://cognitionandculture.net/webinars/cultural-evolution-in-the-digital-age/cultural-evolution-in-the-digital-age-book-club-general-discussion/&#34;&gt;join the discussion&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cultural evolution and networks</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2020_cultural_evolution_networks/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2020_cultural_evolution_networks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./featured.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrewbuskell.com&#34;&gt;Andrew Buskell&lt;/a&gt; just published in &lt;em&gt;Acta Biotheoretica&lt;/em&gt; an insightful combined &lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10441-020-09384-x&#34;&gt;review&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&#34;https://global.oup.com/academic/product/cultural-evolution-in-the-digital-age-9780198835943?cc=gb&amp;amp;lang=en&amp;amp;&#34;&gt;Cultural evolution in the digital age&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/site/hugomercier/&#34;&gt;Hugo Mercier&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/site/hugomercier/not-born-yesterday&#34;&gt;Not Born Yesterday&lt;/a&gt;. There are many things to appreciate in the review. First - but I may be biased here&amp;hellip; - it is a positive one. Andrew concludes by writing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both Mercier and Acerbi&amp;rsquo;s volumes are enjoyable, story-driven journeys. They guide the reader through large and expanding literatures in an entertaining and illuminating way. They are upbeat about human capabilities and provide a useful optimistic counterpoint to the recent spate of epistemological doomsayer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could not have said it better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, it is pleasing to be in good company. &lt;em&gt;Not born yesterday&lt;/em&gt; is an excellent book. In fact, while writing, my own views about how social information is evaluated have somehow glided from a more standard cultural evolution framework to the epistemic (or &amp;ldquo;open&amp;rdquo;) vigilance perspective presented in Hugo&amp;rsquo;s volume. If I would start working on &lt;em&gt;Cultural evolution in the digital age&lt;/em&gt; today it would probably be a quite different book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, and last, the &amp;ldquo;concerns&amp;rdquo; are also perceptive. One of those is that &lt;em&gt;Cultural evolution in the digital age&lt;/em&gt; did not discuss enough the importance of the integration between the literature on social network models and the largely individual-level perspective endorsed in the book. I completely agree. The main theoretical perspectives I drew upon are indeed not particularly sensitive to the topic. Evolutionary psychology theories are mostly theories about individual minds, and while social interactions and communications are certainly important for these theories, they are important with respect to how they shaped those individual minds. (Incidentally, I always thought the evolutionary psychology is one of the approaches that would have more to gain by adopting a modelling perspective, but only very few evolutionary psychology works use it.) Cultural evolution seems more receptive: virtually all theories in cultural evolution take into account population-level dynamics, still populations are generally considered as uniform or - I think - fully-connected networks, i.e. networks were all individuals have the same probability to interact with any other individual in the network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, there are exceptions. At least a &lt;a href=&#34;https://advances.sciencemag.org/content/5/8/eaaw0609&#34;&gt;few&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/ncomms13109&#34;&gt;papers&lt;/a&gt; adopt an explicit &amp;ldquo;cultural evolution on networks&amp;rdquo; perspective and there is an enormous grey area (the &amp;ldquo;grey&amp;rdquo; is just because I am not familiar myself) of works that are relevant from both perspectives. In my folder &amp;ldquo;archive/projects_discussed/interesting_to_do/ok_lets_see/but_probably_not&amp;rdquo; there is an old modelling project aimed at comparing the diffusion of cultural traits under different selective biases (neutral, model-based, frequency-based, and content-based) in different population structures: fully-connected (the control condition, standard in cultural evolution), Erdos-Reyni random networks and Scale-free networks. As the name of the folder suggests, the project is still there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a matter of fact, one of the reasons that motivated me working on &lt;em&gt;Cultural evolution in the digital age&lt;/em&gt; was exactly the lack of integration between the two literatures. However, my unsatisfaction was going in the opposite direction. Research on online cultural dynamics was (and still is) dominated by the network/complexity science perspective. Whereas these works are computationally sophisticated, and some of them are illuminating, I have been sometimes frustrated by the lack (if not, worst, the implausibility) of the assumptions about individual psychology. My feeling is that many questionable ideas circulating about the negative effects of digital online media, e.g. the overestimation of &amp;ldquo;echo chambers&amp;rdquo; effects or of the influence of bots and misinformation, may have found support in the scientific literature because of this problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I have been not explicit about that in the book and, as Andrew&amp;rsquo;s review rightly criticises, not particularly constructive, but the hope (implausible, I admit) was that researchers from the network/complexity science perspective would integrate some of the ideas in their models. But perhaps it is up to us. Interdisciplinarity is hard.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sentiment analysis of song lyrics by genre</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2020_mxm_genres/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2020_mxm_genres/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a recent &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/evolutionary-human-sciences/article/cultural-evolution-of-emotional-expression-in-50-years-of-song-lyrics/E6E64C02BDB0480DB13B8B6BB7DFF598/core-reader&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href=&#34;https://lottybrand.wordpress.com&#34;&gt;Lotty Brand&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://alexmesoudi.com&#34;&gt;Alex Mesoudi&lt;/a&gt;, we documented how the lyrics of popular songs have become sadder in the last few decades. The proportion of words with positive emotional content has decreased and, on the contrary, the proportion of words with negative emotional content has increased, on average, from the 1960s to now. (If you are a reader of this blog you probably already know about all that - if not, see &lt;a href=&#34;https://aeon.co/ideas/why-are-pop-songs-getting-sadder-than-they-used-to-be&#34;&gt;this aeon piece&lt;/a&gt; for more about the research).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several people have suggested that this could be mainly due to the fact that new - sadder or angrier - genres (for example &lt;a href=&#34;https://marginalrevolution.com/marginalrevolution/2020/02/pop-songs-are-getting-sadder-and-angrier.html&#34;&gt;hip-hop&lt;/a&gt;) have replaced the genres dominant fifty years ago. This is a sensible hypothesis. In one of the two datasets we used for the main analysis (indicated in the paper as &amp;ldquo;mxm&amp;rdquo; dataset), derived from the lyrics in the website &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.musixmatch.com&#34;&gt;musixmatch.com&lt;/a&gt;, songs are also tagged with their genre, so it was relatively straightforward to explore the contribution of each genre to the general trend. The R code and the outputs are available in a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/albertoacerbi/mxm_genres_analysis&#34;&gt;GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, here the general trends for the &amp;ldquo;mxm&amp;rdquo; dataset. (If you are interested, we explain in the aeon piece linked above what the facts that these numbers are small and that the proportion of negative emotion-words is anyway always lower than the proportion of positive emotion-words mean for the importance of the trends.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./mxm_all.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going to the genre analysis, there are 168 possible genre tags in the dataset, on a total of 159,015 songs, but the most common 20 genres account for 99% of all songs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./genres.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are clear difference in the emotional tone of lyrics in different genres, and they correspond to the general intuition: among the &lt;em&gt;sad&lt;/em&gt; genres there are indeed recently emerged ones, such as &amp;ldquo;Heavy Metal&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Punk&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Hip Hop/Rap&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Indie Rock&amp;rdquo;, or &amp;ldquo;Alternative&amp;rdquo;. (&amp;ldquo;Holiday&amp;rdquo;, the more positive and less negative genre, is basically the Spotify Christmas playlist of your dreams - or nightmares perhaps.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./overall_emo_genres.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can also look at the prevalence of genres through years. Genres like &amp;ldquo;Alternative&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Heavy Metal&amp;rdquo; did indeed grew in popularity, whereas they were completely absent in the 1960s. On the contrary, positively-connotated genres like &amp;ldquo;R&amp;amp;B/Soul&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Christian &amp;amp; Gospel&amp;rdquo; show a strong decrease. Notice &amp;ldquo;Hip Hop/Rap&amp;rdquo; does not appear as growing too much in this dataset, which implies that is not the cause of the increase of negative emotion in lyrics (&lt;em&gt;in this dataset&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./featured.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This suggests that there is some truth in the idea that the overall increase in sadness is due to the emergence of new, sadder, genres. Genres like &amp;ldquo;Alternative&amp;rdquo;, for example, did not show any trend, but their &amp;ldquo;baseline&amp;rdquo;, so to speak, corresponds well to the current levels of negative/positive emotions overall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./mxm_Alternative.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Heavy Metal&amp;rdquo;, consistently with the stereotype, is indeed, on average, a sad genre - as I said on Twitter, &amp;ldquo;unsurprising sentiment analysis results are good sentiment analysis results&amp;rdquo;. In fact, in 2010, the proportion of words expressing negative emotions was &lt;em&gt;higher&lt;/em&gt; than the proportion of words expressing positive emotions, going beyond the overall results (and showing that the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pnas.org/content/112/8/2389&#34;&gt;Polyanna principle&lt;/a&gt; does not hold everywhere&amp;hellip;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./mxm_Heavy_Metal.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, we can see that also &amp;ldquo;Rock&amp;rdquo; and Pop&amp;quot;, the two most popular genres in the 1960s and still accounting for more than 30% of the total number of songs in 2010, show clear trends going in the overall direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./mxm_Rock.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./mxm_Pop.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This suggests that the overall trend is not only imputable to the introduction of new genres, but that also &amp;ldquo;classic&amp;rdquo; genres have become sadder. In the same &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/albertoacerbi/mxm_genres_analysis&#34;&gt;GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;, you can find the correspondent plots for all the 20 genres analysed.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sentiment analysis of Child Ballads&#39; lyrics</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2020_child_ballads/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2020_child_ballads/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./featured.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have recently published, together with &lt;a href=&#34;https://lottybrand.wordpress.com&#34;&gt;Lotty Brand&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://alexmesoudi.com&#34;&gt;Alex Mesoudi&lt;/a&gt;, a paper studying the expression of emotions in the lyrics of the last 50 years of English-language pop songs - open access &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/evolutionary-human-sciences/article/cultural-evolution-of-emotional-expression-in-50-years-of-song-lyrics/E6E64C02BDB0480DB13B8B6BB7DFF598/core-reader&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. We try to explain two related empirical findings: the frequency of words with positive emotional content decreases and, on the contrary, the frequency of words with negative emotional content increases in song lyrics. (Both by roughly one third. If, for example, the average song in 1960s had 30 words associated with negative emotion, the average song in 2010s has 40, assuming that they have the same total number of words.) This is a specific aspect of a relatively well-known phenomenon, that has been measured in various ways: pop songs have become sadder in the last decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we added in the paper is an attempt of explaining why this happened. We looked for cultural influences, such as upcoming artists copying the emotional tone from successful, or prestigious, artists of the previous years, but we did not find they were able to explain the pattern. We found, instead, that a general preference for songs with more negative lyrics, coupled with &amp;ldquo;unbiased transmission&amp;rdquo;, i.e. upcoming artists copying at random from the artists of the previous years, could explain it. Of course, upcoming artists do not &amp;ldquo;copy at random&amp;rdquo;: unbiased transmission stands for many unknown processes that cumulatively appear similar to genetic drift, where songs tend to &amp;ldquo;inherit&amp;rdquo; from one year to the other some of their features. The effect of unbiased transmission is important in our statistical model, but unbiased transmission is non-directional, so that a preference for negative lyrics, even if weak, can drive the process. We also wrote a popular piece about it in &lt;a href=&#34;https://aeon.co/ideas/why-are-pop-songs-getting-sadder-than-they-used-to-be&#34;&gt;aeon&lt;/a&gt;, where we explain more in detail all that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An interesting question for me is then why, if there is a general preference for negative lyrics, we observe a &lt;em&gt;trend&lt;/em&gt; toward sadder songs or, in other words, why songs in the 1960s, at the beginning of our datasets, were happier? There are many possible answers here: one, that I thought possible, was that in the middle of last century songs were artificially, so to say, happier, possibly because of more control from centralised broadcasting networks, producers, and similar. It could have been possible that, if few people in the key positions wanted to push happier songs, they could succeed. Or at least, their work would have been easier than now, when we have access to more options, from private radio to recorded tape cassettes to, obviously, Spotify and co. In sum, access to more options allows people to listen to the music they &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; want to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How to test this idea? An immediate prediction is that older songs should be sadder than middle-of-last-century songs. After some searches, and a chat with &lt;a href=&#34;https://patrickesavage.wordpress.com&#34;&gt;Pat Savage&lt;/a&gt;, I found the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Child_Ballads&#34;&gt;Child Ballads&lt;/a&gt;, a collection of 305 traditional ballads, put together in the 19th century. The datation of the ballads is problematic (even though most of them are probably from the 19th century), but the collection fits well in a not-very rigorous, but useful, category of &amp;ldquo;older&amp;rdquo; songs. I extracted the texts from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sacred-texts.com/neu/eng/child/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and performed the same sentiment analysis I have made for the recent pop songs. An obvious problem is that the sentiment analysis (&lt;a href=&#34;http://liwc.wpengine.com&#34;&gt;LIWC&lt;/a&gt;, dictionary-based) uses a contemporary lexicon, which may not be suitable for the analysis of old lyrics. A shortcut I used for this (very) exploratory analysis is to also check how many of the words in each songs were recognised by a &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/hunspell/vignettes/intro.html&#34;&gt;contemporary English dictionary&lt;/a&gt; and to use this figure to calculate the proportion of positive- and negative-emotion words. All the code is available in a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/albertoacerbi/child_ballads_emo&#34;&gt;GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;.     &lt;br&gt;
It looks my hypothesis was wrong. The proportion of words associated to emotions, both positive and negative, is more similar to the 1960s figure than to the contemporary one. In sum, old ballads are happier than contemporary pop songs, and in line with pop songs of fifty years ago. (In the plot below, &amp;ldquo;Billboard&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;mxm&amp;rdquo; are the two datasets we used to assess the sentiment of the last fifty years songs. More information in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/evolutionary-human-sciences/article/cultural-evolution-of-emotional-expression-in-50-years-of-song-lyrics/E6E64C02BDB0480DB13B8B6BB7DFF598/core-reader&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; or in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://aeon.co/ideas/why-are-pop-songs-getting-sadder-than-they-used-to-be&#34;&gt;aeon piece&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./positive.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./negative.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, this is a very basic, and hardly rigorous, analysis. In my intuition old ballads are not exactly cheerful and breezy. Still, apparently, they are, at least when compared to contemporary pop lyrics. What to do with these results, I do not know. Are there more rigorous assessments of sentiment for old song lyrics around? Are Child ballads representative? Other ideas that can explain the contemporary trends? Feedback and advice are welcome as usual!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The impact of the “World’s 25 Most Endangered Primates” list on scientific publications and media</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2020_jnc/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2020_jnc/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1016/j.jnc.2020.125794&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A few thoughts on cultural attraction</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2020_cultural_attraction/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2020_cultural_attraction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./featured.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I am finishing the work on the submission of a modelling paper about cultural attraction theory (the preprint, quite different from the current version, is &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/vjcq3/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), I thought I could go back after a while to a darling of this blog. Writing down these few musings is mostly useful for me, but perhaps they can be interesting for the people that already know the diatribe - the post is hardly a crowd-pleaser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, my general position is more or less stable on what I wrote five (!) years ago together with Alex Mesoudi (&lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10539-015-9490-2&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, even if I have a different opinion on many specific points) and, more recently, in the first half of the &amp;ldquo;Transmitting and sharing&amp;rdquo; chapter of my &lt;a href=&#34;https://global.oup.com/academic/product/cultural-evolution-in-the-digital-age-9780198835943?cc=gb&amp;amp;lang=en&amp;amp;&#34;&gt;book&lt;/a&gt;. The points carried forward by cultural attraction theory are valuable and overlooked in much cultural evolution research, so it is important to pay attention to them. Convergent transformation can, as much as faithful copying, bring about cultural stability. Explaining the diffusion of a trait with &lt;em&gt;culture&lt;/em&gt; - a tendency to copy others faithfully - is to assume what requires itself an explanation. We copy the majority, the successful, the elders: until we do not. Individual and social learning are not two different processes, and, yes, I now think that culture &amp;ldquo;is a property, not a thing&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other side, hi-fi copying is important in some domains, and there is a limit to what convergent transformations can achieve. Cultural transmission does allow for the diffusion of &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; information that can not be reconstructed. Cultural attraction people are correct, technically, when they say that high-fidelity transmission is a special case of attraction, with reconstruction equal to zero, or something analogous. However, I believe that the advantages linked to the generality of a theory depend on what we are trying to explain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My position is annoying as I guess I end up to slightly irritating both camps, but, despite what you heard on Twitter, academics are (mostly) a bunch of nice people, and I tend to be able to work with both the factions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, I became more and more convinced that the main reason for the disagreement resides in the fact that different people ask different &amp;ldquo;deep&amp;rdquo; questions about culture. Thom Scott-Phillips says something similar &lt;a href=&#34;https://thomscottphillips.files.wordpress.com/2016/05/scott-phillips-2016-review-of-lewens.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; (at the end of section 2). Many cultural evolutionists are interested to explain what is so special in humans, and the answer is, correctly: culture, as they define it. Many cultural attractionists (?), instead, are interested to explain why some cultural traits are succesfull, given the state of the world and of its inhabitants. Again, I tend to share the latter interest but, of course, both questions are legitimate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A similar way to put it is that many cultural attractionists are humanists (as in researchers working in the humanities) or social scientists that become frustrated with non-scientific explanations of culture, and pushed interdisciplinarity towards hard sciences. Many cultural evolutionists are instead natural scientists that &amp;ldquo;discovered&amp;rdquo; that culture is important to explain human and, up to a point, non-human behaviour, and pushed  interdisciplinarity the other way around. This does not need to be literally true - people actually following the exact career path - but it seems to me it catches an interesting difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, and perhaps most controversial, cultural attraction theory stresses (recently with more emphasis) that factors of attraction are multifaceted and, in particular, not only cognitive. Again, for the internal consistency of the theory, this is perfectly right. Personally, I met cultural attraction theory (which was called, at the time, &amp;ldquo;epidemiology of representations&amp;rdquo;) reading Dan Sperber&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Explaining-Culture-Naturalistic-Dan-Sperber/dp/0631200452&#34;&gt;Explaining Culture&lt;/a&gt;, and this changed my scientific life (and, as a consequence, if I look at it from today&amp;rsquo;s perspective, my life tout-court). While the book is the classic source for the &amp;ldquo;factors of attraction can be psychological and ecological&amp;rdquo; motto, it is also home of chapters on culture and mental (massive) modularity, anthropology and psychology, etc. For me, at least, there was a clear message that pan-human cognitive similarities constrain the forms that cultures can take, and contribute to explaining them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Independently on how these cognitive similarities are implemented and on how they arise, I still believe that cultural attraction theory is more &lt;em&gt;interesting&lt;/em&gt; if this message is true, and I would not shy away from that. For reconstruction and convergent transformation to provide satisfying explanations, they should be reconducted to a coherent something else, whatever this will be. Of course, the importance of these constraints is variable and domain-dependent, so that in some cases we should prefer reconstruction-based explanations, and in others preservative-transmission-based explanations, but that is, I believe, a stimulating empirical problem for cultural evolutionists.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cultural evolution in the digital age</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2019_oup/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2019_oup/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Book Club at &lt;a href=&#34;http://cognitionandculture.net/webinars/cultural-evolution-in-the-digital-age/&#34;&gt;cognitionandculture.net&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;International Cognition and Culture Institute&lt;/em&gt; has organised a book club around Cultural Evolution in the Digital Age running in June and July 2020. The book club includes my precis, commentaries by Alex Mesoudi, Hugo Mercier, Mathieu Charbonneau, Olivier Morin, Pascal Boyer, Sacha Altay, and Tiffany Morisseau, plus my reply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Academic reviews:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Joshua Conrad Jackson, &lt;a href=&#34;https://escholarship.org/uc/item/8hg2441f&#34;&gt;New Technology, Same Culture&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Cliodynamics: The Journal of Quantitative History and Cultural Evolution&lt;/em&gt;, 2020&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With &lt;em&gt;Cultural Evolution in the Digital Age&lt;/em&gt;, Acerbi joins the likes of Peter Turchin, David Sloan Wilson, and Joseph Henrich in offering an engaging and accessible application of cultural evolutionary models, which will almost certainly attract new scholars to the field. Never did I expect to read about Grumpy Cat and the social brain hypothesis in the same book, but the result was genuinely satisfying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stefan Velesky, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jstor.org/stable/10.26613/esic.4.2.195&#34;&gt;Review of Cultural Evolution in the Digital Age&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Evolutionary Studies in Imaginative Culture&lt;/em&gt;, 2020&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Cultural Evolution in the Digital Age,&lt;/em&gt; Acerbi combines cultural evolution with cognitive anthropology and media studies to provide one of the most solid science-based takes on the impact of digital media on human behavior to date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Andrew Buskell, &lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10441-020-09384-x&#34;&gt;Evolution, Cultural Evolution, and Epistemic Optimism&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Acta Biotheoretica&lt;/em&gt;, 2020&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&amp;hellip;] enjoyable, story-driven journey. [&amp;hellip;] guide the reader through large and expanding literatures in an entertaining and illuminating way. [&amp;hellip;] upbeat about human capabilities and provide a useful optimistic counterpoint to the recent spate of epistemological doomsayers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oleg Sobchuk, &lt;a href=&#34;https://academic.oup.com/joc/advance-article-abstract/doi/10.1093/joc/jqaa038/6124730&#34;&gt;Cultural Evolution in the Digital Age&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Journal of Communication&lt;/em&gt;, 2021&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book by the anthropologist Alberto Acerbi builds a bridge between the field of media and communication studies and a rather new approach to studying culture: cultural evolution. Can this bridge be a firm structure? And do media studies and cultural evolution even need each other? Acerbi makes a persuasive case for the usefulness and importance of this connection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Simone Marsi, &lt;a href=&#34;https://ojs.unica.it/index.php/between/article/view/5245&#34;&gt;Cultural Evolution in the Digital Age&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Between&lt;/em&gt;, 2022 (Italian)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Con rigore scientifico, poggiando i piedi su esperimenti di antropologia e riflessioni scientifiche sull’evoluzionismo, Acerbi ci conduce in un inedito viaggio nella nostra quotidianità, disvelando pregiudizi e falsi miti sul mondo digitale, che sottratto al dibattito tra apocalittici della società reale e guru integrati nel mondo dei social, ci viene riproposto come un luogo in cui l’uomo mette in scena sé stesso, con i suoi difetti più torbidi e la sua più alta aspirazione alla conoscenza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;General reviews:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Acerbi advocates for a moderate approach to understanding the impact of digital media. Taking the &amp;ldquo;long view&amp;rdquo; provides a more accurate assessment than alarmist reactions. [&amp;hellip;] Acerbi&amp;rsquo;s book is filled with hope; it is not a Pollyanna assessment of the digital world but a balanced view.&amp;quot; - &lt;em&gt;Choice&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Media coverage:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/AX0Jy0__DbE&#34;&gt;Interview for the podcast &amp;lsquo;The Dissenter&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cs.eslrsociety.org/2020/07/15/cultural-evolution-in-the-digital-age/&#34;&gt;Interview for Cultured Scene, the Early Career Social Learning Researcher&amp;rsquo;s Society magazine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.trouw.nl/wetenschap/sturen-algoritmen-ons-gedrag-dat-valt-best-mee~ba0035f5/&#34;&gt;Sturen algoritmen ons gedrag? Dat valt best mee&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Trouw&lt;/em&gt; (The Netherlands)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lepoint.fr/phebe/phebe-tout-ce-que-vous-pensiez-savoir-d-internet-est-sans-doute-faux-07-02-2020-2361661_3590.php#&#34;&gt;Tout ce que vous pensiez savoir d&amp;rsquo;Internet est (sans doute) faux&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Le Point&lt;/em&gt; (France)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-isbn=&#34;9780198835943&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cultural evolution of emotional expression in 50 years of song lyrics</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2019_ehs/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2019_ehs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Together with Lotty Brand, we wrote a piece for &lt;em&gt;aeon&lt;/em&gt; about the paper: &lt;a href=&#34;https://aeon.co/ideas/why-are-pop-songs-getting-sadder-than-they-used-to-be&#34;&gt;Why are pop songs getting sadder than they used to be?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The piece was then widely covered by popular and scientific media, including for example &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thetimes.co.uk/edition/news/heaven-knows-pops-miserable-now-777dzqw7x&#34;&gt;The Times&lt;/a&gt; (UK), &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.standaard.be/cnt/dmf20200226_04866569&#34;&gt;De Standaard&lt;/a&gt; (Belgium), or &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.information.dk/kultur/2020/02/popsange-soergeligere-soergeligere-viser-ny-undersoegelse&#34;&gt;Dagbaldet Information&lt;/a&gt; (Danemark)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1017/ehs.2019.11&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sichuan food and the transience of traditions</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2019_sichuan/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2019_sichuan/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of my secret passion (or not-so-secret, if you know me a bit) is cooking. Last weekend was devoted to the new edition of Fuchsia Dunlop&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Food-Sichuan-Fuchsia-Dunlop/dp/1324004835&#34;&gt;The Food of Sichuan&lt;/a&gt;, widely considered as one of the best western-accessible resource on the topic. If you want to know, I cooked &amp;lsquo;Strange Flavour&amp;rsquo; Bang Bang Chicken and Fish-Fragrant Aubergines. (Both will need much improvement&amp;mdash;for example I ended up burning the peanuts while deep-frying them&amp;hellip;&amp;mdash; so if I ever happen to offer to cook you Sichuan food, ask for my only piece of resistance so far, the classic Mapo Tofu.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book has a fairly good historical introduction, where a few things caught my eye. Sure, the cuisine of Sichuan is renowned for its variety, and for the ability to combine several ingredients to create distinctive flavour combinations, but at the end of the day many of us will appreciate it for the signature &amp;ldquo;hot-and-numbing&amp;rdquo; taste given by the combination of Sichuan pepper (in the picture below) and abundant serving of chillies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./featured.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, at odd with my intuitive idea of a millennia-old culinary tradition, chillies obviously &amp;ldquo;only reached China in the late sixteenth century [&amp;hellip;] probably brought to China by Portuguese traders&amp;rdquo;. The &lt;em&gt;barbarian peppers&lt;/em&gt; were considered an ornamental plant: &amp;ldquo;it would be at least another century before the use of chillies to flavour food was documented&amp;rdquo;. According to this account, &amp;ldquo;it wasn&amp;rsquo;t until the reign of the Jiaqing Emperor (1796-1820)&amp;rdquo; that the plant was established as a local crop in Sichuan, that is, two centuries ago. Deep-frying, which I associated intimately with Chinese cuisine, seems even more recent in Sichuan: &amp;ldquo;an interest in deep-frying [&amp;hellip;] is said to have come from Americans in 1930s Chongqing.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This reminded me of my previous research about Swedish food. (Yes, when living in Stockholm I had a blog about Swedish food, alas only in Italian, but you can have a look at some popular post, for example &lt;a href=&#34;https://cucinasvedeseperitaliani.wordpress.com/2010/09/08/surstromming/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://cucinasvedeseperitaliani.wordpress.com/2010/04/20/kottbullar/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.) Many classic recipes of the Swedish traditions were, in fact, the results of a few successful recipe books that appeared after the Second World War and canonised the &lt;em&gt;Husmanskost&lt;/em&gt;, i.e. the &amp;ldquo;traditional&amp;rdquo; home-cooked Swedish food. Traditional is in quotation marks not by chance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another example is an Italian classic: &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carbonara&#34;&gt;pasta alla carbonara&lt;/a&gt;. Some even speculate that it was invented to please American soldiers during the liberation of Rome in 1944, by reminding them of their eggs and bacon breakfasts. Whatever this is true or not (it looks too good to be true though), the recipe is never mentioned before the Second World War, suggesting a recent origin. By the way: no onions and no cream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe many other examples can be found for &amp;ldquo;traditional&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;classic&amp;rdquo; dishes. This is of course nothing new. Another of my not-so-secrets is that I had a classic anthropological formation, and, in socio-cultural anthropology, that traditions are often &lt;a href=&#34;https://books.google.co.uk/books/about/The_Invention_of_Tradition.html?id=sfvnNdVY3KIC&amp;amp;source=kp_book_description&amp;amp;redir_esc=y&#34;&gt;invented&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://books.google.co.uk/books/about/Imagined_Communities.html?id=nQ9jXXJV-vgC&amp;amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;amp;source=kp_read_button&amp;amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;amp;q&amp;amp;f=false&#34;&gt;imagined&lt;/a&gt; is common currency. In &lt;a href=&#34;https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=kSukCgAAQBAJ&amp;amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;amp;dq=how+traditions+live+and+day&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ved=0ahUKEwiRkqKZu9DlAhWtTxUIHY53AtkQ6AEIKTAA#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=how%20traditions%20live%20and%20day&amp;amp;f=false&#34;&gt;How Traditions Live and Die&lt;/a&gt; Olivier Morin makes an analogous point using the example of Highland&amp;rsquo;s clans tartans, that were single-handedly created by a fabric producer in the 19th century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other traditions may be indeed millennia old. For example, Sara Graça da Silva and Jamie Tehrani used &lt;a href=&#34;https://royalsocietypublishing.org/doi/10.1098/rsos.150645&#34;&gt;phylogenetic methods&lt;/a&gt; to analyse the relationships between folktales in Indo-European-speaking societies, and they claim to have found &amp;ldquo;evidence that one tale (‘The Smith and the Devil’) can be traced back to the Bronze Age&amp;rdquo;. The point is: we should be wary of considering traditions as, by-default, ancient and robust (perhaps because of an inborn tendency to copy others). Some may be, and others may be not. I wonder whether cultural evolutionists, beside Morin&amp;rsquo;s book and a less recent, and not very well-known I believe, book from Pascal Boyer (&lt;a href=&#34;https://books.google.co.uk/books/about/Tradition_as_Truth_and_Communication.html?id=Wuf2PXR1pBgC&amp;amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;amp;source=kp_read_button&amp;amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;amp;q&amp;amp;f=false&#34;&gt;Tradition as Truth and Communication&lt;/a&gt;), have explored in detail the topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A more general reflection: a backbone of cultural evolution is population thinking, which implies that culture is an emergent, population-level, product of individual interactions, and individual interactions are where the causal magic happens (at least, this is how I read it). From this perspective, it looks natural to think to cultural traditions in a non-essentialist way: they are just the temporary result of individual interactions, looked at on a certain zoom level. However, sometimes &amp;ldquo;culture&amp;rdquo; is essentialised and used itself as an explanation, as in &amp;ldquo;we do it &lt;em&gt;because of our culture&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;. These kinds of explanations are more and more present when reporting and justifying transcultural experiments (a good criticism of this notion of culture is in &lt;a href=&#34;https://brill.com/view/journals/jocc/18/3-4/article-p231_1.xml&#34;&gt;this paper&lt;/a&gt; from Lawrence Hirschfeld). Transcultural experiments are important and necessary, but we need to be cautious when we say that &amp;ldquo;eastern people&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;the Aka&amp;rdquo;, or any other experimental group, behave differently because of &amp;ldquo;culture&amp;rdquo;. It could be, but it could also be that many, interrelated, possibly short-lived, traditions create a specific situation, and it would be interesting to be able to disentangle these possibilities. Anthropologists (in anthropology the WEIRD problem is as a minumum a century-old one: a true tradition!) have recognised this problem, but the solutions proposed have not been, in my opinion, particularly successful, but this may be material for another post.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RStudio on Amazon Web Services</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2019_aws_rstudio/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2019_aws_rstudio/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here a situation that may have occurred to some of you: your R script (a model analysing a big dataset, a simulation where you test many parameter combinations) needs hours to run. If you are lucky, you may have access to a cluster, or a remote computer, where you can run your script. All sorted. Sometimes - as it happens to me now, running &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/albertoacerbi/oranzees&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; individual-based model - you do not have this option. However, I just found out that launching your &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rstudio.com&#34;&gt;RStudio&lt;/a&gt; script on Amazon Web Service (&lt;a href=&#34;https://aws.amazon.com&#34;&gt;AWS&lt;/a&gt;) is quite easy (and it is free).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the information needed is scattered on the web, I put together a short tutorial. If you do not trust me, most material comes from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.louisaslett.com/RStudio_AMI/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, but it is not  explained step-by-step, some information are possibly not relevant for a non-expert (as myself) and, mostly, the AWS interface has been changed from when the page was written. So, follow this short instructions, and you can close your laptop and have your script running for you somewhere else!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-by-step-tutorial&#34;&gt;Step-by-step tutorial&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;1-create-an-aws-account&#34;&gt;(1) Create an AWS account&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, we need an AWS account. Amazon Web Service &amp;ldquo;provides on-demand cloud computing platforms to individuals, companies, and governments, on a metered pay-as-you-go basis&amp;rdquo;. However, some products - including the one we will use - are free. Let&amp;rsquo;s go to &lt;a href=&#34;https://aws.amazon.com/&#34;&gt;the AWS webpage&lt;/a&gt; and create the account. It asks us some personal data, including the address and, annoyingly, a credit card number, in case we use products that are not free, or exceed the usage limits. (In any case, Amazon probably already knows our credit card number.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;2-launch-the-ami&#34;&gt;(2) Launch the AMI&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we want to run our script in the Amazon cloud. Ideally, we would like to run it on a (virtual) computer with RStudio installed. Luckily, someone already did this. Go to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.louisaslett.com/RStudio_AMI/&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; webpage and choose one of the &lt;em&gt;AMI&lt;/em&gt; on the right of the page, according to the geographic location (in my case: EU West, London).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amazon_Machine_Image&#34;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; is the Wikipedia page about AMI (Amazon Machine Image) if you want to know more, but you do not need to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./01.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;3-choose-the-instance&#34;&gt;(3) Choose the instance&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we landed on the AWS page of the AMI we choose. The &amp;ldquo;Free Tier&amp;rdquo; instance is already selected, so we do not have to do anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./02.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;4-configure-the-security&#34;&gt;(4) Configure the security&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To access to Rstudio in the cloud with our browser we need to configure the security in the right way. Thus, before launching the instance, we need to go on the tab 6 (&amp;ldquo;Configure Security Group&amp;rdquo;), and select &amp;ldquo;HTTP&amp;rdquo; from the drop-down menu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./03.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;5-review-and-launch&#34;&gt;(5) Review and launch&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We click on &amp;ldquo;Review and Launch&amp;rdquo; and we land on this page. Check that the &amp;ldquo;AMI details&amp;rdquo; are correct and then click &amp;ldquo;Launch&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./04.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;6-select-the-key-pair&#34;&gt;(6) Select the key pair&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before launching the instance, we are asked to select a key pair. From the drop-down menu we choose &amp;ldquo;Proceed without a key pair&amp;rdquo;, and check the box below. Now we can click &amp;ldquo;Launch Instances&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./05.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;7-the-instance-is-launched&#34;&gt;(7) The instance is launched!&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All good. Click on the ID of the instance (it will be different from the one shown here), to access it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./06.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;8-connecting-to-rstudio&#34;&gt;(8) Connecting to RStudio&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the console of our instance. After some time, the &amp;ldquo;Instance State&amp;rdquo; will be on &amp;ldquo;running&amp;rdquo;. We need to copy the Public DNS, and paste it in the address bar of another page our browser to access our instance of RStudio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./07.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;9-starting-rstudio&#34;&gt;(9) Starting RStudio&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a while this page should appear (if not, we need to wait a bit an retry, it may need a few minutes). The username is &amp;ldquo;rstudio&amp;rdquo;, and the password is our &amp;ldquo;Instance ID&amp;rdquo; (see the previous screenshot, on the left side of the Public DNS).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./08.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;10-virtual-rstudio&#34;&gt;(10) Virtual RStudio&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If all went well, we should see the familiar screen below. There is a &lt;strong&gt;Welcome.R&lt;/strong&gt; script. There are two things we should do (which are well explained in the script). First, it is advisable to change our password, from the &amp;ldquo;Instance ID&amp;rdquo; to something else of our choice. To do this, we first load the package included (&lt;code&gt;library(&amp;quot;RStudioAMI&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;), and use the function &lt;code&gt;passwd()&lt;/code&gt;, which asks for old and new password. The second thing is that we can link our Dropbox so that we can load directly our script, using the function &lt;code&gt;linkDropbox()&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./09.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;11-authorising-dropbox&#34;&gt;(11) Authorising Dropbox&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After few seconds, a message on the RStudio console (&amp;ldquo;Please visit the following URL in your browser now to link the server to your Dropbox account:&amp;rdquo;) will prompt us to authorise the cloud computer to connect to our Dropbox, landing on this page. We need to click on &amp;ldquo;Connect&amp;rdquo;. (We will also receive a mail from Dropbox asking to confirm.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./10.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;12-excluding-folders-from-dropbox-sync&#34;&gt;(12) Excluding folders from Dropbox sync&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, a &amp;ldquo;Dropbox&amp;rdquo; folder appears in the &amp;ldquo;Files&amp;rdquo; tab of RStudio. We do not want to sync &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; our Dropbox folder in the cloud. When our Dropbox folders start to appear in RStudio, we can use the function &lt;code&gt;excludeSyncDropbox(&amp;quot;*&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt; to exclude all files to be synced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./11.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;13-syncing-what-we-need&#34;&gt;(13) Syncing what we need&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine the script we need to run is called &lt;strong&gt;scriptThatRunsForHours.R&lt;/strong&gt;. A good idea is to create a folder in our dropbox - let&amp;rsquo;s call it &amp;ldquo;AWS_RStudio&amp;rdquo; and put the script in that folder. Now we can ask to synchronise only this folder, using the function &lt;code&gt;includeSyncDropbox(&amp;quot;AWS_RStudio&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;. Now we can open our script as we would do in our local RStudio and do whatever we need to do with it, including running it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./12.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;14-going-back-the-script&#34;&gt;(14) Going back the script&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the script runs, we can close our browser, and just forget about it. To go back to our instance, we go again on the AWS webpage, we login to our account, and we click the EC2 service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./13.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We should have one instance running. Clicking on it, we are back to the instance console (see point 8), from where, following again points 8 and 9, we go again on our virtual RStudio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./14.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;15-terminate-the-instance&#34;&gt;(15) Terminate the instance&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the script is finished, and if we do not have anything else to run, from the instance console we can &amp;ldquo;terminate&amp;rdquo; the instance, as shown below. All done!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./15.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;limitations&#34;&gt;Limitations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This quick tutorial is intended as a very basic shortcut to run RStudio on AWS. The pros are that it works, that it should have you run a R script in a handful of minutes and that it does not require any technical knowledge. On the other hand, there are some obvious limitations (all suggestions are more than welcome!):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have not been able to write output files on my local computer. While the modifications of the scripts I made in the instance are saved on my Dropbox, the output files, produced with &lt;code&gt;write_csv(&amp;quot;myLongScriptOutput.csv&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt; are not. They appear in the &amp;ldquo;Files&amp;rdquo; tab in the virtual RStudio and I manually export them from there to my computer (&amp;ldquo;More&amp;gt;Export&amp;rdquo;). This is not very elegant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The virtual RStudio comes with some packages pre-installed. In particular, the &amp;ldquo;tidyverse&amp;rdquo; package, which is the only one I needed, is there. I did not try to install any other package, so I do not know whether this will work straightforwardly or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most annoying aspect is that my script runs &lt;em&gt;slower&lt;/em&gt; in the cloud that on my laptop! (Around twice slower.) This is probably due to the fact that I am using a &amp;ldquo;Free Tier&amp;rdquo; instance, so I would need to pay for more computational power. So, this is a viable option if you are not exactly in a rush, unless someone finds a solution to this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I just scratched the surface of what one can do (again the goal was to provide a fast and easy solution). I do not have idea of how the majority of the options present in the instance console work, and I did not mention few for which I have some idea. (For example, how to monitor your script, or how to pair your instance with a ssh key so to access it directly from terminal, see point 6).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As usual, comments and feedback welcome, and happy to know about better solutions!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vaccine hesitancy is not correlated with social media penetration at country-level in Europe</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2019_wellcome/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2019_wellcome/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Wellcome Trust has recently (yesterday) released the 2018 &lt;a href=&#34;https://wellcome.ac.uk/reports/wellcome-global-monitor/2018&#34;&gt;Global Monitor&lt;/a&gt;, a 140,000 people survey on how ‘people around the world think and feel about science and major health challenges’. Among the many interesting pieces of information, not surprisingly, attitudes towards vaccinations are starting to be widely discussed in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/society/2019/jun/19/survey-shows-crisis-of-confidence-in-vaccines-in-parts-of-europe&#34;&gt;press&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first important thing to notice, as the Wellcome Trust correctly does, is that ‘worldwide, 79% of people agree that vaccines are safe and 84% agree that they are effective’ and ‘92% of parents worldwide said that their children have received a vaccine to prevent them from getting childhood diseases .’ Whatever we may think, the majority of people around the world rightly believe that vaccines are good. Of course, there is a minority of people, especially in western countries, that is less convinced of that. Citing again the Wellcome Trust, ‘In France, one in three people disagree that vaccines are safe, the highest percentage for any country worldwide’. The France figure is, however, one of few outliers, also for western countries, where the averages of people disagreeing that vaccines are safe are around 10%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, that one out of ten persons in western countries could think as such is worrying. Not surprisingly, social media has been identified as one of the culprits of this situation, and I bet that, following the Wellcome Trust survey, the trend will continue (I already found one article &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.independent.co.uk/news/health/anti-vaxx-vaccination-myth-poll-europe-pro-nature-birth-a8964441.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). Out of curiosity, I correlated the Wellcome trust data with recent data on social media penetration/usage in Europe, and they are not correlated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./social_media.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I was on it, I also correlated the data with the importance of religion..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./religion.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;the trust in science&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./science.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;and the GDP pro capita&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./gdp.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally, this is a very basic analysis. It could be for example that, within countries, people that are sceptical of vaccines use more social media than others. That anti-vaxx information spreads effectively in social media is not surprising. There are &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cell.com/trends/cognitive-sciences/fulltext/S1364-6613(15)00197-7?_returnURL=https%3A%2F%2Flinkinghub.elsevier.com%2Fretrieve%2Fpii%2FS1364661315001977%3Fshowall%3Dtrue&#34;&gt;many reasons&lt;/a&gt; why anti-vaccination beliefs are easy to spread (and, conversely, it could be more difficult with pro-vaccination beliefs). Information around vaccines is psychologically attractive, involving potentially disgust and counterintuitive concepts that, coupled with a possible negative bias, make fearmongering on vaccines a good topic for &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41599-019-0224-y&#34;&gt;online misinformation&lt;/a&gt;. All of this, however, is not a prerogative of digital social media (where correct, pro-vaccine, information &lt;a href=&#34;https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jama/fullarticle/2670250&#34;&gt;also spreads effectively&lt;/a&gt;), and vaccine hesitancy is &lt;a href=&#34;http://sethmnookin.com/the-panic-virus/&#34;&gt;as old as vaccines themselves&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, each time you hear someone saying, or writing, that anti-vaccination beliefs are linked to social media you should be sceptical. At least: it is not obvious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested, all the technical stuff (data, R script, what I coded exactly as “vaccine hesitancy”, “social media penetration”, etc.) are in &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/albertoacerbi/vaccines-wellcome&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; GitHub repository.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The ordeal simulation hypothesis</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2019_ordeal_simulation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2019_ordeal_simulation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You have probably heard the adagio that “man bites dog”, and not “dog bites man”, makes for a good piece of news: unusual, exceptional, events are better stories than everyday occurrences. Hidden behind the surface, however, there is another message that seems so obvious we do not even think about it: both examples are negative events. “Dog wins the lottery” would probably be a good piece of news too, but it is not mentioned. That negative news – and possibly negative narratives in general – are more attractive than positive ones is a bit of a cliché, but it supported by much research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An interesting case-study is false news. By definition, they do not need to describe real facts, so they can exploit our preferences in an almost unconstrained way. In a content analysis of a small sample of articles categorised as online misinformation, I found that &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41599-019-0224-y&#34;&gt;negative articles where around five times more numerous than positive articles&lt;/a&gt;. It is not just about news. English-language fiction became consistently more negative &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/02699931.2016.1260528&#34;&gt;in the last two centuries&lt;/a&gt;, and English-language song lyrics did the same &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/preprints/socarxiv/3j6wx/&#34;&gt;in the last fifty years&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And why, yet, this should be the case? There are many possible explanations: one is that the stories we tell each other are simulations. As much as pilots can exercise their flight skills in dangerous situations safe from risks in a simulator, the pleasure we experience when we enjoy narratives would be rooted in the possibility of exercise our skills in an analogous safe environment. The next time you are in the woods you should be suspicious of the wolf.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From this perspective, it makes sense that negative events are predominant in stories: it is worst to arrive unprepared to a negative event than to a positive one. Some &lt;a href=&#34;https://global.oup.com/academic/product/9780190666514&#34;&gt;research&lt;/a&gt; has explored the idea that, in fact, not generally negative events, but threats are what narratives are about. It does not matter &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1090513817301976&#34;&gt;how realistic the threats are&lt;/a&gt;: you can enjoy watching &lt;em&gt;The Haunting of Hill House&lt;/em&gt; even if you do not think ghosts exist or sharing the dubious news about a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.snopes.com/fact-check/morgue-employee-cremated-nap/&#34;&gt;morgue employee cremated while taking a nap&lt;/a&gt; even if you do not usually hang out in morgues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a recently published &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41599-019-0267-0&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt;, Olivier Morin, Oleg Sobchuk, and I, tried to explore further the threath simulation hypothesis. We found two problems with how the hypothesis is often presented. First, it leaves unspecified which kind of threats should be simulated in narratives. Second, and related, it is not clear whether it is a “theory of fictional content”, i.e. it applies specifically to fictional narratives, or to a more wide range of contents, since, as we saw before, also news tend to bend toward the negative (but also, for example, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11515147&#34;&gt;dreams&lt;/a&gt; have been interpreted in the same way).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the paper, we explore a more exacting version of the hypothesis, that we called the Ordeals simulation hypothesis (mainly Olivier’s brainchild). The hypothesis specifies that neither negative events in general, nor threats in general, should be overrepresented in fiction, but ordeals. Ordeals – the meaning is different from the usage of the term in common language – are threats that are severe, rare, and reactable. ‘Reactable’ here means that we cannot prevent them (as we can do for, say, cardiovascular diseases or pathogen contamination), but they are also not completely out of our control (like being struck by lighting). Aggressions, violent social interactions and, most of all, homicides, are all examples of ordeals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./ordeal.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;jpeg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first question is then whether ordeals are overrepresented in fiction with respect to other threats, or, to take a clear case: why do people die in novels? The ordeal simulation hypothesis predicts that agentive or accidental deaths (such as homicides or calamities), but not natural deaths, should be overrepresented. (&lt;em&gt;Game of Thrones&lt;/em&gt; is too easy of an &lt;a href=&#34;https://deathtimeline.com&#34;&gt;example&lt;/a&gt;, but I recently read that the currently much talked &lt;em&gt;Chernobyl&lt;/em&gt; series may have &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.forbes.com/sites/michaelshellenberger/2019/05/09/the-reason-they-fictionalize-nuclear-disasters-like-chernobyl-is-because-they-kill-so-few-people/#7e6edff641fc&#34;&gt;exaggerated&lt;/a&gt; the number of deaths). We coded hundreds of summaries of novels in wikipedia: mortality rates of novels’ characters are disproportionally high, when compared to realistic estimates. For 100,000 adults in US, between 100 and 200 deaths are estimated every year. But, in novels, we calculated this figure as 19,000, that is, three orders of magnitude higher. The realistic rate for agentive death is only 31 over 100,000, but in novels is more than 13,000. Natural deaths are also overrepresented, but less so: in reality the rate is higher than agentive deaths (107 on 100,000), while in novels is only around 2,000. (Much more in the paper.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second question is whether the prominence of agentive deaths is a specific feature of fiction with respect to other kinds of content. To explore this, we used a different methodology: we performed a computer text analysis of two large, comparable, corpora, one of novels and one of private letters and diaries, to detect the frequencies of words related to death in general, and to agentive death (‘kill’, ‘murder’, ‘execution’, etc.) in particular. The ordeal simulation hypothesis would predict that the frequency of agentive death-related words would be higher in the novels than in the private documents, but no difference should be found for general death-related words. In this case, the prediction was not confirmed: mentions of death, both violent and non-violent, were about equally frequent in fictional and non-fictional material.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What can we conclude from all that? Agentive deaths are overrepresented in fiction, but they are also, so it seems, overrepresented in material written without the intention of being made public. Perhaps the ordeal simulation hypothesis is not on the right track. My opinion, however, is that the problem may lie in finding an explanation that works for, and only for, fictional material. From the psychological point of view, how different is to read a true story, a piece of news, or a novel? (agentive deaths sure are overrepresented in news, see the plot below – full study &lt;a href=&#34;https://ourworldindata.org/does-the-news-reflect-what-we-die-from&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./OUD.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How different is to write a novel, a diary entry, or a letter? Perhaps there is no specific feature that makes fictions different from other materials, besides, as suggested before when mentioning misinformation, bigger freedom of explore possible contents. Maybe developing a “theory of fiction” (that works only for fiction) is misguided. There are various elements that make narratives (fiction, diaries, news, but also scientific theories, political orientations, etc.) attractive, these elements are the legitimate objects of study, and we can apply them to various domains, fiction included.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41599-019-0267-0&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt;, and if you are really interested, &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/fjkze/&#34;&gt;all&lt;/a&gt; the data and codes for the analysis. The paper was published in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/collections/feibciaebg&#34;&gt;Cultural Evolution&lt;/a&gt; collection of Palgrave Communications, with many other contributions worth looking at.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why people die in novels: Testing the ordeal simulation hypothesis</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2019_pal_comm_b/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2019_pal_comm_b/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote a presentation of the research behind the paper in &lt;a href=&#34;https://acerbialberto.com/post/2019_ordeal_simulation/&#34;&gt;this blog post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1057/s41599-019-0267-0&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is cultural evolution “neoliberal”?</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2019_neoliberal/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2019_neoliberal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have been involved, over the weekend, in a small twitter debate on the old question of whether anthropology should use qualitative or quantitative methodologies. The debate was not particularly interesting by itself (I had many, probably too many, similar conversations starting when I was an undergraduate student) and the readers of this blog know, or suspect, my position, so I am not dwelling on it. There is, however, a marginal aspect that made me think a bit: I have the feeling that, when it is all said and done, the negative attitudes toward quantifications are linked to the idea that quantifying human culture is politically “neoliberal”, if not altogether “right-wing”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am sure that no critic of quantification in anthropology will accept this as their own position and they will express more cogent (at least from their point of view) arguments. It does not matter: I am happy to explore a straw man here. (A tweet that was stating it explicitly appeared at some point over the weekend, and it was “liked” by one of the persons involved in the debate, but that is just a side-note, a “like” on Twitter does not need to mean anything.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whereas I can grasp why some evolutionary approaches can be considered as supporting neoliberal social policies – even though I think the question is more nuanced and complicated – how can quantification by itself be? Is studying &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.plosone.org/article/info%3Adoi%2F10.1371%2Fjournal.pone.0106565&#34;&gt;how movies influence the popularity of dog breeds&lt;/a&gt; neoliberal? Is it &lt;em&gt;counting&lt;/em&gt; how many different &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ehbonline.org/article/S1090-5138(16)30274-4/fulltext&#34;&gt;folktales&lt;/a&gt; there are in different populations? Is cultural evolution, intended as a general project of applying scientific and quantitative methods to the study of culture, neoliberal?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enough with rhetorical questions, but I would be interested if anybody knows any scholarly reference or developed argument that support this position (again, I know, it is a straw man). The only reason I can think of is that, in the last decades, researchers working on quantitative approaches to culture have been less active in political matters than researchers working on qualitative approaches, even though my impression is that the formers are politically leaning left as much as the rest of social scientists (at least the people that refer to the “cultural evolution” label).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am really not interested in starting a debate, but perhaps there are reasons for considering quantification as such, and I’d be happy to exploit collective intelligence to know more (as said, possibly in the form of scholarly publications, etc.). Ok, I am going back to my R codes now.
&lt;img src=&#34;./wall.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Morgue employee cremated by mistake while taking a nap</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2019_morgue/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/post/2019_morgue/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Online misinformation, fake news, false news, hoaxes, you name it, has been blamed for almost everything bad happening in the last years, from the success of Trump to Brexit, from the election of Bolsonaro to the (relative) spread of the anti-vax movement. The scientific consensus on the prominence and on the effect of online misinformation, however, is, at best, mixed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some highly-publicised studies had supported the scaremongers showing, for example, that falsehood spread &lt;a href=&#34;http://science.sciencemag.org/content/359/6380/1146&#34;&gt;farther, faster, deeper, and more broadly than the truth&lt;/a&gt; or that &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41562-017-0132&#34;&gt;‘low-quality’ information is equally likely to go ‘viral’ than ‘hi-quality’ information because of our ‘limited attention’&lt;/a&gt; (notice however that the former study does not compare ‘falsehood’ with ‘truth’, but debunked rumours versus confirmed rumours, so that real news that nobody debunked, i.e. the majority of them, are not even considered, and the latter has been recently retracted).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many other works, however, had painted a more nuanced image, showing that the production and the consumption of misinformation is &lt;a href=&#34;http://science.sciencemag.org/content/363/6425/374?fbclid=IwAR0ThyrRJk7feelo0SdkBr6obs3NIwjJgZt_E4QCCHYkfAva7Eo8A5A4VlI&#34;&gt;concentrated in a limited portion of social media users&lt;/a&gt;, that individuals that have already extreme political views &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dartmouth.edu/~nyhan/fake-news-2016.pdf&#34;&gt;are more likely to be exposed to political misinformation&lt;/a&gt;, and that, in general, misinformation is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.31.2.211&#34;&gt;unlikely to change people minds&lt;/a&gt;. And, simply, other studies have shown that the actual amount of online misinformation &lt;a href=&#34;http://advances.sciencemag.org/content/5/1/eaau4586&#34;&gt;is not that big&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet, the narrative supporting that online misinformation is dangerous is itself very persuasive. It is easier to think that the people that voted Trump (you can replace this with whatever you do not like) have been manipulated by evil figures, and if they would have access to the correct information they would have done the right thing. This narrative is also quite dangerous, I think, because creates an easy scapegoat (you can make up any newspaper article with this schema: “How [name of social media] helped [thing that you do not like]”) that often distract to more relevant social, economic, and cultural problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, this narrative does not fit particularly well with an evolutionary account of human behaviour. We are a species that heavily relies on communication, social interactions, and learning from others. While details widely vary, researchers studying cultural evolution and cognition agree that, for the characteristics allowing communication, social interactions, and learning from others to be evolved in the first place, we should not be too &lt;a href=&#34;https://psycnet.apa.org/record/2017-22175-001&#34;&gt;gullible&lt;/a&gt;. Of course, the conditions could be so different now that we could be more easily tricked, but this is an open question, and, given a ‘presumption of good design’, we should be at least sceptical of answers that are too pessimistic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given this somewhat reassuring perspective, however, online misinformation does exist, and one can ask what the possible advantages of misinformation could be. In a recent &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41599-019-0224-y&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt;, I proposed that one of these could simply be that misinformation can be manufactured building on features that make it attractive in an almost unconstrained way, whereas ‘true’ news cannot, simply because they need to correspond to reality. Misinformation can be designed to spread more than real information does (whether this is a conscious process or not). Cognitive anthropologists have put forward features that make some content, everything else equal, more appealing, memorable, or attention-grabbing than other content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is an example: many misinformation articles (I examine a small sample of ‘fake news’ from 2017: all the material, including the links and the texts used, is &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/78vhn/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) contains threat-related information, even though threats &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1090513817301976&#34;&gt;do not need to be relevant for us&lt;/a&gt; (as in the article that gives the title to this blog post: not many of us usually take naps in a morgue. Still, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://worldnewsdailyreport.com/morgue-employee-cremated-by-mistake-while-taking-a-nap/&#34;&gt;false news&lt;/a&gt; has been shared/liked/commented more than one million times on Facebook). Other features (negative content, disgust, etc.) and many more details are explained in the paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Misinformation is not low-quality information that succeeds in spreading because of the shortcomings of online communication. Quite the opposite, misinformation, or at least some of it, is high-quality information that spreads because online communication is efficient. The difference is that ‘quality’ is not about truthfulness, but about how it fits with our cognitive predispositions. Online “fake news”, is, from this perspective, not much of a political and propagandistic phenomenon, but is more similar to the diffusion of memes, urban legends, and the like (of course political misinformation exist, even though, interestingly, often takes advantage of similar cognitive preferences to spread, think about the notorious &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pizzagate_conspiracy_theory&#34;&gt;Pizzagate&lt;/a&gt;, with its mix of threat, sex, and disgust).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paper is part of a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/collections/feibciaebg&#34;&gt;Cultural evolution&lt;/a&gt; collection, edited by Jamie Tehrani, and I invite you to have a look at the other articles too!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./cemetery.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cognitive attraction and online misinformation</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2019_pal_comm_a/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2019_pal_comm_a/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote a presentation of the research behind the paper in &lt;a href=&#34;https://acerbialberto.com/post/2019_morgue/&#34;&gt;this blog post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cicap.org/n/articolo.php?id=278920&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; (in Italian) summarising the paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another popular &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lepoint.fr/phebe/phebe-les-vraies-raisons-du-succes-des-infox-09-09-2019-2334367_3590.php&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; (in French).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1057/s41599-019-0224-y&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Copy-the-majority of instances or individuals? Two approaches to the majority and their consequences for conformist decision-making</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2019_plos/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2019_plos/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1371/journal.pone.0210748&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>imsdb movie scripts (dataset)</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2018_imsdb/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2018_imsdb/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Did Einstein really say that? Testing content versus context in the cultural selection of quotations</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2018_jocc/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2018_jocc/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reply to ‘Sigmoidal Acquisition Curves are Good Indicators of Conformist Transmission’</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2018_sci_rep/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2018_sci_rep/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Folk-economic beliefs as “evidential fiction”: Putting the economic public discourse back on track</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2018_bbs/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2018_bbs/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Role of Neutral evolution in word turnover during centuries of English word popularity</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2017_complex_sys/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2017_complex_sys/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cultural complexity and demography: the case of folktales</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2017_ehb/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2017_ehb/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Birth of the cool: a two-centuries decline in emotional expression in Anglophone fiction</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2017_cog_emo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2017_cog_emo/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1080/02699931.2016.1260528&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Review of Tim Lewens, Cultural Evolution: Conceptual Challenges</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2017_phil_sci/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2017_phil_sci/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A cultural evolution approach to digital media</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2016_fhn/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2016_fhn/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.3389/fnhum.2016.00636&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A reappreciation of “conformity”</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2016_an_behav/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2016_an_behav/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Conformity cannot be identified based on population-level signatures</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2016_sci_rep/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2016_sci_rep/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Social learning solves the problem of narrow-peaked search landscapes: experimental evidence in humans</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2016_rsos/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2016_rsos/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The role of redundant information in cultural transmission and cultural stabilization</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2016_jcp/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2016_jcp/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Emergence of Leadership in a Group of Autonomous Robots</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2015_plos/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2015_plos/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>If we are all cultural Darwinians what’s the fuss about? Clarifying recent disagreements in the field of cultural evolution</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2015_phil_bio/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2015_phil_bio/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Philosopher Massimo Pigliucci discussed this article in [The Trouble with Cultural Evolution] (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.philosophersmag.com/index.php/footnotes-to-plato/83-the-trouble-with-cultural-evolution)&#34;&gt;http://www.philosophersmag.com/index.php/footnotes-to-plato/83-the-trouble-with-cultural-evolution)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Footnotes to Plato&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1007/s10539-015-9490-2&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dog Movies Stars and Dog Breed Popularity: A Case Study in Media Influence on Choice</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2014_plos_a/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2014_plos_a/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper has been widely covered by popular and scientific media. Here some examples:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2014/10/16/arts/international/how-much-is-that-doggie-from-the-movie.html&#34;&gt;How much is that doggie from the movie?&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The New York Times&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://news.sciencemag.org/plants-animals/2014/09/lassie-effect-movies-drive-our-preference-certain-dog-breeds&#34;&gt;The Lassie Effect: Movies drive our preference for certain dog breeds&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theguardian.com/culture/2014/sep/15/how-much-is-that-doggie-in-the-movie-films-dictate-most-popular-pooches&#34;&gt;How much is that doggie in the movie? Films dictate most popular pooches&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The Guardian&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://theconversation.com/how-the-films-youve-seen-influence-your-choice-of-dog-31498&#34;&gt;How the films you’ve seen influence your choice of dog&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The Conversation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1371/journal.pone.0106565&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Biases in cultural transmission shape the turnover of popular traits</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2014_ehb/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2014_ehb/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Books average previous decade of economic misery</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2014_plos_b/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2014_plos_b/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper has been widely covered by popular and scientific media. Here some examples:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2014/01/09/science/study-finds-literary-mood-reflects-previous-decades-economy.html?_r=0&#34;&gt;Why Wasn’t it ‘Grapes of Glee’? Study of Books Find Economic Link&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The New York Times&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://healthland.time.com/2014/01/09/the-literary-misery-index-what-the-economy-has-to-do-with-what-youre-reading/&#34;&gt;The Literary Misery Index: What the Economy Has to Do With What You’re Reading&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Time Magazine&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theguardian.com/books/2014/jan/09/study-economic-misery-literature-mood-words&#34;&gt;Literature gloom mirrors economic misery, study finds&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The Guardian&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://edition.cnn.com/2014/01/21/showbiz/literature-economy-hard-times/index.html&#34;&gt;Why hard times make for miserable books&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;CNN&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Information is power&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Radio3 Scienza&lt;/em&gt; (a radio interview in italian, I start around minute 18, download the podcast &lt;a href=&#34;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/s/0jtj91xpmqwdid5/RADIO3SCIENZA_del_17_01_2014_-_Information_is_power.mp3?dl=1&amp;amp;token_hash=AAHLOCu9F7cOk2Q2z3HHBd2SoikN5SMIV9XyfWBBfaDgTg&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1371/journal.pone.0083147&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Regulatory traits: Cultural Influences on Cultural Evolution</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/cp_2014_regulatory/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/cp_2014_regulatory/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Robustness of emotion extraction from 20th century English books</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/cp_2013_emotion/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/cp_2013_emotion/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fashion vs. Function in Cultural Evolution: The Case of Dog Breed Popularity</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2013_plos_a/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2013_plos_a/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The expression of emotions in 20th century books</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2013_plos_b/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2013_plos_b/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/alberto-acerbi/human-emotion-books-history_b_3084869.html&#34;&gt;popular summary&lt;/a&gt; of the paper for the &lt;em&gt;Huffington Post&lt;/em&gt; (US edition). Other media coverage includes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/news/text-mining-uncovers-british-reserve-and-us-emotion-1.12642&#34;&gt;Text mining uncovers British reserve and US emotion&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://artsbeat.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/03/25/fold-up-your-handkerchiefs-books-have-gotten-less-emotional-study-says/?mtrref=undefined&amp;amp;gwh=C9D8521D01CC2505709A530FCDC5B87D&amp;amp;gwt=pay&amp;amp;assetType=REGIWALL&#34;&gt;Fold Up Your Handkerchiefs: Books Have Gotten Less &amp;lsquo;Emotional&amp;rsquo;, Study Says&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The New York Times&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ricerca.repubblica.it/repubblica/archivio/repubblica/2013/03/21/aiuto-nostri-romanzi-hanno-perso-le-emozioni.html&#34;&gt;Aiuto, i nostri romanzi hanno perso le emozioni&lt;/a&gt; (in Italian), &lt;em&gt;La Repubblica&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A radio interview for BBC &lt;em&gt;Material World&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b01r9sl7&#34;&gt;Planck, Elusive Giant Squid, Emotive words&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;script id=&#34;altmetric-embed-js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1371/journal.pone.0059030&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Old and Young Individuals’ Role in Cultural Change</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2012_jasss/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2012_jasss/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Emergence of Leadership in a Group of Autonomous Robots</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/cp_2012_leadership/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/cp_2012_leadership/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Behavioral constraints and the evolution of faithful social learning</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2012_cur_zoo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Apr 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2012_cur_zoo/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Logic of Fashion Cycles</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2012_plos/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Mar 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2012_plos/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Regulatory Traits in Cultural Evolution</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/cp_2012_regulatory/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Feb 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/cp_2012_regulatory/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modeling imitation and emulation in constrained search spaces</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2011_learn_behav/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2011_learn_behav/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predation and the phasing of sleep: an evolutionary individual-based model</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2011_an_behav/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2011_an_behav/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Sometimes Evitable Route to Conservatism and Persuasiveness. A Reply to Xue and Costopoulos</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2010_cur_anthr/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2010_cur_anthr/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Umano troppo umano. Riflessioni sull’opposizione natura/cultura in antropologia</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/ita_2009_umano/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Nov 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/ita_2009_umano/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cultural evolution and individual development of openness and conservatism</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2009_pnas/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2009_pnas/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Orienting learning by exploiting sociality: an evolutionary robotics simulations</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/cp_2009_orienting/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/cp_2009_orienting/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modelli evoluzionistici della cultura</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/ita_2009_rifl/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/ita_2009_rifl/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Naturalmente differenti. Spiegazioni naturalistiche e variabilità culturale</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/ita_2009_differenti/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/ita_2009_differenti/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trasmissione sociale di comportamenti in una popolazione di robot autonomi</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/ita_2008_si/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Aug 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/ita_2008_si/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Social learning in embodied agents</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2008_conn_sci/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jun 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2008_conn_sci/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I edited, together with Davide Marocco and Paul Vogt, a double special issue of the journal &lt;em&gt;Connection Science&lt;/em&gt; on the topic &amp;ldquo;Social Learning in Embodied Agents&amp;rdquo;. This is our editorial.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>To sleep or not to sleep: the ecology of sleep in artificial organisms</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2008_bmc/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Jun 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2008_bmc/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Le trasmissioni della cultura</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/ita_2008_trasmissioni/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/ita_2008_trasmissioni/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>La natura della cultura. Modelli simulativi dell&#39;apprendimento sociale</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/ita_2007_phd/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Nov 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/ita_2007_phd/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Social Facilitation on the Development of Foraging Behaviors in a Population of Autonomous Robots</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/cp_2007_social/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Sep 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/cp_2007_social/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The evolution of pain</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/cp_2007_pain/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Sep 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/cp_2007_pain/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Social Learning and Cultural Evolution in Embodied and Situated Agents</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/cp_2007_embodied/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Apr 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/cp_2007_embodied/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adaptation and Social Facilitation in a Population of Autonomous Robots</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/cp_2007_adaptation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/cp_2007_adaptation/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cultural transmission between and within generations</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2006_jasss/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/2006_jasss/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Antropologia cognitiva e modularità della mente: il caso della folkbiology</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/ita_2006_folkbio/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/ita_2006_folkbio/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trasmissibilità culturale di tratti discreti e continui</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/ita_2006_aisc/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/ita_2006_aisc/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Antropologia cognitiva: uno stato dell&#39;arte</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/ita_2005_si/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Dec 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/ita_2005_si/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Esiste una folkanthropology? E, se esiste, a chi interessa?</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/ita_2005_folkanthro/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/ita_2005_folkanthro/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>La mente nella cultura: cognizione ed analisi dei fatti culturali</title>
      <link>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/ita_2005_annali/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://acerbialberto.com/publication/ita_2005_annali/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
